<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ clavium: or, A vindication of the keyes of the kingdome of Heaven, into the hands of the right owners. Being some animadversions upon a tract of Mr. I.C. called, The keyes of the kingdome of Heaven. As also upon another tract of his, called, The way of the churches of Nevv-England. Manifesting; 1. The weaknesse of his proofes. 2. The contradictions to himselfe, and others. 3. The middle-way (so called) of Independents, to be the extreme, or by-way of the Brownists. / By an earnest well-wisher to the truth.</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E299_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861053</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E299[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ clavium: or, A vindication of the keyes of the kingdome of Heaven, into the hands of the right owners. Being some animadversions upon a tract of Mr. I.C. called, The keyes of the kingdome of Heaven. As also upon another tract of his, called, The way of the churches of Nevv-England. Manifesting; 1. The weaknesse of his proofes. 2. The contradictions to himselfe, and others. 3. The middle-way (so called) of Independents, to be the extreme, or by-way of the Brownists. / By an earnest well-wisher to the truth.</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 90, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H. for Peter Whaley, and are to be sold in Ivy-Lane, at the signe of the Gun.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An earnest well-wisher to the truth = Daniel Cawdrey.</note>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "The keyes of the kingdom of Heaven" (Wing C6437), and "The way of the churches of Christ in New-England" (Wing C6471), both by John Cotton.</note>
                  <note>Variant: page 90 misnumbered 96.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7bre 4th" [i.e. September 4th].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cotton, John, 1584-1652. --  Keyes of the kingdom of Heaven --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cotton, John, 1584-1652. --  Way of the churches of Christ in New-England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:1"/>
            <p>I Have diligently peruſed this Treatiſe, (called <hi>Vindiciae Clavium</hi>) and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the judicious Authour hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly performed what he undertakes, I cannot but conceive it will conduce very much to the ending of our Vnchriſtian Contentions concerning Church-Government, the ſetling of ſome that waver, and reclaiming of ſome that are miſ-lead, and appoſe</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IA. CRANFORD,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 4, 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VINDICIAE CLAVIVM:</p>
            <p>OR, A Vindication of the KEYES of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven,</hi> into the hands of the right Owners.</p>
            <p>Being ſome <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon a <hi>Tract</hi> of Mr. <hi>I. C.</hi> called, <hi>The Keyes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo upon another Tract of his, called, <hi>The way of the Churches of</hi> NEVV-ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Manifeſting;
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The</hi> weakneſſe <hi>of his proofes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The</hi> Contradictions <hi>to himſelfe, and others</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The</hi> Middle-way <hi>(ſo called) of Independents, to be the</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, <hi>or</hi> By-way <hi>of the Browniſts.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By an earneſt well-wiſher to the <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IER. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl> Stand ye in the wayes, ſee and aske for the old pathes, where is the good way, and walke therein.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T.H.</hi> for <hi>Peter Whaley,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Ivy-Lane,</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Gun.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true, which the <hi>Prefacers</hi> to the <hi>Tract,</hi> called, <hi>The way of the Churches of Chriſt in New-England,</hi> do ſay, That we have long called for <hi>a fuller Declaration</hi> of themſelves. For all that hath as yet bin publiſhed, hath not ſatisfied our expectation, Nor do we think them able to ſatisfie any unprejudiced man. The <hi>32. Queſtions,</hi> The <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> The <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the diſſenting Brethren, The <hi>way of the Churches,</hi> &amp;c. Now by them publiſhed, have all been anſwered; which yet theſe <hi>Brethren</hi> take no notice of. The <hi>Keyes</hi> are now in queſtion, in the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; how well they doe fit the words in <hi>The way</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed, or how ſutable they are to the parties allowed to weare them. There is one thing very ſuſpicious, That the <hi>Brethren</hi> doe not agree among themſelves, in the
<pb facs="tcp:113181:3"/> uſe and application of them: For thoſe two Brethren tell us in their Epiſtle, <hi>That they hold with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of New-England,</hi> yet it is evident they agree not with their Author, in <hi>The way:</hi> For they profeſſe, <hi>That they doe not yet fully cloſe with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, paſsim,</hi> (frequent) <hi>in the Booke, before ſome of which,</hi> (belike there are more) <hi>they min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, to note a Star in the Margin. This they could not but ſay and doe</hi> (pace tanti Authoris) <hi>or they could not aſſert the Booke.</hi> And will this ſatisfie any indifferent Reader? In the <hi>Title</hi> page, they promiſe us a <hi>full declaration of the Church-way in all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</hi> But in the ſecond page of their Epiſtle, they tell us, <hi>They doe not cloſe with ſome expreſsions in the Book;</hi> And there are no leſſe than ten Stars affixed in the margine of the Booke; wherein they intimate, <hi>they cannot aſſert the Booke.</hi> Of the ſame minde are the other two <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. p. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Prefacers</hi> to the <hi>Keyes;</hi> and that not in bare expreſsions, but in Doctrinall aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. How ſhould ſuch Tracts ſatisfie us, when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not ſatisfied? And no marv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, for thoſe <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> in their <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> doe (wiſely) profeſſe, they <hi>keep a reſerve open,</hi> to alter their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, upon occaſion of <hi>New-light.</hi> Beſides this, its evident, that the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> does directly
<pb facs="tcp:113181:3"/> contradict the <hi>Authour,</hi> of <hi>The way,</hi> that is, <hi>himſelf,</hi> which, when I have pleaded to ſome friends of his, I have been told, that he hath altered his judgement, ſince he writ <hi>The way,</hi> in many particulars. I have heard indeed he hath often altered his judgement ſince he went to <hi>New-England:</hi> But I cannot well beleeve it in this; becauſe the <hi>Prefacers</hi> to <hi>The way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> bring us his owne words, in a Letter newly written, comming to their hands, when their Epiſtle was in the Preſſe; wherein he affirmes, <hi>That there is not a jot of difference in any Doctrine of Divinity, or Church practiſe. So Mr.</hi> Cotton, <hi>in his Letter to Mr.</hi> R.M. If it be true, that he hath altered his opinion ſince he writ <hi>the Way,</hi> they have done him wrong to publiſh it, after the <hi>Keyes,</hi> wherein the alteration is; If he have not, they would be requeſted to reconcile him to himſelfe. For I find he doth as flatly contradict himſelfe, as ever any man did. I will inſtance but in one place (and leave the rest to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe.) In the <hi>Keyes,</hi> page <hi>4.</hi> he ſayes, <hi>The Keyes were delivered to</hi> Peter, <hi>as an Apoſtle, as an Elder, and as a Beleever.</hi> The ſenſe of the words <hi>(ſayes he)</hi> will be moſt full, if all the ſeverall conſiderations be taken joyntly together. But in <hi>The way,</hi> page <hi>27,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>The power of the Keyes is given to the Church, to</hi> Peter, <hi>not as an Apoſtle, not as an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb facs="tcp:113181:4"/> but as a profeſt Beleever, in the name of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, &amp;c.</hi> Is not this a flat contradiction? and yet the <hi>Prefacers</hi> ſeeme to approve it, for they ſet no Starre in the margine. I ſhall leave it to them to reconcile. How juſtly then may we call for a <hi>fuller Declaration?</hi> and how unjuſtly doe the <hi>Brethren</hi> quarrell us for calling for it?<note place="margin">Ep. p. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Doe not they themſelves promiſe us yet a <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Treatiſe of the ſame Subject, with amplier de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, by joynt conſent of the Churches of Old and New-England?</hi> Thats it that we expect, the <hi>joynt-conſent</hi> of the Churches and Brethren; for their <hi>inconſtancy,</hi> and <hi>difference</hi> in judgement, hath cauſed, as our <hi>non-ſatisfaction,</hi> ſo our juſt <hi>lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> That they ſhould rend a <hi>poore-rent-already-Church</hi> into peeces, by ſetting up the practiſe of a <hi>New way,</hi> and not be agreed of the platforme whereby they practiſe. There are (as I touched before) no leſſe then ten ſeverall Stars, affixed by theſe <hi>Brethren;</hi> wherein, <hi>I</hi> ſhould conceive, they differ from their <hi>Authour</hi> (if not their <hi>Maſter</hi>) not in bare <hi>expreſsions</hi> but in the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> there delivered, as page <hi>45. VVhether the Church hath power</hi> to proceed againſt all her Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, if they be culpable in hereticall Doctrine, or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous crime: The <hi>Authour</hi> holds the affirmative; they ſeeme to hold the Negative. Againe, <hi>page 53. VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:113181:4"/> a Church may conſiſt of leſſe than ſeven,</hi> p. <hi>55: VVhether confeſsion of ſinnes, and profeſsion of faith be neceſſary for a member admitted,</hi> page <hi>68. VVhether ſitting at the Sacrament, have a Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall uſe (made by Chriſt himſelfe) to teach the Church their Majority over their Miniſters in ſome caſes, &amp;c</hi> In theſe and the reſt, we are unſatisfied, and theſe Brethren may doe well to declare their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their <hi>fuller Treatiſe</hi> promiſed. This diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt themſelves, is prejudicious to their cauſe and way, to thoſe that are judicious, that are not ſworn to the words of any Maſter, but Chriſt; much more, when the ſame perſon is not at agreement with himſelf; which, if it be not the <hi>caſe</hi> of the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>Keyes, I</hi> referre to the judgement of the <hi>indifferent Reader,</hi> when he hath read the following Diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:5"/>
            <head>Animadverſions upon the Brethrens Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is indeed the great <hi>controverſie</hi> of the times, <hi>[What is the compleat ſubject of Church power, or the power of the Keyes.]</hi> Theſe <hi>Brethren</hi> ſay, (perhaps truly) that the <hi>Truth</hi> herein hath been long loſt in a double <hi>extreme:</hi> The one was the <hi>tyranny</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (ſo called) or rather of the <hi>Prelacy,</hi> who ingroſſed all, or the chiefe part of that power unto themſelves, not only from the people, but alſo from the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. The other is, the <hi>Anarchy</hi> or popularity of the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> or <hi>Browniſts,</hi> (as they after call them) who gave the people a place and claime to the whole power, and made the <hi>Elders</hi> ſet over them; but their ſervants to exerciſe that power which was properly theirs.</p>
            <p>Probable it is, that <hi>Truth</hi> may lye in the <hi>middle,</hi> between theſe two <hi>extremes;</hi> but how to find it out, is not ſo eaſie. Our <hi>Brethren</hi> goe about it; but, me thinks they doe not hit it: They ſay, [<hi>The Saints</hi> (in theſe knowing Times) <hi>fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the Key of knowledge hath ſo far opened their hearts, that they ſee with their owne eyes into the ſubſtantials of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They doe begin more than to ſuſpect, that ſome ſhare in the Key of power ſhould likewiſe appertaine unto them]</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113181:5"/> Truly juſt one as much as another: The <hi>Brethren</hi> ſuppoſe the <hi>Saints</hi> have a ſhare in the <hi>Key of Knowledge;</hi> when they ſay, they ſuſpect they have likewiſe a ſhare in the <hi>Key of power.</hi> But firſt, they have no ſhare in the <hi>Key of knowledge,</hi> (which is, <hi>preaching and adminiſtration of the Seales,</hi> as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour ſpeaks) except <hi>paſsively,</hi> as to <hi>have their hearts opened by it</hi> (as the <hi>Brethrens</hi> words are:) So, nor have they any ſhare in the <hi>Key of power,</hi> except it be by a voluntary <hi>[conſent, in obedience to the Will and Rule of Chriſt]</hi> as the Authour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeaks, <hi>page</hi> 15. And divers times elſewhere, as we ſhall heare; [<hi>even an orderly ſubjection, according to the Order of the Goſpell,</hi> page 11.] Though the truth is, ſome have taken more upon them than to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> they have a ſhare, even to <hi>practiſe</hi> the <hi>Key of power,</hi> and that <hi>[through the inſtruction and guidance of their Teachers;]</hi> which, how little it comes ſhort of the plea and practiſe of the other <hi>extreme,</hi> ſhall ere long appeare. For the preſent: Theſe <hi>Brethren</hi> ſay, they conceive <hi>[the diſpoſall of this power may lye in a due allotment into divers hands, according to their ſeverall concernments, rather than in an entire and ſole truſt committed to any one man, or any one ſort, or ranke of men, or Officers.]</hi> Herein perhaps we might agree with them: But I am ſure they agree not with their Authour herein, who places all the <hi>power</hi> in one ſort of men alone; that is,<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 45.</note> the <hi>Brethren without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> and gives them leave <hi>[to elect ordaine Officers, admit members, and paſſe Church cenſures without any Officers, yea, to cenſure all their Officers.]</hi> though, we thinke, he contradicts himſelfe in this Tract of the <hi>Keyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Brethren tell us, The Authour (to whom they Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face) takes upon him to diſtribute the bounds of this power. And layes downe this as a maxime; [<hi>That looke in whoſe hands ſoever it fall, they have it immediately from Chriſt;</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:113181:6"/> is, <hi>in regard of delegation or dependance on each other.</hi>] And thus farre we doe not diſſent: <hi>[He then</hi> (ſay they) <hi>conſiders the power of a Congregation; which ſuppoſing to have a Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of its owne, he aſſerteth to be the prime ſubject of entire power within it ſelfe yea, and the ſole native ſubject of the power of Ordination and Excommunication.]</hi> But 1. he needed not to have made ſuch a ſuppoſition, that the Congregation hath a Presbytery of its owne:<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 50, 51.</note> For if they have no Presbytery of their owne, he aſſerteth, that <hi>they have the power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Excommunication,</hi> which is the higheſt cenſure within themſelves; and <hi>[want a Warrant to repaire to the Preſbytery of another Church for either.]</hi> 2. Both he and theſe Brethren know, that this is denyed by many, who make the firſt Subject of all Church-power to be the <hi>generall viſible Church,</hi> and ſecondarily the Congregation, though having a Presbytery of its owne: As a man is the firſt ſubject of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, <hi>Peter,</hi> but at ſecond hand. The Congregation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Elders and Brethren; <hi>[For as for women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, there is a ſpeciall exception by a Statute Law of Chriſt, againſt their enjoyment of any part of this publicke power]</hi> (ſay the Brethren) which I ſee no reaſon for, in regard of ſome part of this power, (as we ſhall ſee anon) the Authour labours to ſhare the intereſt and power between the Elders and the Brethren. And he manifeſts it (ſay they) by way of a parallell. <hi>[As in ſome of our Townes corporate, the power is given to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Aldermen the Rulers and a Common Councell, a Body of the people.]</hi> But I pray obſerve the <hi>diſsimilitude</hi> in this <hi>ſimilitude:</hi> His maine deſigne is, to give the people a ſhare in the <hi>Church power</hi> of Government: But then the parallell will not run even. For the Company of Aldermen, and the Common-Councell, are both Rulers of the Corporation, though in ſeverall ranks and ſubordination: But I ſuppoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:113181:6"/> neither the Authour, nor the Brethren, can truly ſay, the whole company of the people are Rulers in the Church, as the Common-Councell is in the Corporation. If all the people be Rulers, who are the <hi>ruled?</hi> In the City there are multitudes of people, ſubject to the Company of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Common-Councell; but here are all <hi>Governours,</hi> or <hi>governed.</hi> The parallell were fairely laid thus; The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Aldermen, reſemble the Paſtors and Teachers; The Common-Councell, the Ruling-Elders (Officers of another ranke;) The Citizens beſides thoſe, the Brethren out of Office, in the Congregation. Thus all things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond well. But they make the Presbytery to be the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, and the whole Body of the people to be the Common-Councell; which ſure they are not, what ever they ſay; for then the diſtinction of <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>ruled</hi> is loſt: And this appeares clearly in his application of this ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <hi>[He gives to the Elders or Preſbytery, a binding power of Rule and Authority; unto the Brethren, a power to concurre with them; and that ſuch affaires ſhould not be tranſacted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a joynt-agreement of both.]</hi> What power? ſuch as the Common-Councell hath in the Corporation? thats more than a bare priviledge; thats a power of Rule and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a binding power, concurring with the Aldermen; But they ſhould have ſaid: Not the Common-Councell, but the Common people of a City, have ſuch a power to concurre with the Aldermen, that ſuch affaires be not tranſacted, but with their joynt-agreement. But this they cannot ſay, and then the parallell will not hold, unleſſe they change the Common-people for the Common-Councell, thus. As the people of a City only cannot proceed to any publicke ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, unleſſe they have Aldermen over them: ſo, nor have the Aldermen power to ſentence without the concurrence
<pb facs="tcp:113181:7"/> of the people, which is apparently falſe. The parallell muſt be thus: As the <hi>Brethren</hi> only cannot proceed to any publick cenſure without their <hi>Elders:</hi> ſo, nor have the <hi>Elders</hi> power to cenſure without the concurrence of the <hi>Brethren;</hi> which is as falſe as the former. Indeed theſe are very parallell: As on the one ſide, the Common-Councell cannot doe any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid act, without the Aldermen; nor the Aldermen, without the Common-Councell, (unleſſe there be ſome reſerved caſes) ſo, as the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> cannot cenſure without the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> ſo nor the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> without the <hi>Ruling-Elders;</hi> but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the Brethren, is (as in the City, if ſo it were) to make the <hi>Government</hi> popular, as thoſe doe, that are in the one <hi>extreme,</hi> or I underſtand nothing. And then, the laſt clauſe of the Brethren, is to be paralleld thus: As the Common-Councell have not power of cenſuring the whole Court of Aldermen; nor the Aldermen, the whole Common-Councell, though together they have power over any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon or perſons of each: ſo the Presbytery alone, have not power of excommunicating the whole Body of the Brethren; nor the Brethren, the Presbytery, though to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether they have power over any perſon in each: But then thers one thing wanting; The Aldermen and Common-Councell have power over all the people of the City, as well as over particular perſons amongſt themſelves. But in theſe Brethrens way; There are no other people, over which the Presbytery and Brethren ſhould have power; and ſo the <hi>Scene</hi> is miſlaid. I only note againe, That the Brethren and the Authour are not both of one mind: They ſay, [<hi>The Brethren only could not proceed to any publick cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, without they have Elders over them, nor</hi> retrò:] But whether he ſay, <hi>[The Elders have power to cenſure the Body of the Brethren]</hi> or no, we ſhall heare anon; this I am ſure
<pb facs="tcp:113181:7"/> he ſayes:<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 45:</note> 
               <hi>[The Brethren have power to cenſure the whole Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery;]</hi> as was noted afore.</p>
            <p>The next thing which they <hi>comment</hi> on, is the power of <hi>Synods,</hi> becauſe Congregations may miſcarry. <hi>[Wherein</hi> (ſay they) <hi>he grants an Aſſociation of Churches, as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, with power above that of a Congregation, a Miniſteriall power, to determine and enjoyne things concerning the Congregations.]</hi> The words are full and faire, but the ſenſe is flat and empty: For all this power of <hi>determining</hi> and enjoyning, is but <hi>Doctrinall,</hi> or <hi>declarative,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Every Miniſter hath in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, alone, a Miniſteriall Doctrinall Authority, over the whole Church that is his charge, and every perſon in it, <hi>Ep. p.</hi> 9.</note> differing nothing in kind from the power of every ſingle <hi>Paſtor,</hi> but in degree of weight, as a <hi>greater Teſtimony;</hi> as three cords twiſted together, are ſtronger than each of them ſingle. A power not binding or looſing, but <hi>doctrinally</hi> only, not armed with power of <hi>cenſures,</hi> if <hi>injunctions</hi> be not obeyed. But if this power of the <hi>Synod,</hi> be not <hi>juridicall,</hi> what is it? All power in thoſe <hi>Paſtors</hi> thus aſſembled as an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt, is either a power of <hi>Order,</hi> or of <hi>juriſdiction:</hi> The power of <hi>determining</hi> or <hi>decrecing</hi> together, is not the power of <hi>Order;</hi> for then every <hi>Paſtor,</hi> quâ <hi>Paſtor,</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his <hi>Order,</hi> might <hi>decree</hi> and impoſe it upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: which is denyed by all; Therefore it muſt be a power of <hi>juriſdiction;</hi> which yet theſe Brethren, and their Authour doe deny. And if it be not armed with power of <hi>cenſure,</hi> it will come to nothing; as ſhall appeare hereafter. For as for their <hi>withdrawing communion,</hi> it will be little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by an offending obſtinate Congregation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Brethren Epiſtolers</hi> now begin to applaud themſelves as <hi>jumping</hi> in judgement with their Authour, though ſo farre remote as <hi>New-England</hi> (But men agree in errour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that never knew one another.) Their <hi>middle way,</hi> is this very way held forth by this Authour: Yet they ſay after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb facs="tcp:113181:8"/> in ſome things, in his Diſcourſe, <hi>Hic Magiſter non te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur.</hi> They ſay, [<hi>It is the middle way, between that which is called Browniſme, and the Preſbyteriall Government, as it is practiſed,</hi> &amp;c.] But if they remember themſelves well, the two <hi>extremes</hi> were <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Browniſme: [Whereof the one doth in effect put the chiefe (if not the whole) of the Rule and Government into the hands of the people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The other taking the principall parts of that Rule (the due of each Congregation) into the juriſdiction of a common Preſbytery of ſeverall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions</hi> &amp;c.] I appeale their <hi>wiſedome,</hi> if the latter part doe not better fall upon the <hi>Prelacy;</hi> who in the other <hi>extreme,</hi> tooke the principall parts of <hi>Rule</hi> (due in part to the Paſtors of Congregations) into their owne hands. Then the <hi>middle way,</hi> may chance fall out to be the <hi>Preſbyteriall way,</hi> and not theirs. For certainly, that is between thoſe two <hi>extremes.</hi> And <hi>their way,</hi> I dare ſay, (and hope to make it appeare) comes nearer to <hi>Browniſme,</hi> than the <hi>Preſbyteriall way,</hi> to the <hi>Prelaticall.</hi> For the preſent, only marke; That the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall way,</hi> gives the power of Church Government; neither to the <hi>Clergy</hi> alone, as the <hi>Prelacy,</hi> nor to the people alone, or chiefly, as the <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe, but to both. For the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries</hi> (Claſſicall as well as Congregationall) conſiſt of <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Ruling Elders,</hi> who are the Repreſentatives of the people, and choſen by their conſent. But to give the Brethren, the people alone, without Officers, a power, to elect, ordaine, cenſure, &amp;c. (as the Authour doth, whatever theſe Brethren doe) is to put, not only the <hi>chiefe</hi> (as <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe) but the <hi>whole</hi> of the <hi>Rule</hi> into their hands: which, for ought I know, the <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe not. Nor doth the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> ſwallow up the peoples <hi>intereſts,</hi> (as they affirme) for their <hi>intereſt</hi> is ſaved, in their <hi>Ruling-Elders,</hi> choſen by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; as the <hi>intereſt</hi> of the common people of a Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb facs="tcp:113181:8"/> is ſaved in their Common-Councell, choſen by themſelves. And that the <hi>votes</hi> of the <hi>Elders</hi> of that Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation concerned, ſhould be ſwallowed up in the <hi>Claſsis,</hi> &amp;c. is no more abſurd, than that the <hi>votes</hi> of the Burgeſſe of a Corporation, ſhould be ſwallowed up in the Parliament; or that the <hi>votes</hi> of the <hi>Elders</hi> ſhould be ſwallowed up in a <hi>Synod,</hi> confeſſed to be the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt; unleſſe the Brethren thinke, a <hi>Synod</hi> may not <hi>determine</hi> or <hi>decree</hi> any thing without the joynt-conſent of every <hi>Elder</hi> there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled.</p>
            <p>After all this agreement of the Brethren, with this abſent Authour, (to a <hi>wonder,</hi> if not to a <hi>miracle,</hi> as they would have us thinke, though we beleeve they were not ſtrangers to the plot of this Authour, either before or ſince his going over) they enter their <hi>diſſent,</hi> againſt ſome opinions and paſſages of this Authour, in the platforme by him deſcribed. I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not here to <hi>debate,</hi> much leſſe to decide the <hi>controverſie</hi> between them. I only deſire to have it obſerved, That it may rather ſeeme a <hi>wonder,</hi> that theſe and other Brethren, having ſo long ſtudied and profeſſed this <hi>middle way,</hi> ſhould not yet be able to walke hand in hand therein. When will they be agreed, that we may ſee their <hi>new platforme</hi> to be <hi>uniforme?</hi> One of them muſt needs be beſide the way, and why may not both? But we ſhall obſerve greater <hi>differences</hi> than theſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>They now againe reſume the difference between the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples intereſt, and the <hi>Elders Rule</hi> and Authority; and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it by the former ſimilitude, <hi>[Of a Company of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and a Common-Councell, or Body of the people, in ſome Corporations, where the intereſt of the one is diſtinct from the other; ſo as without the concurrence of both, nothing is eſteemed as a City act:] But ſo as in this Company of the Elders, this
<pb facs="tcp:113181:9"/> power is properly Authority, but in the people is a priviledge or power.]</hi> Enough hath been ſaid to this already: Only I would know why they call the Common-Councell a Body of the people? Sure they doe not know any Corporations, I thinke, where the whole Corporation meets with the Aldermen, as a Body. The Common-Councell are a diſtinct Body from the common-people; a Body <hi>repreſentative</hi> only. But then the parallell is ſpoiled; for the <hi>Brethren</hi> as diſtinct from the <hi>Elders,</hi> are not a <hi>repreſentative</hi> Body, for whom ſhould they repreſent? And if all the people of a corporation ſhould meet as the Common-Councell, ſo that nothing may be eſteemed as a City Act, without their concurrence; Surely the <hi>Government</hi> were <hi>Democraticall:</hi> The great miſtake in the plot is; That the Presbytery is compared to the Court of Aldermen, and the Brethren to the Common-Councell. But ſo they are not; for the Common-Councell are <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of the Corporation. It cannot be ſaid, in the Company of Aldermen it is Authority, but in the Common-Councell a <hi>priviledge;</hi> for it is Authority alſo in the Common-Councell; and if it be ſo in the Brethren (as it muſt, if they be parallell to the Common-Councell) I ſee not but the <hi>Independent way,</hi> and the way of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> one of the <hi>extremes</hi> forementioned, is one and the ſame. And let the <hi>Brethren</hi> conſider,<note place="margin">The multitude of the Church doth ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly execute all diſcipline and cenſures by the Presbyters; &amp; the Presbyters by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 98.</note> whether the <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe not ſelect two or three, or more perſons, and put them in <hi>Office,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt them with an entire <hi>intereſt</hi> of power for a multitude, to which that multitude ought (by a command from Chriſt) to be ſubject and obedient, as to an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> to guide them in their conſent; and in whoſe ſentence, the <hi>ultimate formall Miniſteriall Act</hi> of binding and looſing ſhall conſiſt; and yet place the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> originally and chiefly in the people; And then ſee how little difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb facs="tcp:113181:9"/> themſelves, and them. Its true indeed, that without the concurrence of the Aldermen and Common Councell, in the major part, nothing is eſteemed as a City Act: But without the concurrence of the <hi>body</hi> of the people it is. So without the concurrence of the <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> nothing is to be eſteemed as a Church act; but (if the parallell be right) without the Brethren it is. That the <hi>Brethren</hi> have any power of concurrence with the <hi>Elders</hi> in their Acts, is begged, not proved. And their owne words confute it: <hi>[The multitude</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ought (by a command from Chriſt) to be ſubject and obedient to the power of the Elders, as to an Ordinance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as Rulers ſet over them:]</hi> But if they ought to be ſubject and obedient to the acts of their Elders or Rulers, they have no more concurrence to their acts by way of <hi>power,</hi> than the common people have to the acts of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Common-Councell; which is a meere <hi>paſsive</hi> concurrence and conſent.</p>
            <p>The next ſimilitude of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> is nothing parallell to the caſe in hand. <hi>[A Virgin</hi> (ſay they) <hi>hath a power ultimately to diſſent, upon an unſatisfied diſlike, and the match is not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, without her conſent.]</hi> But the common people in a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, have no ſuch power <hi>ultimately</hi> to diſſent (then againe the Government were <hi>Democraticall.</hi>) And if they give this power to the Brethren <hi>ultimately</hi> to diſſent; they give them more than an <hi>intereſt,</hi> even a power of <hi>Authority,</hi> to annull all acts and cenſures made by the Elders; which, I take it, is no leſſe than <hi>Browniſme;</hi> for they can ſay no more.</p>
            <p>Againe, they ſuppoſe <hi>[a Government tempered of Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy and Democracy, in which the people have a ſhare, and their actuall conſent is necceſſary to all Lawes and ſentences; whereas, a few Nobles that are ſet over them, in whom the formall
<pb facs="tcp:113181:10"/> ſanction of all ſhould lye, in theſe it were Rule and Authority, in that multitude, but power or intereſt.]</hi> But I pray, is not that <hi>Government,</hi> where the peoples <hi>actuall conſent</hi> (and ſo their diſſent) is neceſſary to all Lawes and ſentences, <hi>meerely po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular,</hi> and in ſhew only <hi>Ariſtocraticall?</hi> The caſe is juſt the <hi>Browniſts:</hi> Their Church ſeemes to be tempered of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy</hi> in their ſelect <hi>Officers,</hi> choſen and ordained by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as yours are) and <hi>Democracy</hi> in the body of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But they granting the peoples <hi>actuall conſent</hi> (and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) neceſſary to all Acts and ſentences, ſwallow up the <hi>votes</hi> of the <hi>Elders,</hi> and ſo their Government is wholly or chiefly popular. Give ſuch a power to the people (as you doe) and I will uſe your owne words: <hi>[All that is ſaid in the New Teſtament about the Rule of the Elders, and the peoples obedience to them, is to be lookt upon, but as Metaphors, and to hold no proportion with any ſubſtantiall reality of Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Brethren, to make their way more plauſible, ſhew a reaſon of the difference between the <hi>Times</hi> of the Old and New Teſtament. [<hi>Then the Church was in her Nonage; and therefore the ſole power of all Church-matters, was in their Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Governours: But now the Church is out of her Nonage, and more generally able, being viſible Saints (as they ſhould be) to joyne with their guides,</hi> &amp;c.] But they forget themſelves preſently, confeſſing, <hi>[the weakneſſe and unskilfulneſſe of the people (for the generality of them) in compariſon of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, gifted for the Government: He hath therefore placed a Rule and Authority in thoſe Officers over them, not directing only, but binding; ſo as not only nothing ſhould be done without them, but not eſteemed validly done, unleſſe done by them.]</hi> Now I pray, was it any more in the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church of the Old Teſtament? were not they to be viſible <hi>Saints?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113181:10"/> were not their <hi>Guides</hi> gifted for that purpoſe, ſutable to thoſe <hi>Times?</hi> And I thinke the <hi>Browniſts</hi> may grant them thus much: Their <hi>Officers</hi> are but the Churches ſervants, and yet they ſay nothing may (in an ordinary way of Church-Government) be done without them, nor validly done, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe done by them. But I marvell they ſhould call the power of the <hi>Elders</hi> a binding power, when as they ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>[The Elders had no power to cenſure without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the people, as nor the people without the Elders]</hi> which is juſt the ſame which <hi>Browniſts</hi> ſay.</p>
            <p>Nor can this <hi>ballancing</hi> of the power prevent <hi>Anarchie</hi> (what ever it may doe, <hi>Tyranny</hi>) for certainly if the peoples conſent and concurrence be neceſſary to every Church-act, its an eaſie thing for them to bring in <hi>Anarchy,</hi> being alwaies the greater number, and ſo to ſwallow up the votes of the <hi>Elders,</hi> as <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe.</p>
            <p>That Miniſteriall <hi>Doctrinall Authority</hi> ſhould be ſevered from the power of <hi>excommunication,</hi> in ſome parties, we never doubted; becauſe <hi>excommunication</hi> is an act of <hi>juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> which is common to many; but <hi>Doctrinall Authority</hi> is an affluxe of <hi>Order.</hi> But to ſever Rule and Authority from the power of concurrence to excommunication and cenſures, (as they doe in the people) is a meer nullity of Rule and Authority too.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>power of excommunication</hi> ſhould be inſeparably linked to a Congregation; they would faine <hi>illuſtrate</hi> by a knowne compariſon; As the cuſtome is in our Land, <hi>[The ſentencing of a man to death, is not by Lawyers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor by Iudges alone, but by his Peeres, a Iury of men like himſelfe.]</hi> Their <hi>ſimilitude</hi> ſtill halts on the maine legge: For who are the <hi>Iudges</hi> with them, but the <hi>Preſbytery?</hi> and who are the <hi>Iury,</hi> but all the <hi>Brethren?</hi> But this is not ſo in a Corporation:
<pb facs="tcp:113181:11"/> All the City are not the Delinquents <hi>Peeres,</hi> but a <hi>ſelect do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> of men. Now ſuppoſe a man be accuſed as an <hi>offender</hi> in a <hi>Corporation;</hi> ſhall the <hi>whole City</hi> be his <hi>Peeres</hi> or <hi>Iury,</hi> to try him? have they any ſuch <hi>intereſt</hi> or priviledge? is their conſent or diſſent regarded? So the parallell required. If a brother deſerve cenſure, he ſhall not be judged by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors</hi> alone, or with the <hi>Elders,</hi> choſen by the people (as his <hi>Iury</hi>) for the <hi>Government</hi> of the Congregation; but all the people are to be his <hi>Peeres</hi> or <hi>Iury:</hi> This were ſtrange to ſee in a City, and would breed nothing but <hi>Anarchy</hi> and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. So in the Church:</p>
            <p>That Chriſt hath not betruſted a <hi>generall Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Elders,</hi> with that power he hath done the Congregation, is begged, not proved. The reaſon is invalid: <hi>[Becauſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>they are abſtracted from the people.]</hi> But thats not true; for the people are there <hi>repreſentatively</hi> in their <hi>Elders,</hi> who are able to repreſent the caſe of the offender, with all the circumſtances, as fully as if all the people were there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt (ſay they) <hi>[would have this Tribe of men (the brethren perſonally concurring, not by delegation alone, not to the execution only; but even to the legall ſentence alſo of cutting men off:]</hi> This is all begged, and is the queſtion. And it is, as if they ſhould ſay (in the parallell inſtance) God would have all the Corporation perſonally concurring to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſentence, or cutting off a malefactor, not by delegation only (as the <hi>Iury</hi> doe) nor to the execution only; which were a ſtrange confuſion. So that, as at the <hi>Aſsizes,</hi> the multitude of the people preſent, have no concurrence to the legall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, &amp;c. but the <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Iury</hi> only: ſo the <hi>Brethren</hi> are to have no concurrence to the legall ſentence of <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> (except to yeeld <hi>obedience</hi> in the execution) but the
<pb facs="tcp:113181:11"/> 
               <hi>Elders</hi> only: and ſo the parallell is full.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, if the <hi>diſtance of the Preſbyteries</hi> Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall, &amp;c. may <hi>neceſsitate</hi> the cenſure to pertaine to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation, becauſe of the <hi>circumſtances</hi> better knowne to them: By the ſame reaſon, <hi>every Towne</hi> where a malefactor lives, ſhould have the <hi>Seſsions</hi> kept amongſt them; becauſe there the perſon and fact is better knowne, and not one man to be abſent from the cenſure: Nay, a man being to be <hi>excommunicated</hi> out of a particular Church, is <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> out of all Churches, therefore all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt be preſent at the cenſure.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113181:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VINDICIAE</hi> Clavium: OR, A Vindication of the Keyes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What the Keyes be, and what their power.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat by the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> is meant both the Kingdome of <hi>Glory,</hi> which is above, and the Kingdome of <hi>Grace,</hi> which is the <hi>Church</hi> on Earth, I eaſily grant. But I only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire (in the beginning of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) to be informed what you meane by the <hi>Church:</hi> Whether 1. The <hi>inviſible and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Church</hi> of true Beleevers oppoſed to <hi>Reprobates;</hi> or 2. The <hi>Catholicke viſible Church,</hi> oppoſed to <hi>Heathens;</hi> or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113181:13"/> 3. The <hi>particular Congregation</hi> of Beleevers aſſociated in Church-communion, as you uſe to ſpeake. If we may gueſſe at your meaning by the whole proceeding of this Tract; or by your <hi>diſcovery</hi> of your ſelfe in the other Diſcourſe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The way of the Churches</hi> in New-England; (which though it was publiſhed after this of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> yet was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and went up and downe in the darke before it) I thinke you meane it in the latter ſenſe, for a <hi>particular Congregation.</hi> For your firſt Propoſition, there gives us this Reſolution; <hi>[That the Church which Chriſt in the Goſpell hath inſtituted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way p. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to which he hath committed the Keyes &amp;c. it</hi> coetus fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, <hi>a combination of godly men, commonly called a particular viſible Church.]</hi> But of all the reſt, this is the moſt impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſenſe of our Saviours words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. For 1. By the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven</hi> (on Earth) he meanes that <hi>Church,</hi> of which he had ſpoken before, in <hi>v.</hi> 18. But that was, either the <hi>Catholicke viſible Church,</hi> or rather, <hi>the inviſible myſticall Church;</hi> for that only is built upon the rocke, and againſt that the gates of hell ſhall never prevaile: whereas, <hi>particular Churches</hi> may faile. 2. The <hi>kingdome of Glory,</hi> the one part of the meaning of the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> is not contradiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed to a particular <hi>Congregation;</hi> but to the generall <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church</hi> on Earth, oppoſed to the <hi>World</hi> by your ſelfe, The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>[On Earth, that is ſay you) in the Church on Earth, for he gave him no power to bind in the World.]</hi> 3. That <hi>Church</hi> was there meant (ſay you, the way <hi>p.</hi> 1.) whereof <hi>Peter</hi> was one: But <hi>Peter</hi> was not a member of ſuch a particular <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation;</hi> for there was none ſuch extant, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpake theſe words to <hi>Peter.</hi> 4. You ſay againe, it was that <hi>Church</hi> unto which <hi>Peter</hi> or any offended brother might tell the offence, and have it cenſured: But that was never done in a <hi>Church</hi> of Saints, Beleevers, without <hi>officers;</hi> neither was the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113181:13"/> 
                  <hi>church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſuch a church as you deſcribed before; for that had <hi>Officers,</hi> who authoritatively might cenſure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous perſon, yet you joyne them both together. 5. It was (ſay you) a <hi>Church,</hi> who all met in one place for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt: But the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt are not to be found, much leſſe adminiſtred in a <hi>Church</hi> of Beleevers, without <hi>Officers.</hi> 6. When you ſay, <hi>Chriſt committed the Keyes to the Church,</hi> that is, a particular Congregation; you muſt meane it either <hi>Subjectivè,</hi> or <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectivè:</hi> If you meane it in the latter ſenſe, That the <hi>Keyes</hi> are committed to the Church, as the <hi>object</hi> of the exerciſe of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> that is, for the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>good</hi> of the Church, you ſay true, but nothing to the purpoſe. In this ſenſe, the <hi>Keyes</hi> are given, firſt and more immediately to the <hi>inviſible myſticall Church (All</hi> are yours, whether <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c.) then to the generall <hi>viſible Church,</hi> for their ſakes: and then to the particular <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> as a part or member of that generall <hi>viſible Church:</hi> But if you meane it in the former ſenſe, (as you doe and muſt, or elſe you <hi>aequivocate</hi> with us from the beginning, and throughout your whole Booke) you fall into that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme</hi> of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> which you ſo labour to avoid: For to take the <hi>Church,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. for a particular <hi>Congregation</hi> of Beleevers, without <hi>Officers,</hi> is a new, and ſtrange, and falſe gloſſe, maintained by none but <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts.</hi> To conclude, The <hi>Church</hi> of which our Saviour ſpeaks, is called here, the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven</hi> (on Earth:) But a particular <hi>Congregation</hi> of Beleevers is never called the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven;</hi> being but a member or corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that <hi>Kingdome.</hi> It were as improper to call a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> Chriſts Kingdome, as to call <hi>London,</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England;</hi> yet ſo your party ſpeake ſometimes. This I thought good to note, to cleare the way, for the better
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113181:14"/> underſtanding of that which followes: And now goe on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next thing to be explicated is, what the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> be; wherein you reſolve us thus: <hi>[The Keyes are the Ordinances of Chriſt, which he hath inſtituted to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in his Church; as the preaching of the Word, as alſo the adminiſtring of Seales and cenſures.]</hi> I take what you grant, only I ſhall animadvert ſome things. In this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph,</hi> as you doe clearely lay downe the ſtate of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: ſo you doe ſtrongly confute the ſcope of your whole Booke, which is to give the <hi>people</hi> a ſhare in the power of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> that is, in the government of the Church: which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares upon theſe conſiderations; 1. You ſay, the <hi>Keyes</hi> are the Ordinances, which Chriſt hath inſtituted: But the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt are given indeed for the <hi>Church</hi> of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, that is, for their good and benefit, <hi>objectivè:</hi> But are never in all the Scripture, nor in all Antiquity, ſaid to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to that Church, <hi>ſubjectivè.</hi> It ſounds ill at firſt hearing, to ſay that the <hi>people</hi> have any power to exerciſe <hi>Ordinances,</hi> of preaching, or adminiſtring of Seales or Cenſures. The power of preaching or adminiſtring Sacraments by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as none but <hi>Separatiſts doe uſurpe:</hi> ſo your ſelfe complaine of it <hi>page</hi> 6. And why you ſhould allow them power in <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> there is very little reaſon. 2. You ſay, the <hi>Keyes</hi> are <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which Chriſt hath inſtituted to be adminiſtred in his Church: What Church? the <hi>Church</hi> of Beleevers, a particular Congregation; for ſo you meane, as was ſhewed afore: Marke it; to be adminiſtred in that Church (<hi>ſcil.</hi> by Officers inſtituted for that purpoſe) not by that Church without Officers. 3. You adde that which to me clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the <hi>people</hi> of your Church: <hi>[Theſe Keyes are neither ſword nor ſcepter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for they conveigh not ſoveraign power but ſtewardly &amp; miniſteriall.]</hi> Whence thus I argue: The <hi>people</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113181:14"/> Congregation of Beleevers have no <hi>ſtewardly,</hi> or <hi>miniſteriall power</hi> over themſelves; <hi>ergo,</hi> they have nothing to doe with the power of the Keyes: They are not as <hi>Hilkiah</hi> was, whoſe Office was <hi>over the houſe, Iſa.</hi> 22.15, 22. nor <hi>Stewards</hi> in the houſe, as he was, <hi>Gen,</hi> 43.19. nor as thoſe are, who are ſpoken of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Stewards of the myſteries of God.</hi> But you adde a clauſe to draw in the people, ſaying, <hi>[This power (to open and ſhut the gates of Heaven) lyeth partly in their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall calling (whether it be their Office, or their place and order in the Church, &amp;c.]</hi> I ſuppoſe the word <hi>calling,</hi> ſhould be taken here of a <hi>ſpeciall calling, or office,</hi> as we uſe to call it: which againe, would exclude the people from any power in the <hi>Keyes,</hi> as having no <hi>office</hi> in the Church: But you adde, by way of explication of your owne ſenſe: <hi>[Whether it be their Office, or their place and order in the Church]</hi> on purpoſe to ſteale in the <hi>intereſt</hi> of the people, in ſome ſhare of the <hi>Keyes:</hi> But if <hi>place</hi> &amp; <hi>order</hi> in the Church, give the people out of office, any power in the <hi>Keyes,</hi> that is, the Ordinances, (ſo you ſay again) then may <hi>women</hi> &amp; <hi>children</hi> claim an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereſt in thoſe <hi>Keyes;</hi> for they have a <hi>place</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in the Church as well as men; which yet you would ſeeme to deny: But let me profeſſe at firſt, what I ſhall make good from your ſelfe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, I ſee not, but <hi>women</hi> and <hi>children</hi> may challenge a great part of that power of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you give to the <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning the third: What are the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> and the fourth, what is the <hi>ſubject,</hi> to be bound and looſed, I ſhall not contend with you. The fifth, <hi>To whom the power of the Keyes is given,</hi> requires a more ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as being the very foundation of all your new Fabricke, which ſtands or fals with it. The Text is expreſſe: <hi>[To thee</hi> (Simon Peter) <hi>will I give the Keyes, &amp;c.]</hi> in a cleare contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinction to the <hi>Church</hi> before mentioned: upon this rock
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113181:15"/> (of thy confeſſion) will I build my <hi>Church:</hi> which you take for a <hi>particular congregation,</hi> (though by a great miſtake, as was ſhewed above.) But let it be granted for the preſent to be ſo; then the words in all cleare conſtruction run thus: I will build my <hi>Church,</hi> the particular congregation, upon that rocke; and I will give the <hi>Keyes</hi> of that Church (called the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> and ſo by you interpreted) to thee <hi>Peter,</hi> and to ſuch <hi>Officers</hi> as thou art: Otherwiſe he would have ſaid: On this rocke will I build my Church, and I will give unto it the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Kingdome of Heaven, that is, of the Church it ſelfe; which is ſcarſe a reaſonable interpretation of the words. To make way therefore for your great deſigne, you undertake to reſolve that buſie que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (as you call it,) [<hi>How</hi> Peter <hi>is to be conſidered in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this power of the Keyes; whether as an Apoſtle, or as an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or as a Beleever, &amp;c.</hi>] Before I come to conſider your anſwer, I would make bold to put one <hi>ingredient</hi> more into the queſtion; whether <hi>Peter</hi> was not conſidered as a <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> as well as an <hi>Elder,</hi> or <hi>Beleever:</hi> For ſeeing a <hi>Deacon</hi> is one of the Officers of the New Teſtament;<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 32. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 83.</note> (ſome ſay <hi>Iudas</hi> was <hi>Chriſts</hi> Deacon) and your ſelfe ſay, all the <hi>Officers</hi> of the Church were virtually in the Apoſtles; They were <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling-Elders, Deacons,</hi> &amp;c. It may not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly be queſtioned, whether <hi>Peter</hi> did not then repreſent a <hi>Deacon</hi> as well as an <hi>Elder</hi> or <hi>Beleever.</hi> And then againe, whether the <hi>Keyes</hi> were not given to <hi>Peter</hi> as a <hi>Deacon;</hi> and why a <hi>Deacon</hi> only is denyed any power in the <hi>Keyes,</hi> when beleevers are admitted to have a ſhare therin; ſeeing a <hi>Deacon</hi> hath power to collect and diſtribute the <hi>goods</hi> and treaſury of the <hi>Church;</hi> I leave theſe to your conſideration, or theirs who ſhall reply, and come to your anſwer. To ſhew your deſire of <hi>peace,</hi> and your impartiality in inclining to any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113181:15"/> party, you conſider (you ſay) <hi>Peter</hi> in a threefold notion when he received the Keyes <hi>[As an Apoſtle, Elder, Beleever; ſo the ſenſe of the words (you ſay) will be moſt full, if all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations be taken joyntly together.]</hi> The ſenſe indeed is moſt full to your purpoſe, but (I thinke) leaſt of all true.<note n="*" place="margin">The power of the Keyes is given to the Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle, not as an Elder, but as a profeſt Beleever; in the name of Beleevers, &amp;c. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 27. a flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</note> And you doe beg the queſtion, to ſay <hi>Peter</hi> received the power of the Keyes, as all theſe, and in particular, as a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever: For of all the ſenſes, the laſt was leaſt thought on in any age of the Church, till this laſt, when the <hi>Browniſts</hi> and ſuch like ſtumbled upon it. When Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid, <hi>[Peter received the Keyes in the name of the Church:]</hi> Whether he did miſtake the ſenſe of the place or no, you doe utterly miſtake him, to draw him to your meaning: For 1. he did not meane your Church, a particular congregation; but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the generall <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſible</hi> Church; or the <hi>inviſible</hi> myſticall Church. 2. Nor that neither, <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> but <hi>objectivè,</hi> that the Keyes were given to <hi>Peter</hi> as an Officer, for the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p>But you proceed to ſay: [<hi>It appeares Chriſt gave the power of the Keyes to the Body of the Church, even to the fraternity, with the Presbytery,</hi> Mat. 18.17, 18. <hi>When they are met in his Name, and agree together in the cenſure of an offendor.</hi>] But by this place (and your former notion of <hi>Peter</hi> as a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) you may as well inferre, that the Keyes are given to the <hi>Sororietie, q.d.</hi> as to the <hi>Fraternity,</hi> as Beleevers, and as a part of the Body of the Church, which I thinke is flat <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> worſe than <hi>Browniſme.</hi> You know there are ſome, who deny that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18. holds forth any cenſure of <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> at all: Others that grant it, yet by <hi>Church</hi> there, underſtand the <hi>Officers</hi> of the Church, ſuch as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were, to whom Chriſt ſpake: [<hi>What ye binde, what ye looſe,</hi> &amp;c.] You muſt not therefore beg a foundation to your buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113181:16"/> leſt, if it be fetched home, your building fall on your owne head. But you ſay, <hi>[All agree in this, That no offender is to be excommunicated, but with ſome concourſe of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; at leaſt, by way</hi> 1. <hi>of conſent to the ſentence.</hi> 2. <hi>of actuall execution of it, by withdrawing themſelves from him; and this we conceive is ſome part of the exerciſe of the power of the Keyes.]</hi> But truly, this is but the <hi>gingling of the Keyes</hi> at moſt, no part of the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Keyes:</hi> For 1. it belongs to <hi>Stewards</hi> in a Family, only to exerciſe the power of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> to take in, and caſt out what ſervants they pleaſe: The reſt of the ſervants heare the <hi>Keyes</hi> gingle, when they turne the <hi>Keyes,</hi> but have no part in the exerciſe of them; no, not ſo much as by conſent, <hi>active</hi> conſent, I meane, ſo that if they conſent not, nothing is done; but by a <hi>paſsive</hi> conſent only, as approving what the <hi>Steward</hi> hath done: If you grant the <hi>Fraternity</hi> any more, you make them <hi>joynt Stewards</hi> of the Family, the Church, as you ſhall heare hereafter. Nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you ſeeme to give them no more <hi>[The people diſcerning and approving the juſtneſſe of the cenſures before adminiſtred by the Elders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>they give conſent in obedience to the will and rule of Chriſt]</hi> which is no part of the exerciſe of the <hi>power of the Keyes.</hi> For ſuppoſe the <hi>cenſure</hi> be juſtly adminiſtred, and the <hi>people</hi> deny their <hi>conſent;</hi> ſhall not a Delinquent be cenſured unleſſe they will conſent? If not, they have full power in the <hi>Keyes,</hi> ariſing to <hi>authority,</hi> which is the errour of the one <hi>extreme:</hi> If ſo only as <hi>paſsively</hi> to conſent, its evident, this is no part of the <hi>power of the Keyes.</hi> 2. For their <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing,</hi> thats much leſſe any power in the <hi>Keyes.</hi> The <hi>Steward</hi> of a Family having diſcharged a naughty ſervant, and turned and locked him out of doores, all the reſt of the ſervants are to <hi>withdraw</hi> from him; but this is not by way of <hi>active</hi> power, but <hi>paſsive</hi> obedience. Is the <hi>withdrawing</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113181:16"/> people from a man <hi>outlawed</hi> in civill affaires, any intereſt in the <hi>Keyes</hi> of Iudicature? If it be ſaid, except the people conſent and <hi>withdraw communion</hi> from a cenſured perſon, the cenſure is in vaine. I anſwer: If the people ſhould be ſo rebellious to civill Authority, as not to <hi>withdraw</hi> from an <hi>outlawed</hi> man, nothing were done, the ſentence was ſo farre in vaine. If no man could be gotten to execute a malefactor condemned, the ſentence were fruſtrated in reſpect of the execution. But doth this inferre, that the people have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the <hi>Keyes</hi> of ſecular power? The queſtion is not <hi>de facto,</hi> what the people ſtubbornly may doe; but whether they ought not to conſent and withdraw; and whether if they doe not, they can challenge any <hi>intereſt</hi> in the <hi>power of the Keyes.</hi> Againe, if the <hi>Keyes</hi> were given to <hi>Peter</hi> as a <hi>Beleever,</hi> I ſee no reaſon but women and children may come in and challenge a <hi>power</hi> in the Keyes. It ſuffices not to ſay (as the Epiſtolers ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 3.) <hi>[Women and children are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by a Statute Law of Chriſt, againſt their enjoyment of any part of this publick power.]</hi> For though they be forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to ſpeake in the Congregation, or might by <hi>impotence</hi> (as ſome ſay) be excepted in ſome particulars; yet there ſeemes no reaſon why they ſhould be exempted from that <hi>power</hi> here given to the <hi>Fraternity,</hi> which concernes them as well as men, and they are as well able to exerciſe it as men; <hi>viz.</hi> to give a <hi>(paſsive)</hi> conſent, or to withdraw from the party excommunicated; which they may and muſt doe as well as men: For as <hi>women</hi> may be offended, ſo they ſhould in reaſon have ſatisfaction, by conſenting to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: And as <hi>women</hi> may offend, in keeping company with a brother or ſiſter excommunicated, ſo they ought to <hi>withdraw</hi> from them &amp; then if this be any exerciſe of the power of the Keyes, you may heare them <hi>gingle</hi> at the womens girdles;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113181:17"/> which is an <hi>extreme</hi> beyond the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> even downright <hi>Anabaptiſticall.</hi> But you give the <hi>Fraternity</hi> more power than this hereafter, there we ſhall conſider it. Hitherto you have given them nothing, but what is common to them with <hi>women.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the diſtribution of the Keyes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou firſt lay downe the <hi>ordinary Diſtribution of the Keyes,</hi> and then except againſt it, as defective in foure things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>[That any key of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhould be left without power; for the key of knowledge is contradiſtinguiſhed from a key of power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer: It may be this <hi>diſtribution</hi> is not every way exact and perfect, yet I thinke yours is rather worſe: And your exception fals upon your owne diſtribution, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more remotely. For your key of <hi>Faith,</hi> or knowledge (for you make them both one) is diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>key of Order;</hi> which <hi>Order</hi> is either of <hi>power,</hi> or <hi>authority,</hi> and ſo your key of knowledge is left without <hi>power</hi> alſo. 2. Your <hi>key of power</hi> (as you call it) is it ſelfe left without all power, at leaſt <hi>active</hi> power, being only an <hi>obedientiall</hi> power, to conſent and yeeld ſubmiſſion to the will of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> made knowne by the <hi>Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113181:17"/>2. <hi>[There wants (ſay you) an integrall part of the keyes, the key of power or liberty, belonging to the Church it ſelfe.]</hi> But to this I ſay: This is ſo farre from being an <hi>integrall</hi> part of the <hi>keyes,</hi> that it is no <hi>key</hi> at all, no proper <hi>power</hi> at all, as hath partly been ſhewed already. A <hi>key,</hi> in all mens judgement, that ever writ of the <hi>power</hi> of the Church, carries in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, a <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> properly called, <hi>power</hi> in <hi>government,</hi> till now of late; yea, even the <hi>Browniſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves make it a <hi>key</hi> of Authority and Rule in the people: Onely you, to make us beleeve you differ from them, call it a <hi>power</hi> (improperly called <hi>Authority,</hi> pag. 36.) or a <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or a <hi>priviledge;</hi> which was never before called a <hi>key,</hi> till now: For there are many <hi>liberties</hi> or <hi>priviledges</hi> belonging to ſervants in a family, or people in a State; which no man cals a <hi>key</hi> of power, or a <hi>power</hi> in the Keyes. And the truth is, you are not conſtant to your ſelfe: For ſometimes you call it only <hi>liberty,</hi> &amp;c. ſometimes you give the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Brethren,</hi> without their Officers, as full <hi>power</hi> as the Officers themſelves have; and as full <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> as the <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> give them, as we ſhall manifeſt in the ſequell.</p>
               <p>But you adde; <hi>[Proteſtant Churches having recovered the liberty of preaching the Goſpell, and miniſtry of the Sacraments, have looked no farther, ſome of them nor d ſcerned the defect of Church power or liberty due unto them in point of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.]</hi> To this I ſay: The errour of the <hi>Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> was not, that they looked not after the <hi>power</hi> of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for the <hi>people;</hi> but that they laboured not to recover it for their <hi>Elders,</hi> letting the <hi>Prelates</hi> keep quietly the <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> to themſelves. But the errour on the other hand was more eaſie to be fallen into, and more dangerous (which you obſerve to have followed) <hi>[That others finding themſelves wronged (as they did but ſuppoſe) in the withholding a key of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113181:18"/> power which belongs to them, have wreſted to themſelves an undue power, which belongs not to them, the key of Authority.]</hi> True it is, ſome have done ſo; for being allowed (by ſome, perhaps your ſelfe) the <hi>key of power,</hi> or liberty in <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as you call it, they have wreſted, not only the <hi>key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> in preaching and adminiſtring Sacraments, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to them; but alſo the <hi>key of authority,</hi> as you ſpeake; And ſo will your <hi>people</hi> too ere long, I feare, when they are once poſſeſſed a while of <hi>the key of power,</hi> wreſt the <hi>key of authority</hi> in all; both in preaching, and adminiſtring <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and pronouncing <hi>cenſures;</hi> and well they may by your owne grants, as we ſhall heare anon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third <hi>defect</hi> you obſerve; [<hi>In dividing the Key of Order, from the Key of juriſdiction, of purpoſe to make way for the power of Chancellors,</hi> &amp;c.] But 1. That might be the errour of the <hi>diſtributors,</hi> not of the diſtribution. For the <hi>diſtribution,</hi> gives both the <hi>keyes</hi> to the ſame men. For the ſame men that had the <hi>key of knowledge,</hi> had alſo the <hi>key of order</hi> and <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> in the intention of the firſt ſounders of that <hi>diſtribution,</hi> which after ages divided in practiſe. And yet, their <hi>Chancellors,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſaries,</hi> &amp;c. ſome of them at leaſt were <hi>Deacons,</hi> who were reputed of the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> (as they ſpeake) and might preach if they would; and ſo had both <hi>keyes</hi> in one perſon, though limited in ſome <hi>particular acts</hi> of them. But if our late <hi>Deacons</hi> were (as ſome of our <hi>brethren</hi> have ſaid they were) virtually <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and needed no new <hi>Ordination;</hi> then certainly they had the power of <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> with the power of <hi>Order,</hi> though limited, by the corruption of the diſtributors. 2. This <hi>defect</hi> may chance to fall upon your owne <hi>diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Doe not you divide the <hi>key of Order</hi> from the <hi>key of juriſdiction</hi> in your owne <hi>Deacons:</hi> You ſay expreſly in theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113181:18"/> words: <hi>[The Order of Deacons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>page</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>whereof our Lord ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing touching juriſdiction]</hi> I hope you will not ſay, the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of a <hi>Deacon,</hi> fals not under the <hi>key of Order;</hi> yet, for ought I perceive, you make little account of him in your diſtribution. 3. You ſay [<hi>Thoſe Chancellors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with juriſdiction, and more than miniſteriall authority, even above thoſe Elders, who labour in Word and Doctrine.</hi>] But doe not you inveſt the <hi>people</hi> with as much <hi>power</hi> and juriſdiction more than <hi>miniſteriall,</hi> even above thoſe <hi>Elders,</hi> who labour in the word and doctrine, both to open and ſhut the doores of the Church againſt them, <hi>page</hi> 9. beſides what you ſay elſewhere. 4. I would gladly be reſolved, whether you doe not divide the <hi>key of Order,</hi> into a <hi>key of power</hi> or liberty, and a key of <hi>authority,</hi> on purpoſe to make way for the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> as they of old did, for the power of the <hi>Chancellors,</hi> &amp;c. Laſtly, I pray you ſeriouſly to conſider, whether by this [<hi>ſacrilegious breach of Order, inveſting the people with a key of power, even above thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that labour in the Word and Doctrine, to open and ſhut the doores againſt them,</hi> page 9. <hi>(which is the breaking as it were of the files and rankes in an Army; they are your owne words) Satan is not like againe to rout and ruine a great part of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and power of Church officers, and the purity of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and of all the Ordinances of Chriſt in them.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth <hi>defect</hi> is, <hi>[That Order is appropriated to the Officers of the Church only: We put a difference between Office and Order.]</hi> We ſhall ſpeake more fully to this hereafter. All we ſay for the preſent is but this: That <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in the ſtrict and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> ſenſe of the word <hi>(Order)</hi> have hitherto been taken for the ſame. And your ſelfe grant, page 7. <hi>[They may be admitted as aquivalent]</hi> in a right ſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113181:19"/>
               <p>Let us now conſider your owne <hi>Diſtribution: [There is</hi> (ſay you) <hi>a key of Faith, and a key of Order,]</hi> and you have a Text of Scripture for it, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5, 6.</p>
               <p>But by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> there, the Apoſtle meanes not the <hi>keyes</hi> of the kingdome of Heaven, as they are underſtood in this controverſie; but (as I take it) their <hi>Faith</hi> manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in their <hi>orderly</hi> walking, as becomes Chriſtians pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Goſpell. So that by <hi>Order</hi> there is meant their <hi>morall</hi> orderly walking, as in other duties according to the <hi>Rule:</hi> ſo in their ſubmiſſion to the <hi>order of government,</hi> or exerciſe of the <hi>keyes,</hi> in the hands of their Officers. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve no <hi>Interpreter</hi> (but your ſelfe and ſome others of late) ever tooke thoſe words in an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> ſenſe, for the <hi>keyes</hi> delivered unto <hi>Peter.</hi> But we goe on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[The key of Faith</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me with the key of knowledge,</hi> Luke 11.52. <hi>which the Lawyers had taken aw y.]</hi> But 1. by your favour, the <hi>key</hi> of <hi>Faith and knowledge</hi> are not both one, if you underſtand it of <hi>juſtifying Faith:</hi> A man may have much knowledge and no Faith: <hi>Knowledge</hi> may in a ſenſe be ſaid to be the <hi>key of Faith,</hi> as being the <hi>inlet</hi> or Antecedent of Faith; but ſo <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> are not the ſame. 2. The <hi>key of knowledge</hi> is one thing, and <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> is another: The <hi>key of knowledge</hi> is the great <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of preaching</hi> (you ſaid) the <hi>keyes</hi> of the kingdome of Heaven were the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, as the preaching of the Word (the opening and applying of it, <hi>p.</hi> 2) &amp;c. But this <hi>key of knowledge</hi> here you ſpeake of, is (you ſay) common to all <hi>Beleevers;</hi> but a little before this, you complaine that private Chriſtians had uſurped this <hi>key,</hi> to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp;c. <hi>page</hi> 6, Whereas this <hi>key of knowledge</hi> is peculiar to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpell: <hi>[The Prieſts lips keep the key of knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and Faith comes by the Word preached.]</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113181:19"/> This was the <hi>key of knowledge</hi> which the Lawyers had taken away, either by not interpreting, or miſinterpreting the Scripture: They could not take away the peoples <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> much leſſe their <hi>Faith.</hi> They might take away the <hi>key,</hi> both of knowledge and Faith, that is, <hi>preaching,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe, by locking up the Word in a ſtrange language; and ours lately did, by crying and putting downe <hi>preaching.</hi> 2. Whereas you ſay: <hi>[They that had the key of knowledge, had power to enter into the kingdome of Heaven, and it may be, to open the doore to others to enter alſo.]</hi> I anſwer: The <hi>key s</hi> given to <hi>Peter,</hi> Matth. 16. were not to open the Kingdome of Heaven to himſelfe (for that <hi>key,</hi> if a key it was, he had before) but to open it to others, by opening and applying the Word (as you ſaid above) our Saviour ſpeaks of binding and looſing others: <hi>Whoſe ſins ye bind on earth,</hi> &amp;c. and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening for, and ſhutting out others, not himſelfe. <hi>Keyes</hi> are given to <hi>Stewards,</hi> not properly to let in, or ſhut out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but by way of <hi>Office,</hi> to let in, or locke out others. Beſides,<note place="margin">A priviledge to find an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen doore to enter into the fellowſhip of the Church, <hi>p.</hi> 11. which is paſſive, and in plaine ſenſe, one fit to be admitted into the Church. So the Epiſtolers, <hi>p.</hi> 2. The key of knowledge hath opened their hearts; that is, I think, preaching.</note> the <hi>key of knowledge</hi> and Faith which you deſcribe here, is common to all <hi>Beleevers,</hi> even <hi>women;</hi> but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you will not give them a <hi>key</hi> to open and ſhut heaven to others, that is the <hi>key of preaching.</hi> Then againe, why doe you diſlike the former diſtribution; when you alſo make one <hi>key</hi> to be the <hi>key of knowledge,</hi> and ſo leave one of the <hi>keyes</hi> of the Kingdome of Heaven <hi>without power,</hi> contra-diſtinguiſhing the <hi>key</hi> of Faith or knowledge (for with you they are both one) from the <hi>key of power,</hi> which fals under your <hi>key of Order?</hi> Laſtly, whereas you ſay a faithfull ſoule by this <hi>key</hi> entreth into a ſtate of grace, and into the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Church, &amp;c. You may remember, that by the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> which is the Church on Earth, you underſtand a <hi>particular Congregation.</hi> But a man may have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113181:20"/> this <hi>key</hi> of Faith or knowledge, and never enter into your <hi>particular Church,</hi> and ſo this <hi>key</hi> is given to a man out of the <hi>Church;</hi> and yet you ſay, the <hi>keyes</hi> are given to the Church, I leave you to conſider it. Theſe things hang not well together.</p>
               <p>In the next place you come to the <hi>key of Order;</hi> of which you thus write: <hi>[The key of Order, is the power whereby every member of the Church walketh orderly himſelfe, according to his place in the Church, and helpeth his brethren to walke order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo.]</hi> But this is a ſtrange expreſſion of the <hi>key of Order,</hi> never heard of before, too generally and aequivocally ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: For <hi>Order</hi> may be taken either <hi>morally,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally;</hi> Paſſively, or Actively. Morally, ſo it is taken paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, for a <hi>conformity</hi> in carriage, to the <hi>rules</hi> of the word, in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as well as <hi>diſcipline:</hi> But <hi>Eccleſiaſtically,</hi> it is an <hi>Active power,</hi> acting upon others. The very name of a <hi>key,</hi> imports a <hi>power,</hi> intruſted for others good, and not their owne properly. Every one is to <hi>keep Order,</hi> but every one hath not the <hi>key of Order. Order</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> in this <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> ſenſe are both one. None hath the <hi>key of Order,</hi> but one in <hi>Office.</hi> But your <hi>key of Order</hi> is common to every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church:<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p ge</hi> 21.</note> And that it is no more than <hi>morall</hi> or <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Order,</hi> your ſelfe doe ſeeme to grant, when you ſay, <hi>[The brethren ſtand in an Order, even in an orderly ſubjection, according to the order of the Goſpell.]</hi> Every <hi>ſervant</hi> in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and every man, woman and childe in a corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtand in ſuch an <hi>order,</hi> and muſt walke <hi>orderly</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and help others to walke <hi>orderly</hi> alſo; but will any man ſay, therefore theſe have intereſt in the <hi>keyes</hi> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or Corporation? If every member of a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have this <hi>key of Order,</hi> how and why are women and children excepted? or are they no <hi>members</hi> of the Church?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113181:20"/> or may they walke <hi>diſorderly?</hi> The inſtance of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> walking <hi>orderly,</hi> according to the <hi>orders</hi> of the Iewiſh Church, manifeſts the morall ſenſe of the word: For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, the <hi>Fraternity</hi> of the Iewes had no power of the Keyes. The meaning was, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by his <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> to ſome Iewiſh Ceremonies, ſhould manifeſt, that he did not abſolutely oppoſe the Rites of the Iewiſh Church, not that he had any power of the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the government of that Church. Surely the <hi>Iewes</hi> were bound all of them to <hi>withdraw</hi> from every brother that walked <hi>diſorderly;</hi> yet did not beleeve that that was any part of the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the <hi>key of Order.</hi> No more was it in thoſe of <hi>Theſſalonica;</hi> when they did warne the unruly, or withdraw from him that walked diſorderly: And this <hi>Key of Order,</hi> if a Key it were, was common not only to <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> as you ſay, but even to women and children, as I ſaid afore.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Of Order</hi> (you ſay) <hi>there be</hi> 2. <hi>Keyes; one of power or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, another of Authority or Rule; The firſt of theſe is called in Scripture, Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Before I examine the particulars, I ſhall note ſome few things: 1. How <hi>modeſt</hi> errour is at firſt: Here it is firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>power,</hi> mollified by <hi>intereſt,</hi> and then by <hi>liberty,</hi> after by <hi>priviledge;</hi> all which are rather <hi>paſsive</hi> than <hi>active;</hi> but afterwards it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, power, which though it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignifies a <hi>priviledge,</hi> honour, or dignity, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. in a <hi>paſsive</hi> conſtruction, as given and received; yet when it relates to <hi>Government,</hi> or a <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> civilly, it then is taken <hi>actively,</hi> and ſignifies <hi>Authority,</hi> Romanes 13.1. But <hi>page</hi> 36. it is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which properly, (though you ſay otherwiſe, ſignifies <hi>Authority; [Authority, after a ſort, may be acknowledged in the people.]</hi> And the acts there (and elſewhere) given to the people, ſome of them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113181:21"/> at leaſt; as [<hi>joyning in Cenſures, and in determination of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodall acts,</hi> &amp;c.] called, <hi>[a great ſtroke or power in ordering Church affaires;]</hi> amounts almoſt to as <hi>full authority,</hi> as the <hi>Elders</hi> have any. 2. Another thing I note is, that this <hi>power,</hi> intereſt, priviledge of the people, &amp;c. was never called a <hi>Key,</hi> till ſome <hi>new Lock ſmiths</hi> made this <hi>new pick-locke</hi> of the <hi>power</hi> of Church-Officers. For what is all that is given them, if no more than is their due) to the <hi>government of the Church?</hi> In a Family, in a Corporation (I ſay it againe) the ſervants and Citizens have ſome <hi>priviledges</hi> and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, who yet have no <hi>ſtroke in ordering of the Keyes,</hi> either of Family, or City. 3. I deſire to know, under which of the parts of this diſtribution doth the <hi>Deacon</hi> fall. There be 2. <hi>Keyes of Order;</hi> of power or intereſt; of Authority or Rule. Now a <hi>Deacon,</hi> qua <hi>Deacon,</hi> fals under neither of theſe: Not the firſt, for ſo he is conſidered only as a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever:</hi> Not the ſecond, for ſo he is denyed <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> as we heard afore. If you ſay he fals under the <hi>Key of Order,</hi> as an Officer; yet then you divide the <hi>Key of Order</hi> from the <hi>Key of juriſdiction,</hi> (which you blamed in the other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution) and levell the <hi>Deacon</hi> an <hi>Officer,</hi> with people no Officers. We ſhould now come to the particulars of the <hi>power,</hi> or intereſt of the <hi>Brethren:</hi> They have a <hi>liberty</hi> (ſay you) in many things; but they are more fully laid downe in Chapter 4. there we ſhall conſider them: Only now we ſhall conſider the proofe of this <hi>power of the people,</hi> out of the Scripture: Your Text is, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Brethren, you have been called unto Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.] This Text (under favour) is miſerably miſtaken; and that not in mine only, but in the judgement of all <hi>Interpreters;</hi> which you knowing, had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeale to the <hi>Context,</hi> than to the <hi>Commentators.</hi> I ſhall follow you at your owne weapon; Your ſtrength lyes in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113181:21"/> the word <hi>Liberty. [They have a power and liberty, to wit, to joyne with the ſounder part of the Preſbytery in caſting them out,</hi> &amp;c.] But I ſhall appeale the Apoſtle himſelfe to be Iudge between us: In the firſt verſe of this Chapter he uſes the ſame word, [<hi>Stand faſt in the Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.] where it is without all controverſie, underſtood of their <hi>liberty,</hi> or <hi>freedome from the Ceremoniall Law;</hi> called there, the <hi>yoke of bond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge,</hi> which ſome falſe teachers would impoſe upon their necks. Now that the Apoſtle ſpeaking ſtill of the ſame matter, ſhould uſe the ſame word in ſo different a ſenſe, is no wayes probable. Nay ſecondly, in the 11. <hi>verſe,</hi> the Apoſtle ſayes: <hi>[If I yet preach circumciſion, why doe I yet ſuffer perſecution,</hi> &amp;c.] And then <hi>ver.</hi> 13. comes in againe with this: [<hi>Brethren you are called unto Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>viz.</hi> from that Law of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the like, not to the <hi>liberty</hi> by you pretended; [<hi>To chuſe Officers, or to joyne in Cenſures,</hi> &amp;c.] though, theſe were granted to them, yet not in this place: And your gloſſe is very far fetcht and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. <hi>[I would they were cut off that trouble you; where</hi> (ſay you) <hi>he declares what cenſure he wiſhes againſt thoſe that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them,</hi> viz. <hi>cut off,</hi> to wit, <hi>by excommunication.</hi> Obj. <hi>But what power have we to cut them off?</hi> The Apoſtle anſwers: <hi>They have a power and liberty,</hi> to wit, <hi>to joyne with the ſounder part of the Preſbytery, in caſting them out: For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you are called unto Liberty.]</hi> There is not one word of this gloſſe in the Text. And if there were any ſuch power, the people have full power given themſelves to cut them off; for here is not one word of joyning with a <hi>Preſbytery.</hi> See againe, <hi>v.</hi> 16. where the Apoſtle reſumes his exhortation, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>[Vſe not your liberty as an occaſion unto the fleſh;</hi> ſaying, <hi>I ſay then, walke in the ſpirit, and you ſhall not fulfill the luſts of the fleſh:]</hi> Which makes it evident, that the Apoſtle
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113181:22"/> chiefly exhorts <hi>ad bonos mores,</hi> though he touch other things by the bye, but <hi>diſcipline</hi> is leaſt of all intended. And leſt they ſhould uſe their <hi>liberty</hi> from thoſe legall and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall yokes, to contention or licentiouſneſſe, he cautions againſt it, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 16. <hi>[Carnall contention is indeed</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>an uſuall diſeaſe of popular liberty;]</hi> which I feare, you and your partners too much foment, by giving the people this power and liberty, which you ſo much talke of; and by <hi>gingling</hi> theſe <hi>Keyes</hi> in the eares of the <hi>people,</hi> have almoſt made them wilde; not only one againſt another, but againſt their <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Governours</hi> alſo. And no marvell, when you grant them ſo much power <hi>[As to open a doore of entrance to the Miniſters Calling: ſo to ſhut the doore of entrance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in ſome caſes, page.</hi> 9.] much more than which the <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe not grant then. And ſo much of the <hi>pick-locke of Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Key of Authority is a morall power, in a ſuperiour order or ſtate, binding or releaſing an inferiour in point of ſubjection.]</hi> To this I ſay; 1. To call <hi>Authority</hi> a morall power, is very improper: For every ſingle Paſtor, (yea, perhaps brother,) hath a morall power to bind and releaſe, not only an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, but a ſuperiour alſo, in point of ſubjection, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the commands of God. You might rather have called it, a <hi>juridicall,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> power, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any danger, ſeeing you reſerve this power to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or ſuperiours in Order. But 2. you ſpeake too confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly: For the people have a <hi>power</hi> to joyne with the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the cenſures, that is, in binding and releaſing, as you ſay, <hi>page</hi> 14. <hi>[The whole Church may be ſaid to binde and looſe;]</hi> Nay, to open and ſhut the doores againſt their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who are their ſuperiors; and ſo <hi>Authority</hi> is a morall power in inferiours alſo. And <hi>page</hi> 12. you ſay the people
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113181:22"/> have a power, <hi>[To prevent the tyranny, and Oligarchy, and exorbitance of the Elders.]</hi> Surely this muſt be by a <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice,</hi> and thats more than <hi>liberty,</hi> even full <hi>authority;</hi> and being by inferiours, is flatly againſt your owne defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Furthermore, as you ſay [<hi>the Brethren with the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders have power to open and ſhut,</hi> &amp;c.] So you ſay, <hi>[the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with the Brethren doe bind and releaſe,]</hi> page 10. So it ſeemes, as the Brethren can doe nothing without the Elders: ſo the Elders can doe nothing without the Brethren, as the Epiſtolers ſay expreſſely, <hi>page</hi> 4. And who would not now conclude, that the <hi>liberty</hi> is equall in both; or rather, the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> is the ſame in both, and what ſay the Browniſts more?</p>
               <p>And now I thinke you cannot truly ſay, you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this diſtribution of the <hi>Keyes</hi> from the Scripture, nor yet from <hi>antiquity;</hi> though you would faine have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, you would not ſticke upon the former diſtribution, if the words be rightly explained. As how? 1. <hi>[Let them</hi> (ſay you) <hi>allow ſome ſpirituall power to the Key of knowledge, though not a church power.]</hi> But have you not all this while been ſpeaking of the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the Kingdome of Heaven, that is, the Church; and now is the power of the <hi>Key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> no Church power? Againe, have not you your ſelfe taken away from the <hi>Key of knowledge,</hi> not only Church power, but all power whatever, by contradiſtinguiſhing it to the <hi>Key of power?</hi> 3. Is that <hi>Key,</hi> whereby he that hath it, [<hi>not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y enters himſelfe into the Kingdome of Heaven, but alſo opens the doore for others to enter, no</hi> Church power?]</p>
               <p>You adde ſecondly, <hi>[Let them put in a Key of liberty, as well as of authority into Church power.]</hi> But both theſe are but <hi>one Key,</hi> or nothing, as we have ſaid; Nothing indeed to purpoſe, if both theſe muſt conſent, or nothing is done,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113181:23"/> as you and the Brethren aſſert. 3. <hi>[Let them not</hi> (ſay you) <hi>divide from the Key of Order or Office, the Key of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; for Chriſt hath given no juriſdiction, but to whom he hath given Office.]</hi> But 1. Chriſt (it ſeemes) hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the <hi>Key</hi> of Office, from the <hi>Key</hi> of juriſdiction; for hee hath given no juriſdiction to <hi>Deacons.</hi> 2. You ſhould have ſaid, and your ſcope required it, Chriſt hath given to none the <hi>Key</hi> of Order or Office, but to whom he hath given the <hi>Key</hi> of juriſdiction, but that had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted your ſelfe in the inſtance of <hi>Deacons: [Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom</hi> (ſay you) <hi>our Lord ſpake nothing of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> page 6.] Now is it not as ſtrange, that there ſhould be an Office in the Church, without ſome juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; As that there ſhould among the Prelates, bee juriſdiction without an Office, at leaſt, inſtituted by Chriſt? as it was in Chancellors, Commiſſaries, &amp;c. Nay, is it not as ſtrange that there ſhould be <hi>Authority,</hi> that is, juriſdiction, to binde and looſe, in thoſe that have no Office at all; as there is in the people in your way; as that there ſhould be an Office without juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction? And now I leave you to conſider, whether of theſe Diſtributions is moſt conſentaneous to the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113181:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Subject of the Key of Knowledge and Order.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou firſt tell us in generall; <hi>[That as the Keyes be divers, ſo are the Subjects to whom they are committed divers.]</hi> But this is very doubtfull and diſputable; becauſe at firſt, all the <hi>Keyes</hi> were given to <hi>Peter</hi> at once, and therefore one <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> may poſſeſſe them all: And ſure they all meet in Paſtors, every one of them hath all the <hi>Keyes; of knowledge and of power; of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and juriſdiction,</hi> according to the old diſtribution, and perhaps in yours alſo. As the Apoſtles had all the <hi>Keyes</hi> by your confeſſion; <hi>[They might exhort as Paſtors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>teach as Teachers, rule as Rulers, receive and diſtribute the oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church as Deacons:]</hi> So, I ſee no reaſon, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſter of the Goſpell hath virtually in him all the ſame power and Offices: And if they be ſince divided into more hands, for caſe and Order, yet the <hi>ſubject</hi> is primarily but one; and for the diverſity of ſubjects of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes them who plead it, to make it good by Scripture. Vpon this reaſon, there are ſome, who as they queſtion the Office of a <hi>ruling Elder,</hi> having 1. no direct or expreſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for it in the Scripture. 2. No inſtance of any ſuch,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113181:24"/> that ruled, and were not alſo <hi>Paſtors.</hi> 3. Nor doe you ſay, That <hi>Peter</hi> received the <hi>Keyes</hi> as a <hi>ruling-Elder,</hi> but as a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor:</hi> ſo they would not yeeld the Office of the <hi>Deacon,</hi> but that they finde expreſſe inſtituted of it afterwards by the Apoſtles. But I will not multiply controverſies, but come to your particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>[The Key of knowledge (or which is all one, the Key of faith) belongeth to all the faithfull, whether joyned to any particular Church or no.]</hi> But 1. Then one of the <hi>Keyes</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven belongs to <hi>women,</hi> yea to <hi>Infidels;</hi> When God gives them <hi>Faith, [he gives them a Key to receive Chriſt, and to find an open doore to enter into the fellowſhip of the Church.]</hi> But ſure the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> did not repreſent <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels</hi> when the <hi>Keyes</hi> were committed to him. 2. The <hi>Keyes</hi> (you ſaid) were given to the Church; but now you ſay, they are given to ſome before they enter into the Church. But I pray, Sir, is not he entred into the Church, who hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt, and makes profeſſion of his faith? Yes, you may ſay, into the <hi>myſticall Church,</hi> but not into a <hi>particular church-fellowſhip.</hi> I anſwer, he is entred alſo into the generall <hi>viſible Church,</hi> by profeſſion of his faith; to which Church, we thinke, the <hi>Keyes</hi> were firſt given, and after, to the particular Church. But you have ſo long dreamed of a <hi>particular Church,</hi> to be the firſt and only inſtituted Church, that you ſeeme to forget the <hi>viſible generall Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, p. 10</note> and indeed, to call it a <hi>Chimara.</hi> This, we thinke, you learned from your Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, if not your Brethren, the <hi>Browniſts.</hi> Heretofore, in Scripture language, ſo ſoone as men beleeved, and profeſſed their faith, they were ſaid, to <hi>be added to the Church,</hi> not to a <hi>particular Congregation</hi> (for ſo ſome were never added, for ought we know, as the Eunuch, and ſome others) but to the generall viſible Church. And I pray, what <hi>Key</hi> was it that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113181:24"/> opened the doore to enter them into the Church? Was it the <hi>key</hi> of their owne particular <hi>knowledge</hi> or Faith? or the <hi>key of preaching, viz.</hi> the <hi>key of knowledge</hi> in the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and not in themſelves? You ſay here (which is the truth) that <hi>[they find an open doore to enter into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Church:]</hi> which is <hi>paſsively,</hi> to be capable to be admitted into the Church, and not <hi>actively,</hi> to open the doore to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>[The Key of Order, belongeth to all ſuch as are in Church order, whether Elders or Brethren.]</hi> But this is doubtfully ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a double reſpect: 1. What you meane by <hi>Order</hi> as afore. If Order and Office be all one (as you ſeemed to yeeld) then the <hi>key of Order</hi> belongs not to the Brethren at all, but to the <hi>Elders,</hi> who are in office. If Order be taken for <hi>orderly carriage,</hi> or, (as you your ſelfe ſpeak in this very Paragraph) For <hi>[orderly ſubjection, according to the order of the Goſpell]</hi> it is juſt nothing to the power of the <hi>Keyes:</hi> For <hi>keyes</hi> imply an active power, orderly ſubjection is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally paſſive. 2. It is alſo doubtfull, what is meant by <hi>Church</hi> in this place: If it be taken for the generall <hi>viſible Church,</hi> that hath nothing to doe with the power of the <hi>keyes,</hi> which are committed (ſay you) to the <hi>particular Church:</hi> If for the <hi>particular Congregation,</hi> it is then doubtfull ſtill. For it may be asked, what power have the Brethren in <hi>Church Order,</hi> in the <hi>keyes of Order,</hi> more than one not yet in <hi>Church Order?</hi> Your ſelfe ſpeake confuſedly here, in my judgement, when you ſay; <hi>[Every faithfull ſoule that hath received a key of knowledge</hi> (you ſhould rather ſay, knowledge, by the key of preaching) <hi>is bound to watch over his Neighbours ſoule, as his owne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>non ratione ordinis ſed in tuitu charitatis; Not by vertue of a ſtate or order which he is in (till in Church-fellowſhip) but as of common Chriſtian love and charity; one in Church-Order,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113181:25"/> is bound to doe it in both reſpects,</hi> &amp;c.] But 1. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of no particular Church as yet, is in a <hi>Church-Order,</hi> with reſpect to the generall <hi>viſible Church,</hi> (or elſe what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers he from an Infidell?) and ſo is bound to watch over his Neighbour, not only by vertue of common <hi>charity,</hi> but of that <hi>Chriſtian-Order,</hi> wherein he ſtands. 2. Nay, an Infidell is bound, <hi>in tuitu charitatis,</hi> by vertue of common naturall love and charity, to watch over, and admoniſh his brother: and is a Chriſtian (not yet in <hi>Church-Order,</hi> as you call it) bound no more than he, to watch over his brother? If he be, (as he is, by a nearer relation unto the myſticall body, and viſible Church of Chriſt) then he is to doe it, by vertue of his Order, or ſtate of Chriſtianity: If he be not, what differs he from an Infidell? It was a morall Law, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.18. [<hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother, but rebuke him,</hi> &amp;c.] Which <hi>Cain</hi> deſpiſed, when he ſaid;, <hi>[Am I my brothers keeper?]</hi> Surely it is want of <hi>naturall charity,</hi> not to watch over a brother, that is not in <hi>Church-Order</hi> as you meane it. And it is not becomming a Chriſtian to ſay: [<hi>A Chriſtian in Church-Order is not to watch over a brother not in Church-Order,</hi> ratione ordinis, <hi>but only</hi> in tuitu charitatis:] He is bound to doe ſo for an Infidell, and is he bound no more to a Chriſtian? Suppoſe one in your <hi>Church-Order,</hi> ſee a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian not in <hi>Church-Order,</hi> walke unorderly; is he not bound to admoniſh him, by that royall Law of Church-Order, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.1. And if he will not heare him, to take two or three more; and if he will not heare them, to tell it to the Church; and afterwards, to walke towards him, as God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the Church to order it? Hath Chriſt ordained no better remedy to reclaime a Chriſtian, not in <hi>Church-Order,</hi> than to reclaime an Infidell? But further: An <hi>Officer,</hi> or one in a ſuperiour <hi>Order,</hi> by reaſon of his <hi>office,</hi> is bound to watch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113181:25"/> over his brothers ſoule, not only <hi>in tuitu charitatis,</hi> but alſo <hi>ratione ordinis.</hi> Is a brother bound as much as he? or he no more then a brother out of <hi>office?</hi> Againe, a <hi>Deacon</hi> is in a ſuperiour Order, by reaſon of his <hi>office</hi> (as you ſpeake here of <hi>Elders</hi>) in what different reſpect is he bound to watch over his brother? no otherwiſe then a brother out of <hi>office?</hi> Truly then it is all one in your way, to be in an <hi>office,</hi> and out of <hi>office.</hi> And this is the way to baniſh, if not Chriſtian, yet <hi>naturall charity</hi> out of the Church: And it is obſervable, that ſince this <hi>new Church-fellowſhip,</hi> and <hi>Church covenant</hi> hath been ſet up, <hi>charity</hi> is growne very cold, and ſome of them have been heard to profeſſe <hi>[they had nothing to doe with an offendor, not of their owne particular Church-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion:]</hi> And doe indeed account all not of their way, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better than <hi>Infidels,</hi> or as they ſpeake <hi>without;</hi> and in a manner ſay with <hi>Cain, Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> Never was there ſo little <hi>charity,</hi> ſo much ſcorne and contempt of all not in their owne way, as is found in them that profeſſe themſelves the only people, that have found <hi>the way of Chriſt,</hi> though in ſeverall <hi>Sections.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Subject of Church-Liberty.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Key is given to the Brethen of the Church;</hi> for ſo faith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Brethren you are called unto liberty]</hi> Concerning the vindication of that Text enough hath been ſaid above. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113181:26"/> you come to the particulars of their <hi>liberties,</hi> you <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricate</hi> a little, to make it more paſſable. <hi>[As in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the welfare of it ſtands in the due ballancing of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties or priviledges of the people, and the authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: ſo in the Church, the ſafety of it is in the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the priviledges of the Brethren, and the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall authority of the Elders.]</hi> All this is granted: But the right <hi>ballancing</hi> of either, lyes not in the multitude of the people, as having any immediate influence into the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Church or State: For then the government of both were <hi>Democraticall.</hi> But as in our State, the <hi>ballancing</hi> of the priviledges of the people, and the authority of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſupreme, lyes in the authority of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> where there are <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> repreſenting the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo, I thinke it is in the Church; the ballancing of the <hi>Brethrens priviledges,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſters authority,</hi> ſeemes to lye in the <hi>Ruling-Elders,</hi> who are the repreſentatives of the people. But take away this <hi>ballaſt</hi> or poiſe of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and it will be either <hi>abſolutely Monarchicall,</hi> and ſo eaſily <hi>Tyrannicall,</hi> or elſe <hi>Democraticall,</hi> and ſo lyable to <hi>Anarchy</hi> and confuſion, as experience ſhewes us, in the <hi>Papall</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> tyranny, and the <hi>Separatiſts Anarchy;</hi> the two <hi>extremes</hi> before obſerved. But let us take a view of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. Their <hi>Liberties</hi> are;</p>
               <p n="1">1. [<hi>To chuſe their owne Officers:</hi> ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 1. and 6. and 14.] In generall I anſwer thus: The <hi>election</hi> of the people, was no more but a deſignation, or propounding the perſons, and preſenting them to the Apoſtles, not by way of <hi>vote</hi> or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, but by way of deſire, if they were found fit, to have one or ſome of them ordained. But this is little or nothing to the <hi>power of the Keyes.</hi> That place <hi>Acts</hi> 1. was an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary caſe,</hi> wherein the people had little or no hand:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113181:26"/> For 1. they were confined to ſome ſort of men, hat had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with our Saviour. 2. They propounded two, it was not in their power ſo much as to <hi>nominate</hi> the particular man. 3. The Lord himſelfe determined it, and not the Apoſtles, much leſſe the people; As for that word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſtood upon, it cannot be properly taken, as if they by their <hi>votes</hi> or ſuffrages, had conſtituted or ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Mathias</hi> to be an Apoſtle, but barely thus: Seeing God had choſen and ordained him, they accepted him by an <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſubjection</hi> to the revealed will of Chriſt. For the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. It was expedient, that the people ſhould at leaſt have the <hi>nomination</hi> of their <hi>Deacons,</hi> becauſe better knowne to them, and ſo better to be truſted with their owne ſtocke. But they did but <hi>nominate</hi> or preſent the men, they did not <hi>ordaine</hi> ſo much as a <hi>Deacon; [Looke you out ſeven men, whom we</hi> (marke it) <hi>may appoint, or ordaine to this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.]</hi> It is never found in all the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that ever the people <hi>ordained</hi> or impoſed hands upon any <hi>Officer;</hi> which makes me wonder at the <hi>liberty</hi> taken by <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and allowed and practiſed by your ſelf;<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 41.</note> 
                  <hi>[That the Church or Brethren without Officers, may not only elect, but ordaine and impoſe hands upon their higheſt Officers.]</hi> As for the third place, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. The word cannot be well rendred: <hi>[They ordained them Elders, choſen by lifting up of hands:]</hi> For it is not to be referred to the people, but to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas:</hi> who ſurely did not ordaine Elders by <hi>lifting up,</hi> but by <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on</hi> of hands. And ſo taken, it excludes the people; for the Subſtantive to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas:</hi> If they choſe the <hi>Elders</hi> by lifting up of hands, then the <hi>people</hi> are excepted, not only from <hi>ordination</hi> of their <hi>Officers,</hi> but from <hi>election</hi> too, by this Text. But further: ſome of your <hi>Brethren</hi> hold, that <hi>election</hi> is the chiefeſt peece of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113181:27"/> calling, and <hi>ordination,</hi> but a complement to the <hi>ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of it: And if ſo, the <hi>people</hi> doe ordaine them as well as elect, and thats more then a <hi>liberty,</hi> even as full <hi>authority</hi> as the <hi>Browniſts</hi> give to the people: Your ſelfe doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſome where,<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 48.</note> that <hi>[Ordination is a worke of Rule,]</hi> And yet you ſay alſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> 45.</note> 
                  <hi>[That the Brethren may ordaine their Officers;]</hi> Therefore the people have more than a <hi>key of liberty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 8. and often. Ordination &amp; juriſdiction pertaine indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently to all the Preſbyters. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 49</note> they have a <hi>key of rule and authority;</hi> which yet againe you doe reſerve as <hi>proper to the Elders.</hi> Conſider how you can reconcile the contradictions. That the people have a <hi>liberty,</hi> juſtly to except, or rationally, to approve of their <hi>Officers,</hi> is granted; but this is (I ſtill ſay) nothing to the <hi>power of the Keyes,</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>Ordination</hi> of Officers choſen, not in the <hi>election</hi> of Officers to be ordained.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond <hi>liberty</hi> of the people is, <hi>[To ſend out meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers for the publicke ſervice of the Church,</hi> Phil. 2.25.] This may be granted a <hi>liberty,</hi> but nothing to the <hi>power of the keyes:</hi> People may aſſent to, or approve of the reaſonable choice of <hi>meſſengers</hi> to be ſent forth, juſt as poore <hi>Cottiers</hi> in the Countrey, that have no <hi>votes</hi> in the election of their <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> have yet a conſent and approbation to ſend them to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A third <hi>Liberty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> [To accept againſt ſuch as offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to communion, or unto the ſeales of it,</hi> Acts 9.26.] This is nothing more to the <hi>power of the keyes,</hi> than the former. Any <hi>woman</hi> may in a <hi>ſcandall,</hi> except againſt any that offers to partake of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> by way of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the Officers; yet hath no intereſt in the <hi>keyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth: <hi>[To joyne with the Elders, in inquiring, hearing, judging of publick ſcandals, ſo as to bind notorious offendors under cenſures, and to forgive the penitens.]</hi> If this be not aequivocaly ſpoken, it is certainly more then a <hi>liberty.</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113181:27"/> That they may enquire for their own ſatisfaction, and heare by way of preſence, is a <hi>liberty</hi> not to be denyed. But if you meane any more, it is more then a <hi>liberty,</hi> an act of <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>authority.</hi> Heare your owne words, ſpoken with reſpect to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> but will better fit our purpoſe:<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 48.</note> 
                  <hi>[If the Holy-Ghoſt had appointed the people to any ſhare in the keyes, he would have appointed them alſo ſome eminent worke. But what ſhall that be? Shall it be Ordination? Why that is a work of Rule: Or ſhall it be hearing accuſations againſt Elders, and cenſuring them accordingly? Why that is a worke of Rule alſo.]</hi> Let me adde, ſhall it be judging of publick ſcandals, ſo as to bind notorious offendors under cenſure? Why, that is a worke of <hi>Rule</hi> alſo. And conſider now, whether they have not a <hi>key of authority,</hi> as full as the <hi>Elders</hi> themſelves. If you meane a <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcretion only, which all the multitude have at an Aſſizes, it is juſt nothing to the purpoſe; a ſtranger, none of the Congregation, a woman, an heathen may doe as much. But you ſay, [<hi>The Apoſtle alloweth to all the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren a power to judge them that are within,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.22.] But either this is fallacious; There was a power in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> to judge thoſe within; <hi>ergo,</hi> this power was in the people, or elſe it is falſe, if meant of <hi>authoritative</hi> judgement; or if only a judgement of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> it is quite beſides the queſtion. But you fearing an objection, prevent it, to <hi>judge</hi> is an act of <hi>Rule,</hi> which is proper to the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> you anſwer, <hi>[There is a judgement of diſcretion; As in the Iury it is an act of their popular liberty, in the Iudge an act of judiciall authority.]</hi> To this I have many things to ſay: 1. A judgement of <hi>diſcretion</hi> will not ſerve your turne; for that (as I ſaid) is common to all the <hi>people</hi> at an Aſſizes; and that is common to <hi>women,</hi> and <hi>heathens,</hi> if preſent, at your Conſiſtories; and if this be all, what difference is there
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113181:28"/> between the judgement of a <hi>woman,</hi> an <hi>heathen,</hi> and of one of your <hi>Church-members.</hi> 2. The judgement of the <hi>Iury</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an act of <hi>popular liberty;</hi> but not of their <hi>liberty,</hi> more than of thoſe that are not of the <hi>Iury.</hi> For I aske, why are not all the reſt of the people, whom it concernes as much as thoſe twelve men of the <hi>Iury,</hi> admitted to the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with them? Are not they wronged in point of <hi>popular liberty?</hi> would not you ſay, <hi>[The Brethren not admitted to the hearing and judging of an offender, were wronged, if only twelve of the Congregation were deſigned to heare and judge him.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In our native Countrey, the Iudge diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the verdict of the Iury, &amp;c. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 102.</note>] 3. The judgement of the <hi>Iury,</hi> is more than of <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion</hi> (ſo all by-ſtanders judge) even of <hi>authority,</hi> in ſome degree and kind, though not <hi>compleat:</hi> For they <hi>condemne,</hi> or <hi>acquit</hi> the party, which all the reſt together cannot doe. 4. The <hi>Iudge,</hi> I take it, may not <hi>condemne</hi> who they <hi>acquit,</hi> nor <hi>acquit</hi> whom they <hi>condemne,</hi> (except by a ſpeciall <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi>) and thats farre more than a judgement of <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the Iury. If it be ſo with the Brethren here (as the <hi>Epiſtolers</hi> ſay it is) certainly they have more than a <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcretion: But your ſelfe ſay as much; you give the Brethren, not only joyned with their <hi>Elders,</hi> but without any Officers at all, full power to cenſure offenders: Remember your owne words;<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 45, 101.</note> 
                  <hi>[As for mutuall inſtruction, and admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, election, and ordination of officers, opening the doores of the Church, by admiſsion of members, and ſhutting the ſame by Church-cenſures: Theſe things they may doe (if need be) without Officers: yea, and if all their Officers were found cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, either in hereticall doctrine, or ſcandalous crime, yet the Church hath lawfull authority to proceed to the cenſure of them all.]</hi> If this be not as full or more <hi>authority</hi> than the <hi>Elders</hi> have over all the <hi>Brethren,</hi> I profeſſe, I underſtand nothing in this controverſie: yet this I underſtand, that you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113181:28"/> ſpeake cleare otherwiſe ſometimes; denying the <hi>Brethren</hi> any <hi>rule or authority,</hi> reſerving it only to the <hi>Elders:</hi> As if you meant no more, but that the people did but yeeld con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the judgement of their <hi>Elders,</hi> by <hi>obedience</hi> to the will of Chriſt, and many ſuch like words. 5. But to the point in hand: The <hi>Iury</hi> then doth not repreſent the <hi>Brethren,</hi> but the <hi>Ruling Elders;</hi> which <hi>ruling Elders</hi> ſtand in ſtead of all the <hi>Brethren,</hi> as the <hi>Iury</hi> doth in ſtead of all the <hi>people;</hi> and ſo the <hi>priviledge</hi> of the people is ſaved. Otherwiſe, all the <hi>people</hi> ſhould be of the <hi>Iury,</hi> as all the <hi>Congregation</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by you, and others, to be <hi>Iudges</hi> of the offender. And the truth is, it is a <hi>liberty</hi> or <hi>priviledge</hi> to the party that is arraigned, that he may be judged by his <hi>Peeres;</hi> It is not a <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>Iury:</hi> So it is a priviledge for any <hi>accuſed brother,</hi> that he ſhall be tryed and judged by his <hi>Peeres,</hi> the <hi>ruling-Elders:</hi> It is no priviledge of the reſt of the <hi>Brethren</hi> to be his <hi>Iudges;</hi> as it is no priviledge of all the people at the Aſſizes, that they may claime a place in the <hi>Iury.</hi> 6. That which you adde, that there is great difference between the Iudge and Iury: [<hi>For</hi> (ſay you) <hi>though the Iury have given up their verdict, yet the malefactor is not thereupon legally condemned, much leſſe executed, but upon the ſentence of the Iudge.]</hi> This being rightly paralelld, will make againſt you: ſo, though the <hi>ruling-Elders</hi> (repreſenting the people,) give up their votes and judgement; yet the <hi>party</hi> is not excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, but upon the ſentence of the <hi>Paſtor.</hi> And indeed, the <hi>Iury</hi> rather ſeeme to acquit or condemne, than the <hi>Iudge;</hi> he doth but <hi>pronounce</hi> the ſentence, as they have adjudged it: ſo the <hi>ruling-Elders,</hi> being more in number, by <hi>votes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the cauſe, which is pronounced by the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and ſo the <hi>paralell</hi> is faire and full. But that all the people at the <hi>Aſsizes</hi> ſhould give up their <hi>verdict,</hi> as well as the <hi>Iury,</hi> is not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113181:29"/> in <hi>practiſe</hi> in the Common-wealth; and ſo ſpoiles the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell</hi> of the <hi>votes</hi> of all the <hi>Brethren</hi> in the Church. And yet you perſiſt to ſay: [<hi>The whole Church may be ſaid to bind and looſe, in that they conſent and concurre with the Elders, both in diſcerning it to be juſt, and in declaring their judgement, by lifting up of hands, or by ſilence, and after, by rejecting the party,</hi> &amp;c.] Iuſt as all the people at an Aſſizes, may be ſaid to condemne or acquit, becauſe they conſent with the <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Iury,</hi> both by diſcerning it to be juſt, and in declaring their <hi>judgement,</hi> by lifting up their hands, or by ſilence, and after, by rejecting the party. But what if the people doe not conſent (as diſcerning it not to be juſt) nor will reject the party? Is he then acquitted? Thus it muſt be, or it holds not proportion with the caſe in hand: For if the <hi>Brethren</hi> doe no more but <hi>approve</hi> and <hi>execute</hi> the ſentence of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> this is juſt nothing to the <hi>power of the keyes,</hi> intended to be given them, and is a meere <hi>paſsive</hi> priviledge. And that you may ſee your owne inconſtancy, conſider what you ſay elſewhere, page 11. [<hi>The Brethren ſtand in an Order, even in an orderly ſubjection, according to the order of the Goſpell</hi> page 15. <hi>They give conſent, in obedience to the will of Chriſt,</hi> page 37. <hi>They</hi> (the people) <hi>diſcerning the light and truth, readily yeeld obedience to their overſeers,</hi> page 41. <hi>That they may conſent to the judgement and ſentence of the Elders.</hi>] Had you kept your ſelfe conſtant to theſe <hi>expreſſions,</hi> you had both preſerved the <hi>truth</hi> of the Goſpell, and the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p>And now for a concluſion of this <hi>Section;</hi> Let me urge you with an argument of your owne, againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> page 39. [<hi>Hierome</hi> ſayes, <hi>the Churches were governed by the Common-councell of the Presbyters</hi>]<note n="*" place="margin">That nothing was done without their counſell, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was done without their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The way, <hi>page</hi> 31.</note> The Prelates evaſion is, <hi>[By their counſell asked, not followed:]</hi> You anſwer:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113181:29"/> 
                  <hi>This would imply a contradiction to</hi> Hieromes <hi>words: For in asking their counſell, and not following it, the Biſhop ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the church againſt their Councel, which is a contradiction.]</hi> So ſay I: The Church (ſay you) is governed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the <hi>Brethren:</hi> I aske, whether you meane their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and conſent <hi>asked</hi> only, or followed alſo. If the later, then the <hi>Brethren</hi> have as full authority with the <hi>Elders,</hi> as the <hi>Preſbyter,</hi> had with the <hi>Biſhop:</hi> If the former, it is a contradiction, to ſay, The Church is governed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the <hi>Brethren,</hi> and yet is governed againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; ſo that the queſtion clearly ſtated is this: <hi>[Whether the Brethren have ſuch concurrence and conſent, as that they have a negative vote, or caſting voice:]</hi> If they have, its that <hi>popular Anarchy,</hi> of you know whom: If not, its nothing to the <hi>power of the Keyes.</hi> Only, let me but remember you what elſewhere you ſay, concerning the <hi>peoples</hi> power in government of the Church:<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 100.</note> 
                  <hi>[In caſe the Officers doe erre, and commit offence, they ſhall be governed by the whole body of the Brethren; though otherwiſe, the Brethren are bound to obey and ſubmit to them in the Lord.]</hi> How you can recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe things I know not.</p>
               <p>But now you propound a ſad queſtion: <hi>[Whether the Church hath power of proceeding to the utmoſt cenſure of their whole Preſbytery.]</hi> Before I take your anſwer, I obſerve 1. That you might have made the queſtion alſo, whether the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> hath power to proceed to the utmoſt cenſure of the Church, and the Brethren the Epiſtolers, reſolve both negatively, <hi>Epiſt. p.</hi> 4. 2. That you ſuppoſe here, that the Church may proceed to ſome, though not to the utmoſt cenſure of their <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> and that (as you would ſeeme to deny it in your anſwer, ſo) is more than <hi>liberty,</hi> it is a great degree of Authority, not only over one of your members,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113181:30"/> but over your Overſeers: And now I ſhall view your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw. [It cannot</hi> (ſay you) <hi>be well conceived, that the whole Preſbytery ſhould be proceeded againſt, becauſe ſome, a ſtrong party perhaps, will ſide with them, and then the Church ought not to proceed, without conſulting with the Synod.] Reply.</hi> But 1. this is beſides the queſtion, which ſuppoſes the <hi>whole Preſbytery,</hi> and the <hi>whole Church</hi> oppoſed; and ſo your anſwer may ſeeme to intimate, that if none did ſide with them, the Church might proceed againſt them, and that to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> cenſure; but only in a <hi>diſsenſion</hi> of the Church, they may not. 2. If in any caſe, they ought not to proceed, doth not this deſtroy their <hi>independency,</hi> if they muſt fly to a <hi>Synod?</hi> No (ſay you) they ought only to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult</hi> the <hi>Synod.</hi> But if the <hi>Synod</hi> have no power to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and cenſure, they are ſtill but where they were. What if the Presbytery or Church will not ſubmit to their deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or <hi>Declaration?</hi> (for it is no more) what remedy hath the Church againſt their erring, hereticall, ſcandalous <hi>Preſbytery?</hi> If the <hi>Synod</hi> have a power of <hi>cenſure,</hi> then againe you deſtroy your <hi>Independency:</hi> No; <hi>[The Church may withdraw from them:]</hi> So they might before they <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted</hi> the <hi>Synod;</hi> nay, they were bound to doe it in your way, without <hi>conſulting</hi> the <hi>Synod.</hi> But you may call to mind your former thoughts. In your other Tract, you give them full power <hi>[to cenſure their Officers without any Officers;]</hi> as hath more then once been ſaid above.</p>
               <p>And thus your ſecond anſwer is alſo anſwered alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. You ſay, <hi>[Excommunication is one of the higheſt acts of Rule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>and</hi> ergo, <hi>cannot be performed but by ſome Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers;]</hi> Yet you contradict this f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly, in your other Tract, when you ſay; <hi>[In caſe of offence given by an Elder,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113181:30"/> or by the whole Elderſhip together, the Church hath Authority,</hi> (marke that, Authority, which in this Booke you oft deny) <hi>to require ſatisfaction of them; and if they doe not give due ſatiſfaction, to proceed to cenſure according to the quality of the offence.]</hi> And yet (which is ſtrange, me thinks) here you reſolve the cleane contrary: <hi>[The Church cannot excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the whole Preſbytery, becauſe they have not received from Chriſt an office of Rule, without their Officers.]</hi> But now if this reaſon be good, then on the other ſide it might ſeeme reaſonable; That the Presbytery might excommunicate the <hi>whole Church Apoſtate,</hi> becauſe they have received from Chriſt an <hi>office</hi> of <hi>Rule,</hi> without the Church: No, ſay you, <hi>[They muſt tell the Church, and joyne with the Church in that cenſure.]</hi> But this is to ſay and unſay: For if the Church muſt joyne with them, then the Church hath received ſome peece of an <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Rule,</hi> which was before denyed: If you ſay, they have not received any <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Rule,</hi> without their Officers; This may imply, that with their Officers they have received an <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Rule,</hi> which all this while you have ſeemed to deny, allowing them a Liberty, but no <hi>Rule</hi> or Authority. And whereas you ſay; <hi>[They muſt tell the Church, but that cannot be, when the Church is Apoſtate:]</hi> I rejoyne, this makes it reaſonable to me, That there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, to which they muſt tell the offence, by way of <hi>appeale;</hi> or elſe, both an erring Presbytery, or an Apoſtate Church, have no remedy to recover them, inſtituted by Chriſt; and ſo the Church, a multitude, or a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, is not ſo well provided for, as one particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>But you have found a remedy; <hi>[The Church wants not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to withdraw from them.]</hi> Is not this even <hi>tantamount</hi> with excommunication? Is it not the <hi>execution</hi> of that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113181:31"/> ſentence, <hi>to withdraw,</hi> eſpecially in your way. <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> is the contrary to <hi>communion.</hi> Now how doth the Church communicate their Elders? Take your owne words: [<hi>As they ſet up the Preſbytery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>by profeſsing their ſubjection to them in the Lord: ſo they avoid them</hi> (that is, in ſenſe, excommunicate them) <hi>by profeſsed withdrawing their ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from them, according to God</hi>] And this is as much as any <hi>people</hi> doe, or need to doe, to perſons <hi>excommunicate;</hi> unleſſe you grant them a power to the very Act and decree of <hi>excommunication;</hi> which as you have clearly done in your other Tract, ſo you doe here, giving them a power more than Miniſteriall, even a <hi>Kingly,</hi> and more than a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> power, when you ſay; [<hi>They rule the Church, by appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their owne Officers, and likewiſe in cenſuring offenders, not only by their Officers</hi> (which is as much as Kings are wont to doe) <hi>but alſo by their owne Royall aſſent, which Kings are not wont to doe, but only in the execution of Nobles.]</hi> Satis pro imperio.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The laſt Liberty of the Church, is Liberty of communion with other Churches, which is ſeven wayes exerciſed,</hi> &amp;c.] To this I ſay in generall: This is rather <hi>communion of Saints,</hi> than communion of Churches; becauſe in your way, every Church is <hi>independent,</hi> and hath no Church-ſtate, in relation to any, but its owne members. We ſuppoſe this <hi>communion</hi> is the liberty or priviledge of every Chriſtian, by vertue of his intereſt in the generall viſible Church, and not by any peculiar intereſt in a particular Congregation. He that is a profeſſed Chriſtian, and baptized, hath a right to all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, where ever he find them; As of old, he that was a <hi>Citizen of Rome,</hi> or ſo borne, was a freeman, through all the Romane Empire, and enjoyed the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of a <hi>Roman.</hi> A Chriſtian is a <hi>free Deacon</hi> in any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113181:31"/> part of the Chriſtian world; [<hi>A Citizen with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God,</hi> Eph. 2.19.] And this to me ſeemes reaſonable upon theſe grounds: 1. Becauſe every Chriſtian, not yet in a particular Church, or Congregation, is at liberty to joyne himſelfe to any Church, tyed by no <hi>obligation</hi> to one more than another. 2. Becauſe it is lawfull for any member of a particular Church, upon juſt reaſons to leave that Church, and to joyne himſelfe to another, and nothing can hinder his removall or communion with another Church, except he be ſcandalous, &amp;c. 3. It was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the firſt times, before Congregations were fixed, to adde them to the viſible Church, were their number leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer or greater, and give them communion in all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt. 4. Becauſe the whole viſible Church is but one City, one Kingdome, though for orders ſake, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſeverall Corporations. It is not ſo in <hi>civill</hi> reſpects; A <hi>Citizen</hi> of one Corporation, cannot goe and ſet up <hi>trade</hi> in another, becauſe they have their ſeverall <hi>Charters:</hi> But in the <hi>City</hi> of God, the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of Chriſt, there is but <hi>one Charter</hi> for all; and no more is required to admit a man a <hi>member</hi> of any Congregation, but that he profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Chriſtian, and live accordingly. Your <hi>New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> to tye men to your <hi>particular Church,</hi> that he may not <hi>remove,</hi> without a generall leave, will, I feare, prove a ſnare and a <hi>tyranny,</hi> worſe than yet we can imagine.</p>
               <p n="1">1. But come we to your particulars: [Firſt, <hi>by way of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Lords Supper, the members of one Church comming to another Church,</hi> &amp;c.] But 1. Why doe you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in this <hi>Ordinance</hi> only? Have not their children oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally borne there, a liberty alſo of <hi>Baptiſme?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Where neither of the parents can claim right to the Lords Supper; there their Infants cannot claime right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. The way, p. 81. Nor the childe of an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate perſon, <hi>p.</hi> 85.</note> The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is not adminiſtred with reſpect to this or that Church, but to the generall viſible Church:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113181:32"/> Unleſſe you hold, that a man or childe is baptized to no Church, but that particular, and an Infidell to all the reſt. Yet ſome of your brethren will hardly baptize a childe of any, but a member of their owne Church, which is next doore to <hi>Anabaptiſme.</hi> 2. I aske by what <hi>power of the keyes,</hi> doe your <hi>Paſtors</hi> admit a <hi>member</hi> of another Church, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> in yours? Or in what <hi>relation</hi> doth your <hi>Paſtor</hi> ſtand to that <hi>member</hi> of another Church? You ſay, <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> are relates, and he is a <hi>Paſtor</hi> to none but of his owne Church: Either then, to adminiſter the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> to a <hi>member</hi> of another Church, is no <hi>Paſtorall</hi> act, but may be done by a <hi>gifted brother:</hi> Or elſe, a <hi>Paſtor</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> are not ſo <hi>relates,</hi> but that he is a <hi>Paſtor</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the limits of his owne Congregation, which yet you doe deny. 3. You are alſo very ſparing in granting this <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty:</hi> For you adde; <hi>[In caſe, neither himſelfe, nor the Church from whence he comes, doe lye under any publicke of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.]</hi> But what if that <hi>party</hi> be free from the guilt of that offence? Shall the innocent ſuffer for the nocent? what <hi>charity,</hi> what <hi>juſtice</hi> is in this? 4. But your <hi>reaſon</hi> I like very well: <hi>[For we receive the Lords Supper, not only as a Seale of our Communion with the Lord Ieſus, and with his members in our owne Church, but alſo in all the Churches of the Saints:]</hi> Whence I inferre, then it is not any <hi>favour</hi> diſpenſed by you, to a <hi>member</hi> of another Church, but a <hi>dignity</hi> or privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, common to every member of that <hi>body,</hi> by vertue of that <hi>memberſhip,</hi> and not with reſpect to his <hi>particular</hi> Church memberſhip. And I pray, is not <hi>Baptiſme</hi> alſo a Seale of our Communion, with all the members of Chriſts body? Why then may you not admit the <hi>children</hi> of the members of any Church, to be baptized by your <hi>Paſtors,</hi> upon juſt occaſion, as well as to admit the <hi>parents</hi> to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113181:32"/> 
                  <hi>Lords Supper?</hi> Nay further: If the <hi>Sacraments</hi> be Seales of our <hi>communion</hi> with all the members of Chriſt, why doe you not admit any <hi>true Chriſtian,</hi> and his children, to the <hi>communion</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> though they be not as yet admitted members of any particular Congregation? How dare you deny any <hi>member</hi> of that <hi>Body, communion</hi> with its fellow-members, when it hath <hi>union</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with the <hi>Head?</hi> Conſider it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond way of your communion of Churches, is, [<hi>By way of recommendation as</hi> Paul <hi>in the behalfe of</hi> Phoebe, &amp;c.] But this is ſo farre from being any part of the <hi>power of the Keyes,</hi> that it is a <hi>duty,</hi> which a Church or party owe to any Chriſtian that is godly, not by vertue of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church-memberſhip, but by the common intereſt of Chriſtianity; yea, by the common right of <hi>humanity,</hi> even to an honeſt <hi>Heathen,</hi> according to the ninth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which requires us, <hi>to beare true witneſſe to our brother,</hi> if we be thereto required. The <hi>letters</hi> are only <hi>declarative,</hi> of the good behaviour of the party, occaſioned to remove to ſuch a place. Was this (thinke you) a part of the <hi>power of the Keyes,</hi> delivered to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles? Beſides, if there be any vertue in theſe <hi>letters,</hi> to admit a member into <hi>communion,</hi> is there not a like vertue in them, to <hi>excommunicate</hi> one ungodly? And if theſe <hi>letters</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſory have power to admit a member of one Church, to be a member of another, without any <hi>new covenanting,</hi> have they not the like power to admit the <hi>Paſtor</hi> of one Church, to be a <hi>Paſtor</hi> of another Church, without any <hi>new Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> which yet, I beleeve, you doe not practiſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>[By way of Conſultation;</hi> and 4 <hi>by Congregation into a Synod.]</hi> But what is all this to the <hi>power of the Keyes?</hi> If upon <hi>Congregation,</hi> and conſultation of other Church-Officers,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113181:33"/> there be not a binding power, it is rather a <hi>latch</hi> of a doore, which may be opened and ſhut at any bodies pleaſure, than a <hi>Key</hi> to let in, or locke out with any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But of the power of <hi>Synods</hi> more hereafter.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fifth way is: [<hi>The liberty of giving and receiving mutuall ſupplyes one from another; gifted men, or benevolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> &amp;c.] I conceive firſt, theſe are rather <hi>duties</hi> of common <hi>charity,</hi> than of Church <hi>liberty,</hi> or any <hi>power of the Keyes:</hi> And I deſire to know what thoſe <hi>gifted men</hi> were, that the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſent to other Countries? Were they not <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>Prophets,</hi> or <hi>Teachers</hi> in Office? Then they were <hi>Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Teachers</hi> by Office, before they were ſent, before they were elected or ordained by the Churches to which they were ſent. Thereupon it followes, that a <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Teacher</hi> (becauſe you may ſay a <hi>Paſtor</hi> relates to his owne flocke) a <hi>Teacher</hi> (ſo was <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Acts 13.1.) is a <hi>Teacher</hi> to the <hi>generall viſible Church,</hi> not to the <hi>particular</hi> Church only, as you hold. And then againe, a <hi>Teacher,</hi> quâ <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> may preach to another Church, and convert <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens;</hi> and not as a <hi>gifted brother</hi> only, as you ſometimes ſpeake.</p>
               <p>A ſixth way is, [<hi>By way of mutuall admonition, when a publicke offence is found amongſt them: One Church may ſend to admoniſh another, and if that Church will not heare, take two or three other Churches; and if not heare them, then withdraw,</hi> &amp;c.] This admonition is a <hi>duty</hi> of every brother, at leaſt of every Chriſtian, as a Chriſtian, and no <hi>power</hi> of the Keyes at all: And let it be conſidered, that the place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16.<note place="margin">Thoſe two or three are not conſidered as a Church-body, but as a ſufficient num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to joyne with a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offended, &amp;c. agreeing in a duty of brotherly love, &amp;c. The way, <hi>p.</hi> 53.</note> doth not make the admonition of one or more brethren, any <hi>power of the Keyes,</hi> but a <hi>duty</hi> only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning every man, in order to the cenſure of the Church: But if one or more Churches may proceed with a Church-offending,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113181:33"/> as private perſons with an offending brother; why may they not take the third ſtep, as the laſt remedy, to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate</hi> her, being obſtinate, as the Church doth an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o her? No; <hi>[Becauſe the Churches are all of equall authority:]</hi> But ſo are all the <hi>members</hi> of a Congregation of equall authority, yet the <hi>whole</hi> may excommunicate him: And if there be as much <hi>Church-communion</hi> between Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as there is between <hi>members</hi> of a <hi>particular</hi> Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; I ſee no reaſon, why many Churches aſſembled in a <hi>Synod,</hi> may not as well <hi>excommunicate</hi> an obſtinate Church, as a Congregation, a particular <hi>member.</hi> If you deny <hi>excommunication</hi> of a Church, others will (and doe) deny <hi>excommunication</hi> of a member, and ſay, <hi>non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> or <hi>withdrawing</hi> is as much as can be done. And if you ſay, the Churches may withdraw <hi>communion;</hi> I demand, firſt, what is that in effect, but <hi>excommunication,</hi> wanting only a <hi>Synodicall Decree;</hi> yet page 25. you ſay, <hi>[A Synod hath power to determine, to withdraw communion from an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Church:]</hi> And is it any more in the <hi>excommunic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion</hi> of an offending brother? They doe but determine all ſhall withdraw <hi>communion</hi> from him. This is therefore but a meere <hi>Logom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The laſt way of Communion of Churches, is, <hi>[by way of prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gation, or multiplication of Churches:]</hi> But 1. This is rather a <hi>diviſion</hi> of Churches, than either <hi>propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>multiplication:</hi> For theſe very Churches were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all one Church, now only <hi>divided</hi> into two The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the firſt Planters, did not thus <hi>propagate</hi> Churches; but went into places, where no Churches were, no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and there gathered and multiplyed Churches. We have enough of this <hi>diviſion</hi> of Churches, (ſince your way ſet up) but little of the <hi>propagation</hi> or <hi>multiplication.</hi> Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113181:34"/> and Apoſtolicall. For I pray Sir, tell us, next time you write over, how many Churches have you multiplyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>New-England?</hi> Not one, that I ever heard of: You have <hi>d vided</hi> Churches indeed, from <hi>old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but <hi>propagated</hi> none. And our <hi>Brethren</hi> at home, how many Churches have they divided and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtracted ſince their returne, but have <hi>multiplyed</hi> none? If ſome <hi>new Teachers</hi> ſhould ariſe in <hi>New England,</hi> and gather (or rather ſteale) ſome members out of every of your Congregations, would you call this <hi>multiplication</hi> of Churches, or rather <hi>diviſion?</hi> Had you gone into <hi>New England,</hi> and ſent out your <hi>Paſtors,</hi> (who are by calling, <hi>ſpirituall Fathers</hi>) to convert <hi>Indians,</hi> (as was pretended) or our <hi>Brethren</hi> here gone and ſent into <hi>Wales,</hi> and other parts, little better than <hi>heathens,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted them, and had <hi>gathered</hi> them into Churches, this had been a <hi>propagation</hi> of Churches indeed. But this they doe not, nor will doe, nor well can doe: For their opinion is, (and yours too in <hi>New England</hi>) that no <hi>Paſtor</hi> is a <hi>Paſtor</hi> to any, but his <hi>particular Congregation:</hi> ſo their <hi>Paſtors</hi> are only <hi>Nurſes</hi> to give ſucke, not <hi>ſpirituall Fathers,</hi> to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and beget children to God and his Church. That they leave to every <hi>gifted brother,</hi> to raiſe up ſeed to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and not to themſelves. For if once the <hi>children</hi> be borne, and a little growne up, then theſe <hi>(Fathers in Law)</hi> take them up, or rather <hi>ſteale</hi> them from them, who have ſpent their <hi>ſtrength</hi> in begetting, and breeding them, <hi>travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in paine,</hi> till Chriſt was formed in them. But if a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> and flocke be relates, is a <hi>Teacher</hi> ſo too? They may doe well then to ſend <hi>Teachers</hi> to beget children for their <hi>Paſtors;</hi> leſt it be ſaid: <hi>[No man in Office hath any ſkill, or will, or power, to propagate but only to divide Churches.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, why doe you call this a <hi>power of the Keyes;</hi> for a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113181:34"/> Church to <hi>ſend out a Congregation</hi> (as an <hi>Hive</hi> doth a ſwarm) when they are too full? This is <hi>their liberty,</hi> not yours. They have <hi>power</hi> without you, to gather themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to enter into a Church-way, and to chuſe their <hi>Officers,</hi> and doe all, as well as you had.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if <hi>Paſtors,</hi> quâ <hi>Paſtors,</hi> or <hi>Teachers,</hi> quâ <hi>Teachers,</hi> are tyed to a <hi>particular Congregation,</hi> then cannot they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigate Churches; only <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> can doe that: And ſo <hi>gifted Brethren,</hi> not Paſtors and Teachers, are the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Apoſtles: We thinke Paſtors and Teachers are Officers to the whole Church as the Apoſtles were; You will ſay, then they are Apoſtles: Firſt, will you ſay your <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> are Apoſtles, becauſe they goe abroad to convert and <hi>propagate</hi> Churches? Secondly, it followes not; That which made the Apoſtles differ from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, is delivered by your ſelfe, to ſtand in two things: 1.<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 32.</note> [<hi>That an Apoſtle had in him in all miniſteriall power of all the Officers of the Church.</hi> 2. <hi>That Apoſtolicall power exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all Churches as much as to any one.</hi>] But withall you ſay, <hi>[That this power conjoyned in them, is now divided by them, amongſt all the Churches, and all the Officers of the Churches reſpectively.]</hi> I aske then, what Officer of the Church hath power to plant and propagate Churches? Your <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> are no <hi>Officers</hi> of the Church: I hope, <hi>Ruling Elders</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> are tyed as well to their <hi>particular</hi> Churches, as the Paſtors and Teachers; <hi>ergo,</hi> it muſt fall upon the Paſtors and Teachers, or there is no ſuch thing now, as <hi>propagation</hi> of Churches. But take once more your owne grant in this Paragraph, where now we are: [<hi>Though the Apoſtles be dead, whoſe Office it was to plant and gather Churches; yet the worke is not dead, but the ſame power of the Keyes is left with the Churches in common,</hi> &amp;c.] Marke, firſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113181:35"/> you call it a <hi>power of the keyes,</hi> to plant and gather Churches, and an <hi>Office</hi> of the Apoſtles: But this <hi>power</hi> of the Keyes, this <hi>Office</hi> is not bequeathed to <hi>gifted Brethren,</hi> nor to <hi>Ruling-Elders,</hi> or <hi>Deacons; ergo,</hi> it is left to the Paſtors or Teachers. Next, you ſay, the ſame <hi>power</hi> of the Keyes is left with the Churches in common: You ſhould ſay, with the Paſtors or Teachers of the Church, or with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches indeed, but in the hands of her Officers: Otherwiſe, you make not only the <hi>brethren,</hi> but <hi>ſiſters</hi> too (according to their meaſure, as you ſpeake) Fathers and Mothers <hi>[To propagate and inlarge the Kingdome of Chriſt, throughout all generations, as God ſhall give opportunity.]</hi> But were it ſo, yet then much more would it concerne the Paſtors and Teachers (the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, if they have any at all) to propagate and inlarge the Kingdome of Chriſt, as God ſhall give opportunity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Subject of the Key of Authority.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Key of Authority or Rule is committed to the Elders of the Church, and ſo the Act of Rule is proper to their Office.]</hi> But, me thinks, you ſhould have done well, to diſtinguiſh both of Authority and Rule, and alſo of <hi>Elders,</hi> preaching from thoſe they call <hi>Ruling-Elders:</hi> For Authority and Rule may be diſtinguiſhed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113181:35"/> there is Rule in thoſe that are called <hi>Ruling-Elders,</hi> but not Authority to preach and adminiſter Sacraments: I would not have noted it, but that you confuſedly reckon up the <hi>particulars</hi> of Authority and Rule, without diſtinction, what belongs to one ſort of <hi>Elders,</hi> what to another; As if they did equally belong to both.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is: [<hi>That which the Eld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs, who labour in the Word and Doctrine, are to attend unto chiefly,</hi> that is, <hi>the preaching of the word, and the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>] For the firſt, <hi>[the preaching of the Word,]</hi> ſome of your <hi>Brethren</hi> ſay, that private <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> may prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, that is, preach, and others ſay they may baptize too; who yet are denyed power in ruling, as being not <hi>Elders,</hi> not Officers, to whom the Act of Ruling is proper: Indeed you ſeeme to deny <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> power to propheſie publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but your <hi>Prefacers</hi> write, <hi>Magiſter hic non tenetur.</hi> Yet their owne reſolution of the caſe, and their practiſe doth not well agree. They ſay, a gifted Brother may <hi>[occaſionally preach, not in an ordinary courſe.]</hi> But we ſee, they doe it <hi>ordinarily</hi> and conſtantly; witneſſe all their <hi>Lecturers,</hi> their double and treble beneficed Lecturers; and one who takes a Benefice, (but perhaps not the charge of ſoules, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of <hi>Sacraments</hi>) where he conſtantly <hi>preaches.</hi> If you ſay, <hi>They are Elders or Paſtors:</hi> I anſwer, they are ſo, to their owne <hi>ſelect Congregations,</hi> but they are but as <hi>gifted Brethren</hi> to other Congregations; for their principle is, <hi>[Paſtor and flocke are relates:]</hi> which, if it be not a <hi>fine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion,</hi> let the world judge. We deny not, but <hi>gifted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> of ſuch abilities as are fit for Office, for learning and judgement, &amp;c. may for <hi>approbation,</hi> exerciſe their gifts. But we only note the difference of theſe <hi>Maſters;</hi> and that theſe of ours are nearer to <hi>Browniſme;</hi> who by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113181:36"/> preaching as <hi>gifted Brethren,</hi> countenance and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>private members,</hi> ſuppoſing themſelves gifted ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to preach ordinarily; yea, and to adminiſter the <hi>Seales,</hi> which as it is leſſe<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt ſent me not to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, but to preach the Goſpell.</note> than preaching, ſo alſo is <hi>annexed unto preaching,</hi> Mat. 28. as your ſelfe here ſpeakes, and complaine of this practiſe, <hi>page</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond Act of Authority common to the Elders, is, <hi>[They have power to call the Church together.]</hi> 1. You ſaid before, <hi>Rule</hi> was an Act proper to the Office of <hi>Elders:</hi> Now you ſay it is common, you meane perhaps common to both ſorts of Elders: But then you ſhould have explained the difference, or reſolved us, whether the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> have equall power with the <hi>preaching Elders</hi> in this Act. For your inſtance of the Apoſtles, calling the Church to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2. is but for one ſort of Elders, and you bring nothing for the other. 2. Beſides, <hi>to call the Church toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſeemes rather a matter of Order, than of Authority: For one <hi>Elder</hi> of either ſort, may be deputed to this worke. But if this be proper to <hi>Elders,</hi> what if the <hi>Elders</hi> be all offenders, who ſhall call the Church together then? Truly, this power ſeemes firſt to be in the Church, in your way; who as they had <hi>power</hi> to gather themſelves into one Body, without <hi>Officers,</hi> ſo much more, to call an Aſſembly of themſelves. That of <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. for the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> is weakly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged: For it appeares not that they were called on, to call an Aſſembly, (but only to <hi>weep, v.</hi> 17.) it was rather the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> Act to proclaime a Faſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>[To examine all, members or Officers, before they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Church.]</hi> But this, according to your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, is ſpoken to the <hi>whole Church,</hi> and ſo no proper Act of <hi>Elders.</hi> And expreſſely above, you made this one part of the <hi>priviledge</hi> or liberty of the people, to <hi>propound</hi> juſt excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113181:36"/> againſt ſuch as offer themſelves; and if ſo, then alſo to examine them, <hi>page</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth Act of their <hi>Rule,</hi> is, <hi>[Ordination of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.]</hi> But 1. This is too confuſed: What <hi>Elders</hi> doe you meane? Preaching or Ruling? Have the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> power of <hi>Ordination</hi> of Paſtors and Teachers? This, as it is without all <hi>preſident</hi> of Scripture, ſo it is againſt a Rule: <hi>[The greater is bleſſed of the leſſer;]</hi> which cannot be by the Apoſtles Divinity. 2. This is no Act proper to the <hi>Elders,</hi> but common to the <hi>Brethren,</hi> by your owne judgement, if your minde be not altered ſince you writ, <hi>The Way, p.</hi> 50, 51. See it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>[To open the doores of ſpeech and ſilence in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.]</hi> But 1. one <hi>Elder</hi> doth this; <hi>ergo,</hi> one <hi>Elder</hi> hath <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> not over the Church only, but over his <hi>fellow Elders</hi> alſo. 2. You take it from them preſently in ſome caſes: [<hi>When the Elders themſelves lye under offence, the Brethren have liberty to require ſatisfaction,</hi> &amp;c.] That is, the Brethren may open the doore, and begin to ſpeake. And ſtill you are confuſed, not declaring whether this <hi>power</hi> belongs to either ſort of <hi>Elders,</hi> or both alike; eſpecially your inſtance of the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the Synagogue, ſeeming to carry it to the <hi>Ruling Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. [<hi>To prepare matters before hand for the Church, and to reject cauſeleſſe and diſorderly complaints,</hi> &amp;c.] But doe not you hold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. to ſpeake of the Church of the <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> with the <hi>Elders?</hi> then that place is impertinently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, to prove an Act proper to the <hi>Elders.</hi> 2. Have the <hi>Elders</hi> power to judge a complaint to be cauſeleſſe, and to <hi>reject</hi> it, without the cognizance of the people? why then have they not power to <hi>judge</hi> a complaint to be juſt, and to <hi>cenſure</hi> it, without their cognizance alſo? Doe you not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113181:37"/> 
                  <hi>intrench</hi> a little too much upon your peoples <hi>Liberty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. [<hi>The Elders have authority in handling an offence, before the Church, both</hi> jus dicere, <hi>and</hi> ſententiam ferre.] But all this, I thinke the Browniſts yeeld, who yet give the chiefe, if not the only <hi>power</hi> to the people; and give the <hi>Elders</hi> leave, <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam ferre,</hi> to pronounce the ſentence, as their mouth and Deputies. And you ſay: [<hi>They are firſt to informe the Church, what the Law of Chriſt is, which is,</hi> jus dicere; <hi>and then when the Church diſcerneth the ſame, and condiſcendeth to it, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to give ſentence.</hi>] But what if the people <hi>diſcerne</hi> it not, or condiſcend not, that the ſentence ſhall paſſe? Then they may have power, <hi>jus dicere,</hi> which every underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding brother hath, but not <hi>ſententiam ferre:</hi> A goodly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority!</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>[They have power to diſmiſſe the Church, with a Bleſsing.]</hi> To this I ſay little; only I ſay, it is too confuſed, what <hi>Elders</hi> you meane, <hi>preaching</hi> or <hi>Ruling?</hi> and then, I ſay, this is but a matter of <hi>Order,</hi> one only does it, and yet I thinke you will not ſay, he hath Authority over his fellowes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. [<hi>The Elders have power to charge any of the people in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, that they live not inordinately,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. &amp;c.] This is very weakly alleadged by a man of your ſtrength: The Apoſtle ſpeaks this to all the <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> yea, it may concerne <hi>women</hi> ſometimes, to warne the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, eſpecially being to be done in private; and doe you bring this for the <hi>power</hi> of your <hi>Elders?</hi> which ſort of <hi>Elders</hi> doth it concerne to doe this, for neither are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned? Againe, the Apoſtle ſpeaks not of charging or warning at all; but peremptorily bids them withdraw, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and to [<hi>note him by a Letter, and have no company with him,</hi> v. 14.]</p>
               <p n="10">10. [<hi>If the Church fall away to blaſphemy againſt Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113181:37"/> &amp;c. <hi>and no Synod hoped for, or no help by it; The Elders have power to withdraw the Diſciples from them, and to carry away the Ordinances with them,</hi> &amp;c.] But 1. the caſe is miſlaid; for <hi>Acts</hi> 19.9. the Jewes that there blaſphemed, were not of the Church; but only ſuch as came to heare <hi>Paul</hi> preach, which an Infidell might doe; but then this was no proper <hi>withdrawing,</hi> as a <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Keyes:</hi> For what had <hi>Paul</hi> to doe, or the <hi>Elders</hi> with them that are without. 2. Suppoſe the <hi>whole Church</hi> fall away, what ſhall the <hi>Elders</hi> doe now? They may not <hi>excommunicate</hi> them, you ſaid above; and if they may <hi>withdraw,</hi> thats no more power than the <hi>Brethren</hi> have of the <hi>Elders</hi> Apoſtate. 3. How can the <hi>Elders</hi> carry away the <hi>Ordinances</hi> from them? For firſt the <hi>Elders</hi> ceaſe to be <hi>Elders,</hi> when the <hi>flocke</hi> is ſeparated, and ceaſes to be their <hi>flocke.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Brethren</hi> may keep the <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> with them, and have power in your way, to chuſe new <hi>Officers,</hi> to exerciſe the <hi>Ordinances;</hi> and then what care they for their <hi>withdrawing,</hi> either themſelves or the Ordinances? 4. It ſeemes not juſtifiable, that <hi>Elders</hi> ſhould withdraw, and carry away the Ordinances from a company of erring Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. The Prophets of old did not ſo, but continued ſtill to preach, though the people were obſtinate: For this is the remedy to cure their obſtinacy, and ſo the Apoſtle directs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25, 26.</p>
               <p>In the cloſe of this Chapter, you propound a queſtion: <hi>[If the Elders have this power of Rule, how are they then the ſervants of the Church?]</hi> You anſwer by a ſimilitude: [<hi>A Queen may call her ſervants her mariners, to conduct her over Sea; yet they being called by her to ſuch an Office, ſhe muſt not rule them in ſteering their courſe,</hi> &amp;c.] If ſuch be the caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church and her Elders (as you ſay it is) I ſee little or no difference between you and the Browniſts; For they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113181:38"/> make the Church a Queen, and the Elders but her ſervants, called by her to ſuch an <hi>Office;</hi> to exerciſe the power of the <hi>Keyes</hi> in her name: You ſay here, [<hi>The Elders rule the Church from Chriſt, and ſo from their call;</hi> and above, ſect. 7. <hi>The Church condiſcending to the information of the Elders, what the Law of Chriſt is, it is a further act of the Elders power, to give ſentence againſt the offender.</hi>] Juſt as the <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> when the <hi>Queene,</hi> who hath called him to that <hi>Office,</hi> tels him ſhe is reſolved to goe to ſuch a place, puts her command in <hi>execution,</hi> by ſteering his courſe to that place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Authority of Synods.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that you acknowledge <hi>Synods</hi> as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt, and ſet downe the <hi>cauſes</hi> of aſſembling Churches into <hi>Synods,</hi> we ſhall eaſily agree with you: The maine contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is about their <hi>power.</hi> Concerning which you move three queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Q.</hi> What power it is they have received; which you thus reſolve: <hi>[Not only to counſell and give light, but alſo to command and enjoyne things to be beleeved and done.]</hi> But this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113181:38"/> (as was noted in your Prefacers Epiſtle) is but an empty grant. For you meane it rather materially, than formally, by any Authority the <hi>Synod</hi> hath to bind them to obedience or cenſure: Yes, formally (you ſay) <hi>[from the authority of the Synod, which being an Ordinance of Chriſt, bindeth the more for the Synods ſake.]</hi> But the great ſcruple is,<note place="margin">To make their counſell the more weighty and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but not to inveſt them with more rule or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The way, <hi>p</hi> 51.</note> what kind of Authority this is, whether it differ <hi>ſpecifically</hi> from the power of a ſingle <hi>Paſtor,</hi> or of a <hi>Congregationall Preſbytery,</hi> or only <hi>gradually,</hi> as a greater <hi>teſtimony;</hi> for ſo ſome of yours under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it: If in this latter ſenſe, I ſee not how it can be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt, or <hi>authority</hi> diſtinct from the Authority of one ſingle <hi>Paſtor:</hi> For he hath Authority <hi>miniſterially</hi> to declare and command people, what God commands and declares to be his will, <hi>with all Authority:</hi> And this ſeemes to be your meaning; for you ſay <hi>[A truth of the Goſpell taught by a Miniſter, bindeth to faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, not only becauſe it is Goſpell, but alſo becauſe it is taught by a Miniſter for his callings ſake.]</hi> Now ſuppoſe 20, or 40, or more <hi>Paſtors</hi> met together, teach and declare a truth of the Goſpell; &amp; <hi>enjoyne</hi> it to their ſeverall Congregations, by way of a <hi>Decree;</hi> I aske what difference is there between this Authority of theirs, and the Authority of any one of them ſingle? If you ſay, none but <hi>graduall,</hi> then I ſay, they have no Authority as a <hi>Synod,</hi> but as <hi>Paſtors:</hi> If you ſay, <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall,</hi> that is, <hi>juridicall,</hi> whereas a <hi>Paſtors</hi> is but <hi>doctrinall,</hi> you yeeld the cauſe as we would have it. But then they have a power, not only of <hi>decreeing,</hi> which one Paſtor hath not; but alſo of <hi>cenſuring</hi> upon the diſobedience of the people, which you will not eaſily grant. Againe, I thinke you take the <hi>authority</hi> of a <hi>Preſbytery</hi> in a Congregation, to be an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt, and to differ, not only <hi>gradually,</hi> but <hi>ſpecifically;</hi> And the authority of a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> or <hi>Teacher,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:113181:39"/> or <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> ſingle. Now it may ſeeme ſtrange, if a <hi>Synod</hi> be an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt (as you grant) that a <hi>ſingle Preſbytery</hi> ſhould have a <hi>juridicall authority,</hi> to decree and cenſure; and yet a <hi>Synod,</hi> which is a <hi>Preſbytery</hi> of <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries,</hi> ſhould have but only a <hi>doctrinall</hi> authority: You may rather deny <hi>Synods</hi> to be an Ordinance of Chriſt, and call them (as your Prefacers call the firſt <hi>Synod</hi> of the Apoſtles) a <hi>Conſultation,</hi> or if you will, a <hi>Reference by way of Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for deciding of controverſies, &amp;c. Which the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches (unleſſe they bind themſelves by promiſe) need not ſtand to, but may plead their owne <hi>Liberty.</hi> But (ſay you) <hi>[they have a power, (if they cannot heale the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) to determine to withdraw communion from them.]</hi> This power all the Brethren have, as to withdraw from their <hi>owne Elders, apoſtate:</hi> ſo from other <hi>Churches obſtinate,</hi> againſt their admonitions. Or if you place any <hi>emphaſis</hi> in the word <hi>(determine)</hi> that is, to <hi>decree</hi> a ſeparation from them; then you give them a <hi>juridicall power,</hi> which is aequivalent with the power of <hi>excommunication,</hi> whereof withdrawing is but the execution.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Q. [How far the Fraternity may concurre with the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the power of the Synod.]</hi> You reſolve it in 3 particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: 1. [<hi>They have liberty to diſpute their doubts among the Elders,</hi> Acts 15.7.12.] The place I thinke is much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken. The <hi>diſputation,</hi> for ought appeares, was amongſt the Apoſtles and Elders, before the Brethren; not by the Brethren. And when in <hi>v.</hi> 12. the whole multitude are ſaid to keep ſilence, it proves not that they did diſpute: For 1. certainly that had been too much confuſion, for a multitude to ſpeake all at once. 2. Their ſilence now, argues not that they diſputed before;<note place="margin">Acts 21.40. &amp; 22.2.</note> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifies no more but this; they were quiet, or held their peace from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113181:39"/> noiſe or murmurings, uſuall with multitudes, as at an Aſſizes; we feare it; they hearkened attentively. 2. <hi>[They had liberty to joyne with the Apoſtles and Elders, in approving the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and determining the ſame, as the common ſentence of them all.]</hi> That they had a liberty to joyne in approving the ſentence, is no more than the multitude at an Aſſizes have to joyne with the Judge in approving of his ſentence: But that they joyned in <hi>determining</hi> the ſame, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſentence of them all, is far more than the multitude have at the Aſſizes, and is as full Authority as the <hi>Elders</hi> have; And yet this you preſently deny, when you ſay: [<hi>Yet the Authority of the Decrees lay chiefly</hi> (if not only) <hi>in the Apoſtles and Elders<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>] The Apoſtles and Elders did no more but joyne with <hi>Iames</hi> in determining the ſentence, as the common ſentence of them all. 3 <hi>[They had liberty to joyne with the Apoſtles and Elders, in chuſing and ſending meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and writing Synodall Letters, in the names of all.]</hi> If you meant no more than a <hi>paſsive</hi> approbation, it might be yeelded; but if you meane an <hi>actuall,</hi> or <hi>active</hi> concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that they had not been valid without their <hi>votes</hi> and conſent; its far more than <hi>liberty,</hi> as good <hi>authority</hi> as any the Apoſtles and Elders had.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But Elders in a <hi>Synod</hi> have no authority to <hi>determine</hi> any act to bind the Churches, but according to their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. You anſwer: <hi>[We doe not ſo apprehend it: For what need Churches ſend to a Synod for light and direction, if they be reſolved afore hand, how far they will goe?] Reply:</hi> Here either you deſtroy the <hi>liberty</hi> of the Brethren, afore granted, and give the <hi>Synod</hi> a binding power, which you ſeeme to deny? or elſe <hi>prevaricate</hi> in this cauſe. For according to your principles, the <hi>Synod</hi> hath no power to bind the Churches to ſtand to their <hi>arbitrement</hi> (for thats the true power of your
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113181:40"/> 
                  <hi>Synods</hi>) under any penall cenſure; only they may <hi>withdraw;</hi> And then I returne you your owne words: [<hi>What need Churches ſend to a Synod for light and direction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if they be reſolved afore hand, how far they will goe?</hi>]</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Q. [Whether the Synod hath power to enjoyne things both in their nature and uſe indifferent.]</hi> You reſolve it nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. [<hi>From the patterne of Synods,</hi> Acts 15.28. <hi>who enjoyned nothing but neceſſaries, in nature or uſe.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> This is an Argument from Scripture, <hi>negativè;</hi> they did not here enjoyne any thing but neceſſaries; <hi>ergo,</hi> they had no power to enjoyne things indifferent: The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is naught. 2. [<hi>The Apoſtles are commanded to teach what Chriſt commanded;</hi> ergo, <hi>if they teach more, they exceed their commiſsion.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> This Argument is like the former: They were to teach what Chriſt commanded; <hi>ergo,</hi> they might teach nothing elſe in things indifferent: They might teach nothing as a <hi>commandement</hi> of Chriſt <hi>doctrinally,</hi> in matters of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>worſhip;</hi> but this hinders not, but they might enjoyne ſome things indifferent; as they did forbid the uſe of ſome things indifferent in their owne nature; <hi>viz. bloud,</hi> and <hi>ſtrangled.</hi> If it be ſaid, thoſe were not <hi>indifferent in their uſe,</hi> at that time: I anſwer; There is nothing in the <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall,</hi> properly indifferent in the <hi>uſe;</hi> becauſe it fals under ſome generall rules of Scripture; and ſo is to be uſed or not uſed accordingly: The queſtion therefore ſhould be; <hi>[Whether a Synod may enjoyne (or forbid) the uſe of a thing in its owne nature indifferent?]</hi> And then I ſhould anſwer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively, and defend my ſelfe by this very preſident of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. Who did forbid the uſe of ſomethings in their owne nature indifferent? I would not therefore
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113181:40"/> anſwer: <hi>[Chriſt ſpeaketh only of teaching ſuch things which he had commanded, as neceſſary to ſalvation:]</hi> But I would ſay, Chriſt ſpeaks of matters of <hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>worſhip:</hi> That they ſhould teach nothing to be beleeved, as a <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Faith: or practiſed as a part of Gods worſhip, but what he had commanded them. Otherwiſe the Apoſtles did goe beyond their <hi>commiſsion,</hi> in teaching as <hi>neceſſary,</hi> to abſtaine from bloud, &amp;c. which Chriſt never commanded them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forbad, in abrogating the Ceremoniall Law. And whereas you ſay; [<hi>The Apoſtle</hi> 1 Cor. 14.40. <hi>doth not at all enjoyne, nor allow the Church to enjoyne ſuch things as decent, whoſe want or whoſe contrary is not undecent: nor ſuch orders, whoſe want or contrary would be no diſorder.</hi>] I anſwer: that for men to pray or propheſie with their heads covered, or with long haire, and women uncovered, were things in their owne nature indifferent (unleſſe you make it neceſſary, as a morall duty, for men to pray or propheſie uncovered, and women <hi>contra;</hi> which no Interpreters upon that Text doe) and yet the Apoſtle enjoynes the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſo to doe; <hi>ergo,</hi> the <hi>Synod</hi> may doe ſo too: And for your inſtance of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a gowne; [<hi>A gowne</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is a decent garment to preach in, yet ſuch an injunction (for Miniſters to preach in a gowne) is not grounded upon that Text of the Apoſtle: For then, a Miniſter in neglecting to preach in a gowne, ſhould neglect the commandement of the Apoſtle; which yet he doth not; for if he preach in a cloake, he preacheth decently enough.</hi>] True, he ſins not in point of <hi>decency;</hi> but ſuppoſing ſuch a cuſtome in a Church (as the cuſtome was for men, amongſt <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> to preach uncovered, and the women to be convened in the Congregations) the <hi>Synod</hi> might enjoyne all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to preach in a gowne, (as the Apoſtle did enjoyne them to preach uncovered) and he that ſhall preach in a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113181:41"/> cloke, preaches <hi>decently</hi> indeed, but not <hi>orderly;</hi> and ſo ſins againſt the Apoſtles rule of <hi>order,</hi> though not of <hi>decency.</hi> You ſo ſpeake, as if there were only one Rule to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or two at moſt, in the uſe of things indifferent; whereas there are at leaſt five to that purpoſe: And by the ſame reaſon, that the Apoſtle enjoynes men to keep <hi>decency,</hi> he enjoynes to keep <hi>order;</hi> and ſo other rules, concerning things indifferent. Doth not the Apoſtle complaine of diſorder in the <hi>Corinthians</hi> preaching covered? yet the contrary Order was not neceſſary, but in it ſelfe indifferent. The eating of things offered to <hi>Idols,</hi> was a thing in it ſelfe, before that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of the Apoſtles, indifferent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8. yet was now forbidden: If you ſay, this was <hi>offenſive to the Iewes,</hi> and <hi>ergo</hi> neceſſary <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc:</hi> I anſwer, this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon made it neceſſary only, where ſuch eating was knowne to be offenſive, but the <hi>Canon</hi> made it neceſſary every where.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third reaſon is taken (you ſay) from the nature of the [<hi>Miniſteriall Office in Church or Synod: which is ſtewardly, not Lordly, and</hi> ergo, <hi>they may diſpenſe no more injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to Gods houſe, than Chriſt hath appointed them.</hi>] I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, its true, he may diſpenſe nothing as an <hi>inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt, but what he hath commanded: But yet a <hi>Steward</hi> may require of the Family, and enjoyne them the uſe of things in themſelves indifferent, for Order and <hi>uniformity.</hi> As that all ſhall meet in ſuch an houre, in ſuch a place, to prayers, &amp;c. So I thinke you doe in your owne Churches. It is indifferent to receive the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> at Morning or at Evening, yet ſome of you enjoyne it to be done at Evening. It is indifferent to <hi>baptize,</hi> in a river, in a paile, in a Font, in a Baſon; yet, I beleeve, you enjoyne one of theſe, and forbid the other. And whereas you ſay, <hi>[Chriſt in theſe things never
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113181:41"/> provided for uniformity, but only for unity.]</hi> I anſwer: then the Apoſtle exceeded his <hi>commiſsion,</hi> in enjoyning the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> uniformity, in their orderly praying or prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying; yea, <hi>unity</hi> is much preſerved by <hi>uniformity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you propound à queſtion; <hi>[Whether a Synod hath power of Ordination or excommunication:]</hi> And anſwer 1. <hi>That you doubt it was not ſo from the beginning.</hi> 2. <hi>That if any ſuch occaſion ſhould ariſe amongſt you, you</hi> (in a Synod) <hi>ſhould determine it fit to be done, but referre the adminiſtration of both, to the Preſbytery of ſeverall Churches.</hi>] So perhaps would the Presbyteriall Churches. But the queſtion is, what is to be done, if the Officers of the particular Churches be dead, or hereticall, who then ſhall doe thoſe acts? Either the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> muſt doe it, but that you refuſe, or a <hi>Claſsis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 50, 51.</note> or a <hi>Preſbytery</hi> of another Congregation; but that you alſo deny, as <hi>having no warrant:</hi> Then it followes, the Brethren without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers muſt both ordaine <hi>Elders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 100.</note> and <hi>excommunicate</hi> offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; which you fully grant in the other Tract. But as clearly contradict in this, as is evident in the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, for <hi>Synodicall Ordination, [that</hi> Matthias <hi>was ſo called to be an Apoſtle,</hi> Acts 1.] you anſwer: <hi>[It appeares not, they acted them in a Synodicall way.]</hi> But I pray Sir, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what you ſaid above, concerning that <hi>Synod,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>[That it riſe up to be a Synod, or generall Councell, by the Apoſtles preſence, they being Elders of all the Churches.]</hi> So it may be ſaid of that Aſſembly, Acts 1. the <hi>Apoſtles preſence,</hi> and the <hi>whole Church,</hi> then extant, there aſſembled, made it a <hi>Synod;</hi> and if ſo, then in a <hi>Synod,</hi> there was an Apoſtle ordained: If I may uſe that word of an Apoſtle, which I may the better to doe, by your grants, who urge the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>[he was voted by the common ſuffrages of them
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113181:42"/> all.]</hi> And if an Apoſtle, much more a <hi>Deacon,</hi> or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as <hi>Acts</hi> 6. in another like Aſſembly. The other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> impoſing hands upon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to that Office (of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip) by the impoſition of hands of ſome Officers or members of the Church: The way, <hi>p.</hi> 45</note> was not indeed an <hi>Ordination,</hi> properly ſo called, though you call it a <hi>[ſeparation of them to the worke of the Apoſtleſhip.]</hi> nor in a Synod, but in a particular Church; yet it was in a Presbytery of Prophets and Teachers, perhaps of ſeverall Churches, there occaſionally met, and yeelds us this inſtruction; That <hi>Elders</hi> of one or more Churches, may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hands, that is, ordaine (in your ſenſe) <hi>Elders</hi> imployed in other Churches; for ſo were <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas.</hi> Whence we would inferre two things more: 1. That if a <hi>Claſsis</hi> or <hi>Preſbytery</hi> may ordaine, then may a <hi>Synod</hi> ordaine. 2. That however the people or Brethren have no power to ordaine or impoſe hands: for thoſe were <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> that impoſed hands on <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this Chapter: whereas you ſaid, [<hi>The Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>did diſpenſe no cenſure againſt the falſe Teachers, an evident argument, they left the cenſure to the particular Churches.]</hi> I anſwer: This is an Argument like the former: They diſpenſed no cenſure, <hi>ergo,</hi> they had no power, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they revoked their errour, and repented, and ſo there was no need: However, the <hi>Synod</hi> could not cenſure them, till they knew them obſtinate. What was after done, we know not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:113181:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The firſt Subject of all this Power; and of Independency.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Etting paſſe what is ſaid of Chriſt, the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Subject of all power, as out of all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, we conſider only what you ſay of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall</hi> power.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> [A <hi>particular Church, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Saints, is the firſt ſubject of all the Church-offices, with all their ſpirituall gifts and power,</hi>] 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, &amp;c. But, under favour, all the Texts produced to prove the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, are miſtaken, or miſapplyed. The firſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. is not ſpoken to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> or any other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, as a peculiar <hi>priviledge</hi> unto them; but either, of all Saints in the world, or of thoſe in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> as Saints, not promiſcuouſly of the whole Church, as a Church, conſiſting of good and bad: For, was <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos;</hi> was life and death, were <hi>things preſent,</hi> and <hi>things to come,</hi> given to wicked men and hypocrites in that Church? was <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle, and <hi>Cephas</hi> another, given as a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar priviledge to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> only? Yea, is not this meant of the <hi>inviſible myſticall Church,</hi> and not of any particular Church? For the ſecond, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. you ſay, <hi>[Theirs was ſuch a Church, of whom it is ſaid; They came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113181:43"/> into one place.]</hi> But we have told you, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, this was not ſuch a Church as you deſcribed, <hi>[A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Saints profeſsing the faith]</hi> without their Officers: which I thinke you meane here alſo; (for theſe things are taken out of, The way, <hi>p.</hi> 1.) This was a Church that had many Officers. The third Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. is not meant of a particular Church. For I pray, were the Apoſtles ſet in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> only, as a particular Church? Were not they Miniſters of all, and given to all Churches? Your labour about <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſome,</hi> to referre it to the Apoſtles, is but a meere <hi>criticiſme;</hi> for let it be <hi>ſome,</hi> or <hi>which,</hi> it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not. For thoſe Apoſtles or Prophets were not ſet in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> as the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> thereof, but in the generall <hi>viſible Church:</hi> ſo the paralell place, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. is neceſſarily meant of the Church of Saints, or the body of Chriſt generally, or indefinitely, not of this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church. What weake proofes are theſe, for a propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of ſo great concernment, as being the very foundation of the <hi>Independent</hi> Government?</p>
               <p>But you read of no <hi>Nationall</hi> Church, nor <hi>Nationall</hi> Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers given to them by Chriſt: Yet (ſay we) we reade of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers more than <hi>Nationall,</hi> given to the Churches, even <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall,</hi> as Apoſtles and Prophets: And ſome thinke we reade of <hi>Nationall</hi> Officers, ſuch was <hi>Titus</hi> for <hi>Crete;</hi> as an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, though we take theſe to be extraordinary. 2. We read of <hi>Nationall</hi> Churches, living under one common go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as the Churches of <hi>Galatia;</hi> yet but one Church; and the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> had many Congregations, yet but one Church: And if many Congregations may be called one Church in a City; why all the Congregations in a <hi>Nation,</hi> may not be called one <hi>Nationall Church,</hi> I ſee no great reaſon? Not indeed in a <hi>typicall</hi> ſenſe, as the Church
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:113181:43"/> of the Jewes was, a Nationall Church. 3. You grant, that the Officers of particular Churches of a Province, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may meet, as a <hi>Synod,</hi> by an <hi>Ordinance of Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaks of the dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of many particular Iewiſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together in ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, even to the communion of a thouſand Churches, and all of them will have ſuch mutuall care, and yeeld ſuch mutuall help and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if they were all but one Body. The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 56.</note> and there determine, and enjoyne things for all their Churches; and this <hi>Synod</hi> you call, a Church of Churches: Now, are not thoſe Officers, Officers to all thoſe Churches, and may not they be called Nationall Officers, in a candid ſenſe? It is therefore a meere <hi>Logomachy,</hi> to diſpute, whether there be a Nationall Church, or Nationall Officers, or no: But [<hi>the Officers themſelves</hi> (ſay you) <hi>and the Synods themſelves, and all their power, are primarily given to the ſeverall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of particular Congregations, either as the firſt ſubject in whom they are reſident, or as the firſt object, about whom they are converſant,</hi> &amp;c.] Let me firſt tell you, you plainly vary the queſtion, which is, of the <hi>firſt ſubject,</hi> not of the firſt <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>firſt object</hi> of all the Church <hi>Officers,</hi> is not the particular Churches; certainly the <hi>firſt object</hi> of the Apoſtles and Prophets was the generall viſible Church, not any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church: Nay, every <hi>Paſtor</hi> is firſt given to the whole Church, ſecondarily to this or that particular Church as the <hi>object;</hi> as I thinke, I have proved above, at leaſt, you doe not ſufficiently diſprove it: But 3. that the power which a <hi>Synod</hi> puts forth, [<hi>is ſubjectively firſt in the Synod;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Keyes. <hi>p.</hi> 47.</note>] is your owne aſſertion in your 4. propoſition; you did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much forget your ſelfe here, to aſſert the contrary; and thinke to evade, by altering the ſtate of the queſtion, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>firſt object,</hi> for the <hi>firſt ſubject,</hi> or joyning them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when the queſtion is of the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> only. Surely, if the <hi>power</hi> of a Synod be any thing more than the power of a particular Congregation; the particular Congregation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the <hi>firſt ſubject,</hi> in whom the power of the <hi>Synod</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:113181:44"/> is reſident. But when I conſider your firſt propoſition bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I begin to thinke your meaning is, that the Church par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, even without Officers, is the firſt Subject of all Church-power; becauſe 1. ſuch a Church you define in, <hi>The Way,</hi> to be the only inſtituted Church; and ſecondly, you give them power to derive their power upon their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, in chuſing and ordaining them, and then ſending them to a <hi>Synod;</hi> and ſo indeed, they are the firſt Subject, even of the power put forth in the Synod: But if this be not downright <hi>Browniſme,</hi> I confeſſe, I know not what is. Let me but make uſe of your owne <hi>characters</hi> of the firſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all power: <hi>[The firſt ſubject of any power hath it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocally:]</hi> But a particular Congregation of Saints, hath not all Church-offices, and all ſpirituall power reciprocally: For it may be without all Officers: ſo cannot fire, the firſt Subject of heate, be without heate. Againe, take the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond character: <hi>[It firſt putteth forth the exerciſe of that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.]</hi> But ſay I, a particular Congregation without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, doth not firſt put forth the power of an <hi>Officer,</hi> or of a <hi>Synod; ergo,</hi> If you ſay, yet the third will fit it rightly: <hi>[It firſt communicateth that power to others.]</hi> becauſe the Church firſt makes her owne Officers, and then imployes them in the Church or Synod. I aske, whether this be not that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme</hi> which the <hi>Brethren</hi> ſpeake of; giving [<hi>the chiefe, if not the whole of the power into the hands of the people (without their Officers) as if Chriſt had radically and originally eſtated it in the people,</hi> Epiſt. p. 2.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. Propoſ. <hi>[The Apoſtles were the firſt ſubject of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall power.]</hi> But then 1. why doe you not ſay, proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably, that the <hi>Paſtors</hi> are the firſt Subject of Paſtorall power; and the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> of <hi>Ruling power,</hi> &amp;c? 2. If the firſt Subject of all the Church-offices, with all their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113181:44"/> ſpirituall gifts and power, be a particular Congregation, how can you ſay now, that the Apoſtles were the <hi>firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of Apoſtolicall power? Nay rather, in your way, the <hi>particular Congregation,</hi> is the <hi>firſt ſubject,</hi> even of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall power; and the Apoſtles had it by derivation from them; and ſo make the Church the <hi>Queene,</hi> that beſtoweth all theſe Offices upon her Officers; and ſo ſay the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. But to the contrary, its certaine, there were Apoſtles, who had this Apoſtolicall power, before there was any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation; As ſhall appeare in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You ſay, their power ſtood in this; <hi>[That each Apoſtle had in him all miniſteriall power of all the officers of the Church, Paſtors, Teachers, Rulers, Deacons.]</hi> But this is a flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to your firſt propoſition, That a <hi>particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> was the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all the Church-offices and power: There cannot be two <hi>firſt ſubjects,</hi> much leſſe three <hi>firſt ſubjects</hi> of one Adjunct; and yet here you joyne Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts with Apoſtles, and ſay, that <hi>[one Apoſtle or Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, carried about with him the liberty and power of the whole Church; and</hi> ergo, <hi>might alone baptize and cenſure.]</hi> If you ſhould ſay, they received this power from the Church, you ſay, that which jumps with the Browniſts opinion, and that which is apparantly falſe. Take all your 3. <hi>characters</hi> of a <hi>firſt ſubject:</hi> 1. It firſt receiveth that <hi>power.</hi> 2. It firſt puts forth the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of that <hi>power.</hi> 3. It firſt <hi>communicateth</hi> that power to others: They all fall upon the Apoſtles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was any particular Congregation; They firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power from Chriſt; They firſt exerciſed that power; They firſt communicated that power, by making <hi>Paſtors, Elders, Deacons:</hi> Beſides, in your other Tract you ſay, expreſſely as much, or more.<note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 83.</note> 
                  <hi>[One Apoſtle received both
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113181:45"/> the gifts and power of all the Officers of the Church, and might exerciſe them all alone, without the Church.]</hi> Though your <hi>Brethren</hi> that publiſhed that Tract, doe affixe their <hi>Starre</hi> againſt it, which (according to their intimation in their Epiſtle) ſignifies as much as, <hi>Magiſter non tenetur.</hi> And no marvell, for you are not conſtant to your ſelfe: Your firſt and ſecond propoſitions doe directly contradict one another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. [<hi>Apoſtolicall power</hi> (ſay you) <hi>extended it ſelfe to all Churches, as much as to any one; and ſo they were the firſt and laſt ſubject of Apoſtolicall power.]</hi> This ſtill makes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction greater: For how then, could you truly ſay; <hi>[The particular congregation was the firſt ſubject of all Church-power:]</hi> when the power of a particular Congregation extends it ſelfe no further then its owne bounds, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall power extends to all Churches? 2. How can you ſay they were the <hi>laſt ſubject</hi> of all power; when you ſaid afore, The <hi>particular congregation</hi> is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power? And when you ſay here, <hi>[That ample and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall latitude of power, which was conjoyned in them, is now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided even by themſelves, amongſt all the Churches, and all the Officers reſpectively.]</hi> Then it followes 1. That the Church is not the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power; for it is divided by the Apoſtles, amongſt all the Churches. 2. That the Apoſtles were not the <hi>laſt ſubject</hi> of all Apoſtolicall power; for it is left with the Churches and Officers: But ſtill the queſtion is, whom the Apoſtles did betruſt firſt, with the ordinary power of <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons?</hi> The Churches (ſay you) and the Officers reſpectively: But what doe you meane? that one part of that power was given firſt to the Churches; another part, firſt to the Officers? This is not conſentaneous to your firſt propoſition: where you ſay, <hi>[The Church is the firſt ſubject of all Church offices,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113181:45"/> and all Church power:]</hi> Or doe you meane (as you ſhould, if you ſpeake congruouſly) that the Church receives all power firſt, and then diſtributes it among the Officers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively? Then (ſay I) your <hi>middle way,</hi> fals out to be the <hi>extreme</hi> of <hi>Browniſts;</hi> who make the people the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power. But I thinke the truth is; That the Apoſtles betruſted the power of the Officers, not firſt with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but with the Officers themſelves: They, and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, ordained Elders in every City, not the Churches: <hi>Paul</hi> gives <hi>Timothy</hi> a charge, [<hi>to commit that which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of him, to faithfull men, that might be able to teach others alſo,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.2.] To conclude this: You ſaid above, That the <hi>Keyes</hi> were diſtributed into ſeverall hands; the <hi>Key</hi> of Liberty unto the <hi>Brethren;</hi> the <hi>Key</hi> of Authority unto the <hi>Officers;</hi> and is not this a contradiction to what your firſt propoſition doth aſſert; That the <hi>particular</hi> Church of <hi>Brethren,</hi> is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all Church-offices, and of all Church-power, and ſo of the Authority of the <hi>Officers?</hi> conſider it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Propoſ. <hi>[When the Church of a particular congregation, walketh together in the truth and peace, the Brethren are the firſt ſubject of Church liberty, and the Elders thereof, of Church-authority; and both, of all Church-power, needfull to be exerciſed amongſt themſelves.]</hi> This is very <hi>cautelouſly</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, yet not enough to cover your <hi>contradiction.</hi> Either this propoſition is the ſame with the firſt, or elſe it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts it. There you ſaid, that the <hi>particular congregation</hi> of Saints, was the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all the Church-offices, with all their ſpirituall gifts and power: Now you divide this power, between them and the Elders; giving the one Church-liberty, the other, Authority. 2. There is a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for this too; it is but <hi>when they walke in truth and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113181:46"/> Peace:</hi> But if they walke not ſo, what is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all that power? Have not the <hi>Brethren</hi> their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> their <hi>Authority,</hi> as the firſt Subjects, when they differ? If ſo; then your caution is idle, [<hi>when they walke in truth and peace:</hi> If not, then neither of them ſingle, nor both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power needfull to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed amongſt themſelves: And we ſhall heare anon, a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power needfull to be exerciſed amongſt themſelves; <hi>When there are diviſions and factions among them,</hi> page 47. Yet againe, in your other Tract, you give the particular Congregation of <hi>Brethren,</hi> the whole <hi>power,</hi> of chuſing, ordaining Officers, and cenſures of their Officers, if they be hereticall.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Brethren</hi> are the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of Church-liberty, you labour to prove thus: <hi>[By removall of any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſubject, whence they might derive it: Not from their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; for they had power to chuſe their owne Elders: Not from other Churches, for all Churches are equall: Not from a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod; they of</hi> Antioch <hi>borrowed none of their Liberties from Ieruſalem.]</hi> I anſwer; the enumeration is not ſufficient: For though they received it from none of thoſe, yet they might derive it from ſome others; namely, from the <hi>Elders</hi> of other Churches, by whom they were firſt converted to the <hi>Faith:</hi> For the <hi>Liberties</hi> or priviledges that a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath, as diſtinct from <hi>Elders,</hi> comes to them by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their <hi>intereſt,</hi> either in the <hi>Body myſticall,</hi> or <hi>Catholicke viſible Church;</hi> which is in <hi>Order,</hi> before their member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of a particular Congregation: They muſt be <hi>viſible Saints,</hi> before they can gather into a <hi>congregation</hi> of viſible Saints; and every one ſingle hath a <hi>liberty</hi> or priviledge to aſſociate, before they can all be aſſociated: Now thence it followes, that thoſe Elders that firſt converted them did
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113181:46"/> 
                  <hi>virtually</hi> derive that <hi>liberty</hi> or priviledge to them; <hi>Faith</hi> comes by hearing: How ſhall <hi>they heare without a Preacher?</hi> Remember your owne words:<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>[The Key of knowledge (or which is all one the Key of Faith) belongeth to all the faithfull, whether joyned to any particular Church, or no; which argueth, that the key of knowledge is given not only to the Church, but to ſome before they enter into the Church.]</hi> Now who gave them this <hi>key of Faith,</hi> inſtrumentally, but <hi>[the Miniſters by whom they beleeved?]</hi> Therefore, the Church of a particular Congregation, are not the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of Church-liberty; but every particular <hi>Beleever</hi> hath it firſt, and that derived from ſome <hi>Elders.</hi> And certainly, in the firſt <hi>plantation</hi> of Churches, the <hi>Officers, Elders</hi> I meane, were before the Churches themſelves: The <hi>Planters</hi> were before the <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> The Apoſtles being firſt converted and <hi>ordained</hi> by Chriſt himſelfe, were ſent abroad, and converted people, many times ſingle; afterwards, when they were increaſed, they united into Churches. Now, you ſuppoſe the Church to be before the <hi>Elders;</hi> becauſe they chuſe their owne <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> which is not generally true. Though it may be ſo in Churches <hi>planted,</hi> yet not in the firſt <hi>plantation</hi> of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Indeed, in your way, the Churches are before their <hi>Elders,</hi> and doe chuſe and ordaine their <hi>Elders;</hi> but from the beginning it was not ſo: And beſides, <hi>Elders</hi> now, in order of nature, if not in time, are before the Churches, in all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches; being ordained for the moſt part to be <hi>Elders,</hi> before they be <hi>Elders</hi> to this or that particular Church: And though your Churches doe chuſe their <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> yet I hope they doe not make or <hi>ordaine</hi> them <hi>Elders:</hi> but after they are <hi>ordained,</hi> chuſe them to be theirs.<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p</hi> 55.</note> You ſpeake ſometimes of <hi>[tranſlation of an Elder from one Church to another;]</hi> which, in my apprehenſion, implyes him an
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:113181:47"/> 
                  <hi>Elder</hi> before he be tranſlated to another Church: Though I know you are not conſtant to your ſelfe herein; holding it as a principle; <hi>[Elder and flocke are relates:]</hi> and giving the <hi>Brethren,</hi> without any <hi>Officers,</hi> power not only to chuſe, but to ordaine their <hi>Elders;</hi> and ſo your Churches are before their <hi>Elders,</hi> and give them their power, by election and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination; and <hi>Browniſts</hi> doe no more. I would gladly know a reaſon why, if the Churches had power to chuſe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine their owne <hi>Officers,</hi> the Apoſtle ſhould trouble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and them, to ſend <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> to ordaine <hi>Elders</hi> in every City; had it not been eaſier to have written to the Churches to doe it themſelves?</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Elders</hi> are the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of <hi>Rule and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> you endeavour to prove: 1. <hi>[Becauſe the charge of Rule over the Church, is committed to them immediately from Chriſt.]</hi> But this firſt, is contradictory to your firſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which made the <hi>particular congregation,</hi> the <hi>firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of all Church-officers, and all Church-power; and the Church communicates and derives that power to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, chuſing and ordaining them. 2. If the charge of <hi>Rule</hi> be immediately committed to them from Chriſt, how can the Church be the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all power? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles indeed had all their power immediately from Chriſt; but other <hi>Officers</hi> had it immediately from them, and from others intruſted by them, with that power: When you ſay, <hi>[The Office it ſelfe is ordained by Chriſt, though the Elders be choſen to their Office by the Church of Brethren]</hi> You vary the queſtion: For the queſtion is not, who ordaines the <hi>Office;</hi> but who ordaines the <hi>Officers:</hi> Thoſe that the Apoſtles ordained, had their <hi>Office</hi> immediately from Chriſt, but had not their <hi>Ordination</hi> immediately from Chriſt; that was the <hi>priviledge</hi> of the Apoſtles. Now from
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:113181:47"/> whomſoever the <hi>Officers</hi> derive their <hi>Ordination</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, from them immediately they doe derive their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But (ſay you) the <hi>Officers</hi> doe immediately derive their <hi>Ordination</hi> from the Church of <hi>Brethren; ergo,</hi> they derive immediately their Authority from the Church of <hi>Brethren:</hi> And conſequently, the Church of <hi>Brethren</hi> is the firſt ſubject of <hi>authority,</hi> as well as of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and not the <hi>Elders.</hi> Certainly, all your 3 characters of a firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, fall upon the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors. 1. They firſt received their power from Chriſt. 2. They firſt put forth the exerciſe of that power. 3. They firſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated that power to others. You ſay here; [<hi>God hath not given a ſpirit of Rule and Government ordinarily to the greater part of the body of the Brethren; and</hi> ergo, <hi>neither hath he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them the firſt receit of the Key of Authority, to whom he hath not given the gift to imploy it.]</hi> But you give the body of the <hi>Brethren</hi> alone, the firſt receit (and exerciſe too) of the <hi>Key</hi> of Authority, when you give them power to chuſe and ordaine their <hi>Officers</hi> (which <hi>Ordination</hi> is confeſſed by your ſelfe, to be an Act of <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>authority) ergo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 48.</note> you doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contradict your ſelfe; without any poſſibility of <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation,</hi> that I can imagine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. How can the <hi>Brethren</hi> inveſt an <hi>Elder</hi> with <hi>Rule,</hi> if they had not power of <hi>Rule</hi> in themſelves? <hi>Sol. [Partly by chuſing him to that Office, which God hath inveſted with Rule; partly, by ſubjecting themſelves unto him.] Reply</hi> 1. Your firſt reaſon is of no validity; chuſing to an Office, doth not inveſt with the <hi>Rule</hi> of that Office. <hi>Election</hi> gives not an <hi>Office,</hi> but only <hi>nominates</hi> or deſignes a perſon fit for that Office: It is <hi>Ordination</hi> that gives the Office, and the <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>authority</hi> of that Office. The ſeven <hi>Deacons</hi> choſen by the people, were not <hi>Officers,</hi> till the Apoſtles had ordained
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113181:48"/> them: If they were not, then <hi>election</hi> gives no Office, and conſequently, no <hi>authority</hi> belonging to that Office: If they were, then <hi>Ordination</hi> is a meere empty Ceremony; and the <hi>Brethren</hi> doe properly give them <hi>authority,</hi> which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have not to give: Beſides, <hi>election</hi> to this or that place, preſuppoſes (at leaſt ſometimes) the party inveſted with <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> before (as in the caſe of tranſlation of an Elder from one Church to another) and only admits him to the exerciſe of it; <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> as they ſpeake. 2. Your ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is as weake as the former; <hi>[Becauſe they profeſſe their ſubjection to him:]</hi> This cannot inveſt him with the <hi>Rule,</hi> ſuch as we ſpeake of. Suppoſe a company of <hi>Brethren</hi> chuſe a <hi>gifted Brother</hi> to propheſie to them, and profeſſe their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to him in the Lord; doth this inveſt him with <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of an <hi>Elder,</hi> to rule over them? If it doe; then <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is a thing not neceſſary, either by the <hi>Brethren</hi> or <hi>Elders;</hi> (yet by and by we ſhall heare you require <hi>Ordination of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> to make a compleat <hi>Elder:</hi>) If it doe not, then you have not ſatisfied the objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. The Church is Chriſts <hi>Spouſe, Wife, Queene; ergo,</hi> ſhe hath the <hi>Keyes of Rule</hi> at her girdle. <hi>Sol. [There is a great difference between Queens and poore mens Wives: The firſt have their Officers for every buſineſſe, and ſervice; and ſo no Key left in their hands of any Office, but of Liberty, to call for what they want, according to the Kings Royall allowance: But poore mens wives, that have no Officers, may carry the keyes at their owne girdles.] Reply.</hi> This anſwer overthroweth it ſelfe: For 1. the <hi>liberty</hi> which you grant this <hi>Queene,</hi> the Church, is part of the power of the <hi>Keyes,</hi> and a great part too (if not the whole) <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>chuſe and ordaine her owne Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> and to cenſure them offending; which no <hi>Queene</hi> is allowed to doe; <hi>ergo,</hi> the Church hath the <hi>Keyes</hi> at her gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:113181:48"/> which a <hi>Queen</hi> hath not. 2. You ſay, and that truly, <hi>[The Queene hath only a liberty to call for what ſhe wants;]</hi> but hath no power to make her owne Officers. The <hi>King</hi> doth that by ſome <hi>Officers</hi> deputed by himſelfe for that purpoſe, to ſet them apart, to give them their <hi>commiſsion</hi> or oath, &amp;c. Juſt ſo it is in the Church: All the <hi>Officers</hi> are given to the Church, <hi>objectivè,</hi> for the good and benefit of the Church; but they have no <hi>power</hi> to make and ordaine their owne <hi>Officers,</hi> but only to call upon them for that allowance which the <hi>King</hi> of the Church hath granted them. 3. If poore mens wives may carry the <hi>Keyes</hi> of any Office at their owne girdles, when their husbands have no <hi>Officers;</hi> you ſeeme to give a greater honour and <hi>liberty</hi> to them, then to Queenes or Ladyes; and withall, you give us leave to inferre, That Churches that have no <hi>Officers</hi> of their owne, are in better caſe than thoſe that have: They that have <hi>Officers,</hi> have put the <hi>Keyes</hi> in their <hi>Officers</hi> hands: They that have none, may and doe weare them at their owne gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles; which if you affirme (as you often doe) I dare affirme it to be <hi>flat Browniſme,</hi> and not the <hi>middle way,</hi> you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. The whole body naturall, is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all the naturall power; as ſight is firſt in the body, before in the eye. <hi>Soil. [It is not in the myſticall, as with the naturall body; there the faculties are inexiſtent, not ſo here.] Reply</hi> 1. This againe contradicts your firſt propoſition; where you ſay, a particular Church is the <hi>firſt ſubject</hi> of all Church-offices and power: And here you ſay, they are not <hi>actually inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent,</hi> how then is it the firſt Subject, ſeeing <hi>accidentis eſſe, eſt ineſſe?</hi> 2. If the Church chuſe out of themſelves, <hi>Officers gifted,</hi> are not they then inexiſtent? 3. You confeſſe they are in ſome caſes: [<hi>unleſſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>ſome of them have all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:113181:49"/> the gifts of all the Officers, which often they have not.</hi>] True, but oftentimes they have, either <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> or men fit to be <hi>Preſbyters;</hi> And then you anſwer not the objection: And if they have <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> before they chuſe them to be <hi>theirs,</hi> (as your words ſeeme to import they may) then they doe not inveſt them with <hi>power of Elders,</hi> by chuſing them, as formerly you ſeemed to aſſert. Laſtly, you ſay; [<hi>If the power of the Preſbytery were given to a particular Church of Brethren, as ſuch,</hi> primò &amp; per ſe, <hi>then it would be found in every particular Church of Brethren.</hi>] But ſay I, you aſſert both the <hi>Antecedent</hi> in the firſt propoſition; <hi>[Every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation is the firſt ſubject of all Church power;]</hi> and the <hi>conſequence,</hi> when you ſay; <hi>[Every particular Church hath power to chuſe, ordaine, and cenſure;]</hi> ergo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. The Government is mixt of <hi>Monarchy, Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy,</hi> and <hi>Democracy; ergo,</hi> the people have ſome power in Government. <hi>Sol.</hi> Your firſt anſwer ſeemes to yeeld the thing: [<hi>In a large ſenſe, Authority may be acknowledged in the people: As</hi> 1. <hi>when a man acteth by counſell, he is then Lord of his owne action.]</hi> But thats nothing to the objection. The people of the <hi>Aſsizes</hi> act by <hi>counſell,</hi> in approving the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: If you grant the Brethren no more, you mocke them, and grant them nothing. 2. But you grant them far more; [<hi>Election of Officers, concurrence in cenſures, determination of Synodall acts,</hi> &amp;c. (you might have added, <hi>Ordination,</hi> and then you had given them full Authority) <hi>by theſe they have a great ſtroke or power in ordering Church affaires.</hi>] A great ſtroke indeed; as full Authority as you give the <hi>Elders:</hi> And this you grant, when you give your reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and would allow them only <hi>liberty: [For</hi> (ſay you) <hi>no act of the peoples power or liberty is binding, unleſſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Preſbytery concurre with it.</hi>] No more doth any
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:113181:49"/> act of the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> bind, unleſſe the power of the people joyne with it. So ſay your Prefacers, <hi>Epiſt. p.</hi> 4. So ſay your ſelf; when you allow them ſuch a power, as the want there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of retards the ſentence. But why doe you darken your owne meaning, by ſuch ambiguous anſwers? when you grant the Government to be <hi>democraticall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, 100</note> but not <hi>[meerely democraticall;]</hi> yea, (if I underſtand any thing) you make it as <hi>meerely democraticall,</hi> as <hi>Browniſts</hi> themſelves, when you give them power, without any <hi>Officers,</hi> to chuſe, ordaine, cenſure, even Officers themſelves, as we have often told you. I pray Sir, when the Brethren ordaine, or cenſure Officers, without a <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> doth not that act of theirs properly bind? It muſt, or it is meere vanity, having no <hi>Preſbytery</hi> to joyne with them: And if ſo, is not this properly Authority without more adoe?</p>
               <p>But you would prove Elders to be the firſt Subject of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, from removall of other Subjects: <hi>[They have is not from the Elders of other Churches; or from a Synod: All Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and all Elders are equall.]</hi> But 1. This is apparently falſe in the Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure way: For the <hi>Elders</hi> of the firſt Churches were ordained by the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, who were Elders of all Churches; and as Elders, not as Apoſtles, ordained Elders, and ſo gave them their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity immediately from Chriſt. 2. Your reaſon, becauſe they are all equall, will hurt your ſelfe: For if that be a good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they cannot derive it from <hi>Elders</hi> of the other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, becauſe they are equall, it is much more ſtrong againſt you; they cannot derive it from the people, who are their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours: Beſides, by this rule, <hi>Elders</hi> of their own Church cannot ordaine any <hi>Elders</hi> to that Church, when they want; for they are all <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll:</hi> But by your favour, he that is to receive the <hi>Office,</hi> and with it, the Authority of an <hi>Elder,</hi> is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:113181:50"/> inferiour to thoſe Elders who are to ordaine him; for <hi>the leſſer is bleſſed of the greater:</hi> though when he is once ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he be their equall: And though the Elders of a <hi>Synod</hi> be equall, ſingly conſidered; yet joyntly, they are ſuperiour to any one ſingle, and have more Authority than he hath; or elſe, all you ſpeake of <hi>Synods</hi> is but vanity: But if they have not their Authority derived from <hi>Elders</hi> of other Churches, nor from <hi>Synods;</hi> nor from the Elders of their owne Church, becauſe they are all equall; either they muſt derive it from the people, or they have none of all; and ſo the people have as much Authority as any Elder of them all; yea, in your way more.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third branch of the third Propoſ. <hi>[Both Elders and Brethren together, are the firſt ſubject of all power, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full amongſt themſelves]</hi> You prove it by inſtance, 1. <hi>[In point of Ordination: which is compleat, when the people have choſen him, and the Preſbytery of the Church have laid their hands upon him.]</hi> But 1. I obſerve, that here you make <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> an Act of Authority, and place it in the Elders; <hi>ergo,</hi> either the Brethren cannot ordaine <hi>Elders,</hi> which yet you ſay they may; or elſe, they have Authority, which yet you ſeeme to deny. 2. Some of your <hi>Brethren</hi> here, hold <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> to be nothing but a ceremoniall ſolemnity, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Miniſters calling, is (ſay they) in the peoples <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; ergo,</hi> either Authority is in the people, who give the ſubſtance; and <hi>liberty</hi> only in the <hi>Elders,</hi> who give but the ceremony: or the calling of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> is compleat without <hi>Ordination;</hi> and yet you require <hi>Ordination</hi> to the integrity of it: But if the Brethren may ordaine without their Officers, then they alone are the firſt Subject not of <hi>Liberty</hi> only, but of <hi>Authority</hi> alſo: And ſo this Propoſition is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:113181:50"/>
               <p>A ſecond Argument, is taken from <hi>[their independent and indiſpenſable power in Church cenſures, which are ratified in Heaven,]</hi> The ſame anſwer will ſerve to this alſo: For firſt, the Brethren alone without Elders (ſay you) may cenſure, and if rightly done, it is <hi>indiſpenſable,</hi> not to be reverſed by any power on Earth, becauſe ratified in Heaven; <hi>ergo,</hi> they are the firſt ſubject of all Church-power needfull within themſelves. 2. And that the rather, if they can ordaine El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders too; for then the Elders derive their power from them. 3. But ſuppoſe, (which is poſſible enough) the Brethren and Elders erre in their cenſure of a member, is not the cenſure then reverſible? I aske, by whom? if all power needfull for themſelves be within themſelves, what ſhall the wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged party doe? Is he remedileſly miſerable? If it be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable, and reverſible, it muſt be by ſome other Church or <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsis,</hi> &amp;c. But then, a Congregation of <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> are not the firſt ſubject of all power needfull amongſt themſelves. If you ſay, you meane, when they <hi>walke in truth and peace;</hi> you ſhould yet have told us what the party muſt doe, when they walke not in truth and peace; And if they have not a power to right a wronged party, they have not all power needfull to be exerciſed among themſelves.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Objections</hi> by you brought and anſwered, rather concerne the <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> than the <hi>Preſbyteriall</hi> way, at leaſt, ſome of them, only 2 or 3 may be vindicated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj</hi> 1. To tell the Church, is to tell the Presbytery of the Church. <hi>Sol. [We deny not, the offence is to be told to the Preſbytery; yet not to them, as the Church, but as the guides of the Church.] Reply.</hi> This is partly to yeeld the cauſe: For you grant that the buſineſſe is to be told firſt to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; [<hi>who if upon hearing the cauſe, and examining the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, they find it ripe for publicke cenſure, they are then to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:113181:51"/> propound it to the Church,</hi> &amp;c. And you grant the people no more, but <hi>[conſent to the judgement and ſentence of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.]</hi> The Presbytery alſo are to admoniſh the party au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively; and if he will not heare them, to paſſe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon him; <hi>ergo,</hi> the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is the Church there meant, and not the <hi>people,</hi> who neither admoniſh, nor cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure authoritatively, but only diſcerne the nature of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and conſent unto the ſentence: The Church there meant, is that part of the Church, which the party refuſes to heare; but he refuſes to heare the Presbytery, who doe ſpeake to him, not the people, who doe not authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſpeake to him; <hi>ergo,</hi> to tell the Church, is to tell the Presbytery. <hi>Sol.</hi> 2. <hi>[The Church is never put for the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery alone in the New Teſtament.] Reply</hi> 1. This is to beg the queſtion: we ſay, it muſt ſo be underſtood in this place, and you doe not diſprove it. Nay 2. you rather confirme it by your anſwer to the firſt objection; Our Saviour alludes to the <hi>Church-cenſure</hi> in the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church: But there the Church cenſuring, was the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> a Court of the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; <hi>ergo,</hi> as ſhall further appeare in the next.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. In the old Teſtament, the Congregation is often put for the Elders and Rulers of the Church. <hi>Sol. [Not alone, but ſitting in the preſence of the Congregation.] Reply:</hi> That is enough for our purpoſe: For we doe not deny, but the people might be preſent, to heare things then, and ſo they may now: But if the <hi>Elders</hi> be called the Church, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the people, when they ſate in preſence of the people, much more may they be called the Church, when they ſit alone. And to that cuſtome of the Jewes (your ſelfe acknowledge in anſwer to the firſt objection doth our Saviour allude; when he ſayes, <hi>[Tell the Church]</hi> But the cuſtome of the Jewes, was to tell the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:113181:51"/> the people. And whereas you ſay: <hi>[If a ſentence illegall was paſſed by them, the people did ſometimes proteſt againſt it, ſometime refuſe to execute it, and the ſame they might and ought to doe, at any time, in like caſes.]</hi> Though this may be true, when things are done in an illegall way, and evidently illegall (as the inſtances are) yet it is a dangerous aſſertion to Government; for under that pretence, people will take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to make void any ſentence, if they conceive it but ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. By Church, he meant a <hi>Synod,</hi> or <hi>Claſsis</hi> of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of many Churches. [<hi>Sol.</hi> 1. <hi>We find not any where that a Church is put for a Synod of Presbyteries.] Reply:</hi> The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is of this place, and you muſt not beg, that it is not here meant of a Synod of Presbyteries. If it be meant but of the <hi>Congregationall Presbytery,</hi> it quite deſtroyes the power of the people: But we doe not ſay, it is directly meant of a <hi>Synod</hi> of Presbyteries, but by a juſt conſequence: If a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall <hi>Preſbytery</hi> be here meant (as we thinke it is) to reclaime a particular offending party in a Congregation: Then by proportion, here is meant a <hi>Synod</hi> of Presbyteries, when a whole Church erres, or is hereticall; or elſe, Chriſt hath not provided ſo well for a whole Church, as for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon. And thirdly, we cannot ſee a reaſon, why a Church may not be taken for a Synod of Presbyteries, as well as a Synod may be called <hi>[A Church of Churches,]</hi> as it is by your ſelfe, <hi>page</hi> 49. <hi>[A Congregation of Churches, a Church of Churches; for what is a Synod, but a Church of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?]</hi> ſo you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 2. <hi>[As a Congregation cannot reach the removall of all offences: ſo it may be ſaid, that it were not fit to trouble Synode with every offence; and when they doe meet, they may erre alſo, and ſo may a generall Councell, and ſo no remedy for them.</hi>]</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:113181:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 1. We doe not ſay that <hi>Synods</hi> are to be troubled with every ſmall offence, or to take the buſineſſe of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation out of their hands; but only with greater matters, and when the <hi>Congregationall Preſbytery</hi> cannot end them, or is ſo bad it will not. 2. <hi>Synods</hi> and <hi>Councels</hi> may erre, but not ſo eaſily as a particular Congregation: And <hi>alicubi ſiſtendum,</hi> there muſt be an end of purſuit, and referre the buſineſſe to the judgement of Jeſus Chriſt, the King of the Church. As in caſe of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the higheſt Tribunall that we have, they may erre; and if they doe, private perſons muſt ſit downe, or <hi>appeale</hi> to the next. But that is a ſtrange aſſertion, [<hi>That it was not the purpoſe of Chriſt to preſcribe a rule for the removall of all offences out of the Church; but only ſuch private and leſſe hainous, as grow notorious by obſtinacy: For if they be publicke, the Apoſtle gives another rule, to caſt ſuch a perſon out of all communion, without that admonition,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>Reply:</hi> The Apoſtle did not meane abſolutely, that they ſhould caſt out the <hi>inceſtuous</hi> perſon; but ſuppoſing his impenitency, and obſtinacy, to give ſatisfaction: For I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine, that the Apoſtle would have an humbled, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent offender caſt out of all communion; And you know, it is ſuppoſed by many learned <hi>Divines,</hi> the man was not excommunicated, but upon the charge, reproofe, and admonition, yeelded and eſcaped the cenſure: Of which, more by and by.</p>
               <p>But (ſay you) <hi>What if the whole Preſbytery offend? or ſuch a party as will draw a faction in the Church? The readieſt courſe is to bring the matter to a Synod</hi>] But you have preſcribed two other <hi>remedies</hi> elſewhere: 1. The Brethren may <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw;</hi> or 2. they may proceed to <hi>cenſure</hi> their whole Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, that is, (I thinke) to <hi>excommunicate</hi> them; why then ſhould they trouble themſelves with a <hi>Synod,</hi> which is hardly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:113181:52"/> procured? <hi>If the Congregation be found faithfull and willing to remove an offence, by due cenſure, why ſhould the offence be called up to more publick Iudicature, and the plaiſter made broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than the ſore?</hi>] They are your owne words, <hi>page</hi> 42. I forbeare the other objections.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>From the practiſe and example of the Church of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.] Obj.</hi> This was the act of <hi>Paul,</hi> no act of judiciall authority in the Church, but rather of ſubjection to his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, &amp;c. <hi>Sol. [The judgement of</hi> Paul, <hi>was not a judiciall ſentence, delivering him to Satan; but a judicious doctrine, and inſtruction, teaching them what to doe in that caſe.] Reply:</hi> Thus you may evade that other Text, where yet you grant, that <hi>Paul</hi> alone did excommunicate <hi>Alexander,</hi> and juſtifie his doing of it, as <hi>[having in him the power of the whole Church; and when abſent from the Church, or party, he might uſe it.]</hi> Are not the places paralell? I have delivered him to Satan; and I have judged already, that ſuch an one be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to Satan: Elſe it might be ſaid, <hi>Paul</hi> did not deliver <hi>Alexander</hi> to Satan, but only judged it doctrinally, that the Church ought to excommunicate him; And that the Church did, by a <hi>juridicall</hi> ſentence, deliver the inceſtuous perſon to Satan, is not evident (as I ſaid afore) but rather, that hearing of the Apoſtles ſentence decreed againſt him, he repented, and ſo the execution was ſtayed. <hi>Sufficient un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the man is the rebuke of many,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.6] As for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of him, it might be only <hi>brotherly,</hi> by way of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as offended by him, not <hi>juridicall</hi> by way of authority: For the brethren (by your owne confeſſion) had only Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, not Authority, and <hi>ergo,</hi> could not authoritatively for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, as nor <hi>authoritatively</hi> bind him: The ſame power binds and looſes: But the <hi>Elders</hi> only did or could authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively bind; <hi>ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:113181:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Some in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did it; <hi>viz.</hi> the Presbytery. <hi>Sol. [It is apparent by the Text, that the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren concurred, and that with ſome act of power;</hi> viz. <hi>ſuch power as the want of putting it forth, retarded the ſentence and the putting it forth, was requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſite to the adminiſtration of the ſentence.] Reply:</hi> This is not evident in the Text; yea, if ſuch power be in the <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſurely it is more than <hi>liberty,</hi> it is direct <hi>authority; viz.</hi> a <hi>negative vote,</hi> to retard the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which is as much as the <hi>Elders</hi> have: If you meane only a <hi>judgement of diſcretion,</hi> and a withdrawing, to execute the ſentence, it is true, that liberty they have, a <hi>rationall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> or diſſent; but that is rather a <hi>paſsive,</hi> than an <hi>active</hi> concurrence to the ſentence. But the queſtion is, whether the ſentence be null, if they will not concurre to it: If ſo, then the Apoſtles own ſentence might have been nullified, when he delivered this party, or <hi>Alexander</hi> to Satan; and he could not ſay, I have delivered him unto Satan: For it was in the peoples power (and a <hi>liberty,</hi> you ſay, <hi>purchaſed for them by Chriſt</hi>) to retard or ſpeed the ſentence. Not one of your reaſons prove, that the <hi>Brethren</hi> concurred <hi>actively</hi> to the ſentence: For 1. the whole Church might (and were) reproved, for not <hi>mourning,</hi> and for not <hi>withdrawing,</hi> for their parts; not for not ſentencing of him. 2. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement was directed to the Church, when gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet not to all alike; the <hi>preſence</hi> of the Brethren, the <hi>ſentence</hi> of the <hi>Elders:</hi> Many things are ſo directed to a whole Church, which yet muſt reſpectively be executed. As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, when you are all gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, I will that there be preaching and adminiſtration of <hi>Sacraments;</hi> doth this command concerne <hi>actively</hi> the Brethren? 3. The Apoſtles words doe not declare this act of theirs to be a <hi>judiciall</hi> act: when he ſayes, <hi>[Doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:113181:53"/> judge them that are within?]</hi> Even this firſt may be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>Officers;</hi> and ſecondly, it is by your ſelfe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcretion, not of authority (of which we ſpeake.) A <hi>judgement</hi> of diſcretion, is allowed all the people at an <hi>Aſsizes;</hi> but this hath no <hi>power</hi> at all in it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called: And truly, if the Apoſtles words carry any colour of <hi>judgement</hi> in the Brethren, it may ſeeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a judgement of <hi>authority,</hi> rather than of <hi>diſcretion;</hi> ſo he gives them more than you dare plead for; though not more than, I feare, they will ere long uſurpe. 4. It is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the <hi>Brethren</hi> may and muſt forgive him, as well as the <hi>Elders,</hi> but not with one and the ſame kind of <hi>forgiveneſſe.</hi> The people at an Aſſizes, doe in their <hi>judgement of diſcretion,</hi> acquit the party whom the <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Iury</hi> doe acquit, with the judgement of Authority. What poore and weak proofes are theſe, for a matter of ſuch moment? as eaſily denyed, as affirmed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. <hi>Corinth</hi> was a Presbyteriall Church. <hi>Sol. [No ſuch thing appeares.] Reply:</hi> It more than probably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, it being a <hi>Mother-City,</hi> where God had much people, and they had many <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent gifts (as you gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) it is not likely therefore they had but one Congregation: And if there were many, it may as probably be ſaid, that this command was directed to the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of ſeverall Congregations, met together, as the contrary can by you be proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg</hi> 4. [<hi>From the guilt of offence which lyeth upon every Church, when any offence committed by their members, lyeth uncenſured as on</hi> Pergamus, Thyatira, &amp;c.] <hi>Sol.</hi> It doth not appeare that thoſe Churches were each, but one ſingle Congregation; but of ſome of them the contrary; as <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which had many <hi>Elders,</hi> and much people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:113181:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:113181:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:113181:55"/> &amp;c. And beſides, I deſire you would call to mind, your owne expoſition of ſome of thoſe Texts; when it is ſaid, <hi>[To the Angell of ſuch a Church;]</hi> that is, ſay the <hi>Prelaticall</hi> party, <hi>To the Biſhop:</hi> you anſwer; <hi>Angell</hi> is put for <hi>Angels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The way, <hi>p.</hi> 49.</note> a company of <hi>Elders; [Not a ſingle perſon, but the whole company of the Miniſters of the Church, (the whole Preſbytery of perſons, more than one), as is evident, by his ſpeech unto them as unto many; unto you, and ſome of you,</hi> &amp;c.] whence theſe 3. things may be collected: 1. That the <hi>guilt</hi> is not imputed to the whole Church, but to the Angell of ſuch a Church; that is, (ſay you) the <hi>Miniſters;</hi> which quite deſtroyes your Argument. 2. That theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> were a whole <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> the whole company of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church; therefore its very probable, there were more Congregations than one, in each of thoſe Churches, and ſo we find <hi>Preſbyteriall,</hi> not <hi>Independent</hi> Churches. 3. That the Church is ſometime taken for the Presbytery of the Church, which afore you have denyed: However, I pray conſider, that the <hi>Brethren</hi> are never called the Angels of the Church; nor yet are the <hi>Ruling-Elders</hi> any where cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Angels, but the Miniſters only, as you call theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: which makes it more than probable, that it is ſpoken to a Presbyteriall Church, the Miniſters of ſeverall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, even according to your owne expoſition; at leaſt, to the Presbytery of each Congregation, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes your aſſertion, that the <hi>Brethren</hi> have any intereſt in the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Keyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Propoſ. <hi>[In caſe a particular Church be diſturbed with error, or ſcandall, and the ſame maintained by a faction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. Now a Synod of Churches, or of their Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, is the firſt ſubject of that power and authority, whereby errour is judicially convinced and condemned, the truth ſearched
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:113181:55"/> out, and determined, and the way of truth and peace declared, and impoſed upon the Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Propoſition you undertake to make good by two Arguments: Firſt, [<hi>From the want of power in ſuch a Church, to paſſe a binding ſentence; becauſe the promiſe of binding and looſing is made to a Church:</hi> 1. <hi>not erring;</hi> 2. <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth,</hi> 18.17, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In anſwer hereunto, I will not ſay, That this Argument proves not the propoſition; for it proves indeed, that a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church is not the firſt Subject of this power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but it doth not prove that a <hi>Synod</hi> is: But this I ſay, that by this way of arguing, a Church can ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have power to bind or looſe, when there is not an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall agreement,</hi> which how rarely it happens, experience tels us now, and will doe more hereafter, in your owne Churches: Few Churches there are, that ſo walke together in peace and truth, that there is no diſagreeing party amongſt them; therefore that <hi>power</hi> is ſeldome in their hands, but upon every difference or faction amongſt them, their power reverts to a <hi>Synod;</hi> and ſo a <hi>Synod</hi> muſt be called (which is not eaſily done) and troubled with every difference of a Congregation; which you impute (unjuſtly) as a fault, upon the <hi>Preſbyteriall</hi> way. 2. You have otherwiſe determined in <hi>the way.</hi> Suppoſe the whole Presbytery be in an errour or ſcandall (as they may) ſhall the faction now deveſt the <hi>Brethren</hi> of their power and authority, to cenſure and caſt them out? which you have fully given them there, and here doe ſeem to take away. 3. You mitigate the buſineſſe much; when you ſay, <hi>[A Synod of Churches is the firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that power, whereby errour is convinced,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruth and peace declared and impoſed on the Church.</hi>] For all this is only a <hi>doctrinall declaration,</hi> and impoſition,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:113181:56"/> not <hi>authoritatively,</hi> by way of <hi>juriſdiction.</hi> The <hi>cenſure</hi> you reſerve to the Congregation, where you had placed it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But what if the <hi>Synod</hi> of Churches erre or diſagree, &amp; there be a faction alſo amongſt them? you will know your owne words: <hi>[An erring, or diſagreeing Church binds not.]</hi> So all will come to nothing: The cenſure of the <hi>Synod</hi> binds not; for they can but declare what is truth: The cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>particular Church</hi> binds not; for they are in a faction: ſo you give the <hi>Brethren</hi> a power, and preſently take it away againe. If then a <hi>conſiderable party</hi> fall into errour or faction, by variance, they preſently loſe (like the Bee her ſting) their power of binding and looſing; and if this be but once knowne (as it cannot be hid) how eaſie is it for any <hi>Delinquent</hi> to make a party, or faction, and ſo eſcape all binding cenſure; ſeeing neither the Church erring, or at variance, nor a <hi>Synod</hi> hath any binding power?</p>
               <p>Your ſecond Argument, is, [<hi>From the patterne,</hi> Acts 15.1. &amp;c. <hi>When there grew errour and faction in the Church of</hi> Antioch, <hi>they determine not the caſe, but referred it to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders.</hi>] But firſt, the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> did only <hi>doctrinally</hi> declare the truth; they did not cenſure the <hi>erring Brethren</hi> (ſo you pleaded above) but referred that to the Church of <hi>Antioch.</hi> 2. If <hi>declaration</hi> had been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> needed not to have ſent ſo farre as <hi>Ieruſalem; Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were able enough to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> the truth at home; and ſo, that particular Church, though erring and at variance, was the firſt ſubject of that power, here given to a <hi>Synod.</hi> 3. You miſlay the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; when you ſay, <hi>As in the caſe of an offence of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brother, perſiſted in, the matter is at laſt judged in a church, which is a Congregation of the faithfull: ſo in the offence of a Church, the matter is at laſt judged in a congregation of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:113181:56"/> &amp;c.] For the <hi>judgement</hi> is not of the ſame kind, but you doe meerely <hi>aequivocate</hi> with us. The <hi>judgement</hi> of the Church upon a <hi>Brother,</hi> is <hi>juridicall,</hi> even by way of <hi>cenſure,</hi> of <hi>excommunication:</hi> But the judgement of a <hi>Synod</hi> is only <hi>doctrinall</hi> and declarative. If you grant any more, you and we are agreed.</p>
               <p>Before I conclude this propoſition, I only animadvert theſe few things: 1. That you grant the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Acts 15.1. to have been a <hi>formall Synod,</hi> wherein your Diſciples here doe diſcent from you, as appeares in their Epiſtle; and call it only a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation,</hi> by way of <hi>Arbitration:</hi> To which <hi>Arbitration,</hi> it ſeemes the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> was not bound to ſtand; for they did not (for ought appeares) promiſe or bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtand to their <hi>arbitrement;</hi> nor might they ſo bind themſelves (by your <hi>doctrine,</hi> and theirs too) for that were <hi>[to give away their priviledge purchaſed by the bloud of Chriſt.]</hi> 2. You yeeld alſo,<note place="margin">The Keyes, <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note> that the Apoſtles did not act here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as Apoſtles, and determine the matter by Apoſtolicall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; but as <hi>Elders,</hi> in an ordinary way, as the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the buſineſſe proves, as you well obſerve: Yet your <hi>Schollers</hi> here, ſubmit not to your <hi>doctrine,</hi> as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in their <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> though they neither ſhew any reaſon for it, nor confute yours. 3. You call a <hi>Synod</hi> a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Churches <hi>(for what is a Synod but a Church of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches)</hi> and yet deny, that a <hi>Preſbytery of Churches</hi> is ever called a Church. 4. You ſay: <hi>The Elders there (at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem) <hi>were not a few, the Beleevers in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>being many thouſands.</hi>] Therefore, ſay wee, they were more than could meet together in one place, and yet called but one Church: whence we may inferre, There was not an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:113181:57"/> Church</hi> of one, but a <hi>Preſbyteriall</hi> Church, of many Congregations. Laſtly, you ſay; <hi>[This patterne plainly ſheweth to whom the Key of Authority is committed, when there groweth offence and difference in a Church.]</hi> But the <hi>Key</hi> of Authority (if you remember what you ſaid above) hath this power in it, as to <hi>adminiſter</hi> the Seales, ſo to <hi>bind</hi> an obſtinate offender under <hi>excommunication;</hi> and to releaſe and forgive him upon repentance. Grant but your <hi>Synod</hi> of Churches, ſuch a <hi>Key</hi> of Authority, to <hi>bind</hi> an offending party, or Church, and to releaſe them upon repentance, and the matter is at an end. But if you grant no more, but a <hi>doctrinall</hi> declarative power, you grant but what every Paſtor ſingle hath. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be the <hi>Key</hi> of Authority, given by our Saviour to the Church, let every indifferent Reader judge.</p>
               <p>And now you come to your Corollaries, concerning the <hi>Independency</hi> of Churches, to ſhew how they are, or are not <hi>Independent:</hi> Wherein, I purpoſe not to follow you; and that for this reaſon; becauſe, for the moſt part, you doe but repeate what you have ſaid before: You ſay, your ſelfe, <hi>[You take the firſt Subject, and the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Subject to be all one.]</hi> Therefore, ſay I, if the Church of a particular Congregation be not the <hi>firſt Subject</hi> of all Church-power, as is evinced above, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it the <hi>Independent</hi> Subject of that power. I have only ſome things to obſerve in your ſecond Corollarie, and then I ſhall conclude: You ſay, [<hi>The eſtabliſhment of pure Religion, and the Reformation of corruptions in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, doe much concerne the civill peace: If Religion be corrupted; there will be warre in the gates,</hi> Judges 5.8. <hi>and no peace to him that commeth in, or goeth out,</hi> 2 Chron.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:113181:57"/> 15.3, 5, 6. <hi>But where Religion rejoyceth, the civill State flouriſheth.</hi>] And this you truly refer to the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; <hi>[partly by commanding, and by ſtirring up the Churches and Miniſters thereof, to goe about it, in their ſpirituall way: partly alſo, by civill puniſhments upon the wilfull oppoſers and diſturbers of the ſame.]</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I deſire to know, 1. By what Authority our <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> here in <hi>Old-England,</hi> having not only Chriſtian Magiſtrates, covenanting to reforme; but alſo, calling and commanding an Aſſembly of <hi>Divines,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme according to the Word, doe take upon them to ſet up, and eſtabliſh a forme of Church-Government of their owne, before they have demonſtrated it to be the way of God; to the great diſturbance of the peace, both of Church and State? 2. I doe demand alſo, why many of your <hi>diſciples</hi> here, plead for a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> of all Religions (which you will not tollerate in <hi>New-England</hi>) which they call <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>conſcience,</hi> and the proſecution of ſuch diſturbers, they call <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution:</hi> When as they may heare you ſay, <hi>[It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Magiſtrate to puniſh the wilfull oppoſers and diſturbers of Reformation:]</hi> And more then that, you tell them; [<hi>Of the Times of the New Teſtament it is propheſied, that in ſome caſes, capitall puniſhment ſhall proceed againſt falſe Prophets, and that by procurement of their neareſt kindred,</hi> Zach. 13.3. <hi>And the execution thereof, is deſcribed,</hi> Rev. 16.4. to 7. <hi>Where the rivers and fountaines of waters (that is, the Prieſts and Ieſuits, that conveigh the Religion of the Sea of</hi> Rome, <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Countries) are turned to bloud, that is, have bloud given them to drinke by the civill Magiſtrate.]</hi> Does
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:113181:58"/> this hold true only againſt Prieſts and Jeſuits: and are all other <hi>erroneous, ſchiſmaticall, blaſphemous</hi> Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to be tolerated? I leave them to conſider it, and you and them to reconcile this and other your many differences and contradictions amongſt your ſelves: And when you are well agreed in the <hi>way,</hi> we ſhall conſider how farre you agree with the <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 7. l. 22. <hi>reade</hi> offender, (and often, after) p. 23. l. laſt r. inſtitution. p. 24. l. 4. <hi>r.</hi> inſtitution. p. 25. l. 16. <hi>r.</hi> for. p. 26. l. 26. for. 1. <hi>r.</hi> 15. p. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 23. r. except. p. 32. l. 15. <hi>r.</hi> whom. p. 34. l. laſt but one, <hi>r.</hi> Counſell. p. 35. l. 8. <hi>r.</hi> Presbyters. p. 45. l. 17. put out the ſecond (in) p. 53. l. laſt, for And, r. from. p. 55. l. 2. for feare, <hi>r.</hi> heare. p. 76. l. 10. for of, <hi>r.</hi> at.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113181:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
